<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Death considr'd as a door to a life of glory penn'd for the comfort of serious mourners, and occasion'd by the funerals of several friends, particularly one who dy'd at Easter, and of the author's own funeral in atecessum.</title>
            <author>Pierce, Thomas, 1622-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28111</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8199439</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204239</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264207955</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2175</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08199439</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28111)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204239)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1237:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Death considr'd as a door to a life of glory penn'd for the comfort of serious mourners, and occasion'd by the funerals of several friends, particularly one who dy'd at Easter, and of the author's own funeral in atecessum.</title>
                  <author>Pierce, Thomas, 1622-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>126 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the Author's private use,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1690?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Death.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Future life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204239:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204239:2"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:204239:2"/> DEATH Consider'd as a DOOR TO A Life of Glory.</p>
            <p>PENN'D For the COMFORT of Serious MOURNERS, AND Occasion'd by the <hi>Funerals</hi> of several <hi>Friends;</hi> Particularly of one who Dy'd at <hi>Easter:</hi> AND OF The <hi>Author</hi>'s own Funeral in <hi>Antecessum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the <hi>Author</hi>'s private use.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204239:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204239:3"/>
            <head>DEATH consider'd as a DOOR TO A Life of Glory.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>The INTRODUCTION.</head>
               <p>§. 1. LOoking out for a fit subject of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation at a Funeral, I saw it had been the great Wisdom of the Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished Church of <hi>England,</hi> (than which I knew nothing Wiser, and whose Appointments I ever thought it my greatest Wisdom to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve,) that the same Portions of holy Scripture, which tend to Establish us in the Belief of our <hi>Lord</hi>'s Bodily <hi>Resurrection,</hi> and of our <hi>Own,</hi> should still be Read at the Solemnity of <hi>All Christian Burials.</hi> Besides, I still found the <hi>best</hi> and <hi>greatest</hi> Comfort I could administer either to Others or to my self, at the Funerals of the Best and the Greatest Friends, arose from this Consideration, (being sufficiently improved
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204239:4"/> and dwelt upon,) That <hi>Jesus Christ being Risen would Raise Ʋs also from the Dead.</hi> A Subject equally in Season both at a Funeral and a Feast; at a Solemn Time of Mourning, and holy Mirth. Very suitable to a Funeral at any season of the Year, but <hi>more</hi> suitable than at any, to One at <hi>Easter;</hi> because the Blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and Goodness, and Desirableness of Death, <hi>to such as die in the Lord unto whom they liv'd,</hi> does not only consist in This, <hi>That they Rest from their Labours</hi> (it is not only Good as the End of Evil,) but in This most especially, That their Death is but the Door to a Life of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that the last Day of their Lives is but the First of their Immortality. So that the Benefit of their Death lies chiefly wrapt up in a Resurrection. This is the Ground and Foundation of every Pious Man's Comfort in All his Sufferings. And as such 'twas recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by <hi>Paul the Aged</hi> to his <hi>Son Timothy,</hi> as an Amulet or Preservative to be still carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about him, and apply'd by True Faith up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on All Occasions. <hi>Remember that Jesus Christ was raised from the Dead.</hi> (2 Tim. 2. 8.) <hi>For if we be Dead with him, we shall also live with him,</hi> (v. 11.) <hi>if we suffer, we shall reign,</hi> (v. 12.) The same Receipt or Prophylactick he carefully prescribes to the <hi>Thessalonians.</hi> For having set
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204239:4"/> forth the Method of our Lord's second Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to judge the World, <hi>Descending from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with a shout, with the voice of the Archangel, and with the Trump of God, when the Dead in Christ shall Rise first, and the Faithful yet living shall be caught up with them in the Clouds, to meet the Lord in the Air, and so shall be ever with the Lord;<note place="margin">1 Thess 4. 16, 17.</note>
                  </hi> he concludes with a <hi>Wherefore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 18.</note>
                  <hi>Comfort one another with these words.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> also in his Epistle to the New Christians of the Dispersion, begins with Thanksgiving to God Almighty for having <hi>begotten</hi> us into a <hi>lively</hi> and a never-dying <hi>Hope, by and through the Resurrection of Jesus Christ from the Dead:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 3.</note> which there he lays as the Foundation of all their <hi>Ʋnspeakable and Glorious Joy;<note place="margin">v. 8.</note>
                  </hi> amidst the various Tribulations, <hi>(v.</hi> 6.) which as Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Christ they were sure to suffer. And what was <hi>The Saving of their Souls</hi> he set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them for their Incouragement, But <hi>the Reward of their Faith</hi> in the Resurrection? <hi>v.</hi> 5. So <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s pious Descant upon St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Christian Caveat <hi>concerning Them which are asleep,</hi> that <hi>we sorrow not as others who have no hope,</hi> is built upon the sole Ground of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection;</hi> and is as rational, as 'tis ingenious. <hi>Cur enim doleas, si periisse non credis? cur im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patienter feras subductum, quem credis Reversu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertull. de Patien. c.</hi> 9.</note>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:204239:5"/>
                  <hi>Profectio est, quam credis mortem,</hi> &amp;c. <q rend="margQuotes"> Why should any man grieve at a Friend's Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whom he believes not to have perished, but to have been <hi>translated</hi> only, or for a certain time <hi>withdrawn?</hi> What we common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call <hi>Death,</hi> is nothing more than a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval from Place to Place: and why should any one repine at a Friend's <hi>going Before</hi> to a state of Bliss, whom he heartily prays, and hopes, and expects to <hi>Follow?</hi> we <hi>contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously</hi> use our Saviour, when we deplore their Condition whom he hath called unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; or when we envy Their state of Life, which is vastly happier than our <hi>own. Cupio dissolvi,</hi> and <hi>God's will be done,</hi> is, or should be, <hi>every True Christian's Vote:</hi> and why should any man grieve, that his Prayers are Heard?</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 2. From which Descant of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in full accordance with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> It remains that a good Christian, <hi>who lives by Faith,</hi> is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy in his own mind as full Acquiescence and Serenity, as that of <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Wise man is sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be; which he compares, not unfitly, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Talis est Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entis animus, qualis Mundi status supra lunam. Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per illic Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num est.</hi> Sen. Ep. 59.</note> to the state of the World above the Moon; never obnoxious to the least <hi>shadow</hi> of <hi>Cloud</hi> or <hi>Tempest.</hi> And therefore at the Exequies of such as <hi>sleep in Christ Jesus,</hi> (be they the Dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204239:5"/> and Best of Friends,) Nothing can be more in Season, than That exhortative of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Thessalonians,</hi> (in his 1 <hi>Epistle</hi> and 5. <hi>Chapter) Rejoyce evermore, And in every thing give Thanks. Rejoyce evermore</hi> (v. 16.) as well in <hi>Affliction,</hi> as in <hi>Prosperity; And in every thing give Thanks,</hi> (v. 18.) not only in the <hi>Best,</hi> but the <hi>Worst</hi> Condition. <hi>Hard sayings</hi> at the first Hearing; But such as other Scriptures have softned to us. <hi>Rejoyce evermore;</hi> that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> Matt. 5. 12. <hi>And in every thing give Thanks;</hi> That is seconded by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 13, 14, 16.</p>
               <p>§. 3. This <hi>Flower of Paradise</hi> (pretended to by the old <hi>Stoicks,</hi> as a thing growing in their <hi>own</hi> Garden, though no where obtainable out of Christ's,) can never flourish or be well <hi>Rooted,</hi> unless it be in the <hi>Love,</hi> and the <hi>Faith</hi> of Christ: <hi>in Love without Dissimulation, and Faith unfeigned.</hi> Such a Faith as is <hi>the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of things not seen;</hi> and <hi>the Substance of things hoped for: and the Victory which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the World;</hi> that is, the World of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, or the Temptations of the World; the Enmity, and Friendship; the Pains, and Pleasures; the frowns, and favours; the frights, and flatteries; the Crosses, and Injoyments; the Pomps, and Vanities of the World. For
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204239:6"/> that a <hi>True Christian Faith</hi> is still <hi>Victorious</hi> over All These, is proved already by <hi>One Induction</hi> in the Eleventh Chapter to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> and may be proved by <hi>another,</hi> to wit, a Vastly Great Number of <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>Confessors,</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> whom the Annals of the World, and especially of the Church, do oblige us with. And as there's no Sounder Arguing than <hi>Ab Actu ad Potentiam;</hi> so is there no readier way (as far at least as I can judge) whereby to <hi>fortifie</hi> our <hi>Belief</hi> of the two last Articles in the Creed, <hi>The Resurrection of the Body,</hi> and <hi>the Life Everlasting,</hi> (the Reviviscence of our flesh, and Immortality of our Spirits,) than by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templating the Importance of our Apostle's Assertion to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Christ is risen from the Dead, and become the First-fruits of them that slept. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 20.</note>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>§. 4. THE <hi>latter end</hi> of this Text may very well be made the Subject of a fit Preface to the <hi>beginning.</hi> For <hi>Death</hi> it seems is but a <hi>Sleep,</hi> since <hi>Christ</hi> is <hi>risen from the Dead.</hi> God the Son has chang'd its <hi>Nature;</hi> and God the Holy Ghost has chang'd its <hi>Name</hi> too.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204239:6"/> Though it continues its wonted <hi>Tyranny,</hi> as to <hi>all other</hi> Creatures; yet as to <hi>Ʋs,</hi> it is <hi>Reform'd.</hi> There having been put upon it by <hi>Grace</hi> a much more <hi>gentle</hi> disposition, than by <hi>Nature</hi> it ever had. For <hi>Ʋs</hi> to <hi>dye,</hi> and to be <hi>buried,</hi> is but to <hi>lay</hi> our selves <hi>down,</hi> and to <hi>take our rest. Even so saith the Spirit of them that dye in the Lord,</hi> not that they <hi>perish,<note place="margin">Rev. 14. 13.</note>
                  </hi> but that they <hi>Rest from their Labours.</hi> The great <hi>Reformer</hi> of Death is <hi>Christ; (The</hi> immaculate <hi>Lamb slain from the Foundations of the World;)</hi> whose Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest over it was the <hi>Epocha,</hi> from whence it's Reformation did take its <hi>Date.</hi> Our blessed Saviour said of <hi>Lazarus</hi> (by a kind of Prole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>psis) though he lay buried till he <hi>stunk,</hi> (even no less than <hi>four days,) our Friend Lazarus sleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; but I go to awaken him out of sleep; <note place="margin">Joh. 11. 11.</note>
                  </hi> which when the Disciples misunderstood, thinking he had spoken of a natural sleep only, and thereupon answer'd, <hi>if he sleep he shall do well,</hi> (v. 12.) Jesus said unto them plainly, <hi>Lazarus is Dead.</hi> (v. 14.) Yet when <hi>Jairus his Daughter</hi> lay <hi>as dead</hi> as this <hi>Lazarus,</hi> our Saviour said unto the <hi>Mourners,</hi> as they were <hi>weeping</hi> and <hi>bewailing</hi> her, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>weep not: she is not dead,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 8. 57.</note>
                  <hi>but sleepeth.</hi> Now how can we salve our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's words from implying a <hi>Contradiction,</hi> unless it be from this pertinent and most plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204239:7"/> Consideration, that he intended to shew the <hi>difference</hi> between the Dissolutions of <hi>men,</hi> and <hi>Brutes?</hi> In respect of the former, <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Sleep</hi> are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, two expressions for the same thing; and are accordingly made use of in many passages of Scripture; in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar by our Apostle, no less than four times in This one Chapter. Of those five hundred <hi>Brethren at once,</hi> who saw Christ risen, the <hi>greater part</hi> were alive, <hi>but some</hi> (saith he) are <hi>faln asleep.</hi> (v. 7.) so He saith of Saints and Martyrs; not that they are <hi>perished,</hi> but <hi>only faln asleep in Christ.</hi> (v. 18.) <hi>Behold,</hi> (says he again) <hi>I shew you a Mystery; we shall not all sleep, but shall all be changed.</hi> And in my Text, <hi>Christ the first-fruits of them that slept.</hi> All which we owe to the first part of it, <hi>Christ is risen from the Dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 5. For if <hi>Christ had not risen,</hi> Death had been a meer <hi>Destruction,</hi> and not a <hi>Sleep:</hi> A perpetual <hi>Banishment</hi> from the Territories of <hi>Nature;</hi> not a <hi>Door</hi> (as <hi>now</hi> 'tis) to a <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Glory.</hi> The <hi>Form</hi> and Matter of every man had been eternally <hi>divorc'd;</hi> never to injoy a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond meeting. And when our dearest friends dye, we might have reason to be <hi>sorry as men without hope.</hi> Funeral Sermons would be <hi>Dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and <hi>Dismal things,</hi> very fit to be preached,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204239:7"/> not in Sable only, but Sackcloth; if our dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est friends departed were wholly shut out of the World. And yet so they must have been, if <hi>Christ himself had not risen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 6. But <hi>now</hi> (God be thanked) the Case is quite alter'd. For <hi>Christ is risen from the Dead:</hi> and not only so, but he is risen the <hi>first-fruits</hi> too; a word of intimate relation to all the <hi>dead sheafs</hi> of the <hi>general Harvest.</hi> And being <hi>so</hi> risen, He hath <hi>trodden</hi> down Death, that we might also <hi>trample</hi> on it. Which tho' a <hi>long</hi> sleep indeed, yet 'tis not <hi>endless.</hi> For in case <hi>nothing else</hi> will awaken us out of it, <hi>the last Trump</hi> will. So says our Apostle towards the end of this Chapter, <hi>we shall be changed in a moment, in the twinkling of an Eye at the last Trump, when the Trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 51, 52.</note> Changed with a Witness, and the most to be imagin'd to our Advantage. For what is now sown in <hi>weakness,</hi> shall be raised again in <hi>Power.</hi> What is sown in <hi>Corruption,</hi> shall be raised in <hi>Incorruption.</hi> What is sown in <hi>dishonour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 42, 43.</note> shall be raised again in <hi>Glory.</hi> Or to express it in other words of our Apostle to the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> Christ shall <hi>change our vile Body, that it may be like unto his Glorious Body.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philip. 3 20, 21.</note> So true it is what is said by a kind of Proverb, That as <hi>Sleep</hi> is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204239:8"/> nothing better, than <hi>the Elder Brother of Death;</hi> so <hi>Death it self</hi> is nothing worse, than the <hi>younger Brother of Sleep.</hi> For <hi>Christ</hi> is risen from the <hi>Dead,</hi> and become the first-fruits of them that <hi>slept.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 7. This Text I may say is the <hi>Double Hinge,</hi> whereupon the <hi>whole Chapter</hi> does seem to <hi>turn.</hi> For it does not only assert our blessed <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Resurrection, but asserts it as an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> for the inforcement of <hi>our own.</hi> And the whole <hi>Door of Hope</hi> opened to us by a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer,</hi> does seem to hang more especially on <hi>these two Hinges; that Christ is Risen,</hi> and (by a Consequence unavoidable) <hi>that we must Rise.</hi> I say we <hi>must,</hi> on a <hi>supposal</hi> that <hi>Christ</hi> is Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen. Because there is <hi>such</hi> an <hi>essential Tye,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Head</hi> and the <hi>Members</hi> of the very same <hi>Body,</hi> between the <hi>Root</hi> and the <hi>Branches</hi> of the very same <hi>Tree,</hi> between the <hi>Former</hi> and <hi>Later Fruits</hi> of the very same <hi>Harvest;</hi> that the <hi>First,</hi> being granted, infers the <hi>Second.</hi> A thing the fitter to be made out in every popular Congregation, not upon <hi>Easter</hi> Sunday only, but <hi>every</hi> Sunday in the <hi>year,</hi> (if occasion serves) because amongst <hi>all</hi> the principal Doctrines of our Religion, or the <hi>Twelve</hi> important Articles of our Creed, there is not certainly any <hi>One,</hi> either <hi>believ'd</hi> with more <hi>difficulty,</hi> or <hi>doubted</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:204239:8"/> of with more <hi>Danger,</hi> than that we shall <hi>rise</hi> out of our <hi>Graves, and see God in our Flesh, not with other, but with these same Eyes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 19. 25, 26, 27.</note>
               </p>
               <p>§. 8. First 'tis so <hi>difficult</hi> to <hi>believe</hi> it for Flesh and Blood, that it was one of the <hi>last</hi> myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries (or rather the very last of All) which found Admittance with the <hi>Apostles;</hi> though there were greater means us'd, and more pains ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to teach them <hi>this</hi> lesson, than <hi>any other.</hi> And when the learnedst of the Greeks were first converted to Christianity, which they received <hi>by degrees,</hi> (as little Children do learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,) by <hi>line upon line, precept upon precept, here a little and there a little,</hi> first one part, and then another; Though they believ'd (whilst they were <hi>Heathens)</hi> the <hi>Immortality</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> yet they would sooner admit of any thing, than the <hi>reviving</hi> of a <hi>Dead Body.</hi> This was still the <hi>last Article</hi> in each particular Man's <hi>Creed;</hi> and was one of the very <hi>last</hi> the Fathers put into the <hi>Nicene:</hi> It having been <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Niceph. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listus Eccl. Hist. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c</hi> 13. <hi>&amp; Platina ad an.</hi> 381.</note> added by <hi>Gregory Nyssen</hi> at the Appointment and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Second Council</hi> of <hi>Constantinople.</hi> But when I say <hi>the last Article</hi> in the <hi>Neophyte</hi>'s Creed, I mean 'twas That they believ'd <hi>the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test;</hi> or That to which they surrendred their <hi>last Assent.</hi> In so much that <hi>Synesius</hi> was made a Bishop in the Greek Church, (for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204239:9"/> of his Learning, and the goodness of his life,) before he could absolutely believe, that humane <hi>Bodies,</hi> as well as Souls, shall (by a general Resurrection) be made <hi>Immortal.</hi> For considering how many Bodies have been burnt down to <hi>Ashes,</hi> which Ashes have been disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by all the Two and Thirty <hi>Winds;</hi> how many Bodies have been <hi>drown'd,</hi> and made a Feast for the <hi>Fishes,</hi> which Fishes have made a Feast for the use of <hi>Men;</hi> how many Bodies have been moulder'd into the <hi>Element</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> which Earth becomes fruitful for <hi>Sheep and Oxen,</hi> which again are for the sustenance and food of <hi>Men;</hi> how many Bodies have been <hi>mangl'd</hi> for the Instruction of the <hi>Physician,</hi> who makes a Skeleton of the <hi>Bones,</hi> a piece of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>skin,</hi> a drinking Cup of the skull, a Perriwig of the <hi>Hair,</hi> Mummy of the <hi>Muscles,</hi> and several Med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cines of that <hi>Mummy,</hi> all which are for the service and use of Men too; Lastly, considering how many <hi>men</hi> are devour'd by <hi>Canibals;</hi> how many <hi>Children</hi> by their <hi>Parents;</hi> and <hi>Parents</hi> by their <hi>Children;</hi> (as in the Famin at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> besieg'd by <hi>Titus;)</hi> and the Body of <hi>Mausolus</hi> by the Wife of his Bosom <hi>Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misia,</hi> (who in the excesses of her Affection Drank up the <hi>Ashes</hi> of her Husband instead of <hi>Spice,)</hi> so as the Bodies of <hi>some</hi> have been
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204239:9"/> the Sepulchres of <hi>others;</hi> I say, considering These things, Men were <hi>difficult</hi> in believing the <hi>Resurrection of the Body,</hi> and objected such things as these, against the <hi>Gospel</hi> and the <hi>Creed</hi> of the <hi>primitive Christians. Pliny</hi> himself was such a Fool, (however learned in other points, and notwithstanding He had written <hi>De his qui Flati</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. Nat. Hist. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c</hi> 52.</note>
                  <hi>revixerunt,)</hi> as to deny that God Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self can <note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>l</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note>
                  <hi>revive a dead man,</hi> or crown a <hi>Mortal with Immortality.</hi> The <hi>Epicuraeans</hi> and the <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks</hi> despis'd St. <hi>Paul</hi> for his Doctrine, as <hi>New,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 17. 18, 19, 20.</note> and <hi>strange Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> would needs have had the Resurrection <hi>already past.</hi> The <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 18.</note>
                  <hi>Seleuciani</hi> or <hi>Hermiani</hi> contended as much to have it <hi>Present;</hi> and that in the daily <hi>Procrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Augustin. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</hi> 59.</note> of men and women; whereby the <hi>Parents</hi> were said by Them, to <hi>live again</hi> in their <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity.</hi> This was all the Resurrection Those Hereticks would allow. Nor was it only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd in gross by the <hi>Sadducees</hi> and <hi>Herodians,</hi> by <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and the <hi>Manichees</hi> (as it is at this day by the <hi>Disciples</hi> of the <hi>Leviathan,)</hi> But the very <hi>first</hi> tidings which were brought of <hi>Christ</hi>'s <hi>Rising,</hi> by <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and <hi>Joanna,</hi> and <hi>Mary the Mother of James,</hi> did seem to Christ's own <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles</hi> as <hi>idle Tales; and they believed them not;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 24. 10, 11.</note> tho' immediately after they believ'd their own <hi>Senses,</hi> their <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 4. 20.</note>
                  <hi>Eyes,</hi> their <hi>Ears,</hi> and their <hi>Fingers</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:204239:10"/>
                  <hi>ends</hi> too. Even <hi>Cleophas</hi> and his <hi>Companion</hi> (St. <hi>Luke himself</hi> in probability,) even whilst <hi>Christ</hi> was <hi>talking</hi> to them, were <hi>slow of heart to believe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vers 25.</note> him risen. <hi>Festus</hi> thought that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side himself,</hi> and that <hi>over-much learning had made him mad,</hi> (how patient soever he had <note place="margin">Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. 23. 24.</note> been of the <hi>precedent</hi> part of his speech,) as soon as he spake of <hi>Christs arising from the Dead.</hi> And lastly some of Those <hi>Corinthians</hi> whom our Apostle writes to, tho' in all <hi>other</hi> points they had espoused the Faith of Christ, and had been admitted into the Church by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Laver of their Regeneration, did yet professedly <hi>disbelieve the Resurrection of the Dead.</hi> (V. 12.) These were the men, who gave <hi>occasion</hi> to our Apostles whole Discourse of a Resurrection; and so we may thank their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity,</hi> for this additional assistance of our <hi>Belief;</hi> by all the Arguments and Reasons which our Apostle strictly presseth all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians with.</p>
               <p>§. 9. Secondly, as it is <hi>Difficult</hi> to <hi>believe</hi> the Resurrection I now contend for; so <hi>not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it,</hi> is just as <hi>Dangerous.</hi> For it leads us to a suspicion, that <hi>Christ himself is not Risen;</hi> and that the Scriptures themselves are <hi>false,</hi> which do so frequently <hi>affirm</hi> it. It makes us <hi>obstinate</hi> in our <hi>Sorrow</hi> for the <hi>Death</hi> of dear <hi>Friends;</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204239:10"/> and either too <hi>fearful</hi> or too fearless of <hi>our own.</hi> It emasculates and enervates our care of <hi>Vertue;</hi> and makes us <hi>abandon</hi> our selves to <hi>Vice.</hi> For what Man living would <hi>cast</hi> his <hi>Wheat</hi> into the <hi>ground,</hi> if he did not <hi>believe</hi> its Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and withal its Improvement in time of Harvest? There is nothing more vexing, than <hi>Labour in vain.</hi> Would the <hi>Merchant</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture <hi>all</hi> his <hi>stock</hi> upon the <hi>Ocean,</hi> did he not <hi>hope</hi> by that means to <hi>advance</hi> his <hi>Wealth?</hi> or would the very hard <hi>Student out-watch</hi> his Candle, and <hi>prevent</hi> the early <hi>Sun</hi> with his <hi>Lucubrations,</hi> if he did not well <hi>hope</hi> to increase his <hi>knowledge?</hi> and to be <hi>paid</hi> for That know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, either in the <hi>present,</hi> or <hi>future</hi> World? Would the Souldier <hi>court</hi> hardships, or <hi>covet</hi> dangers the most affrighting, and so as to <hi>sight away</hi> Both his <hi>Hands</hi> on the stage of Honour, if he were not <hi>led on</hi> by a <hi>Great Commander?</hi> I mean the <hi>General</hi> Commander of humane Actions and Exploits, a strong and steady <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation</hi> of some proportionable <hi>Reward?</hi> No, 'tis a Maxim in Philosophy which never fails, or grows false; <hi>Omne agit propter finem.</hi> Every <hi>Motion</hi> implies a <hi>Center,</hi> and every <hi>Action</hi> must have its <hi>End.</hi> Even they who most <hi>study</hi> to squander away their precious Time, to <hi>lose</hi> the hours they should <hi>employ</hi> and <hi>negotiate</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:204239:11"/>
                  <hi>with,</hi> have something or other in <hi>Design,</hi> which makes them most <hi>industriously</hi> and <hi>elaborately</hi> Idle; it makes them <hi>earnest</hi> and <hi>diligent</hi> in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Nothing. Expectation of Advantage,</hi> in one kind or other, is universally the <hi>whetstone</hi> which sets an <hi>edge</hi> on <hi>all Appetites,</hi> and makes them <hi>keen</hi> after <hi>Action,</hi> both Good, and Evil. Did ever any Man spread a Net, <hi>without</hi> a purpose to catch <hi>some</hi> Prey? or <hi>with</hi> a set purpose of catching <hi>none? Who goeth a warfare at his own Cost,</hi> says our Apostle? <hi>Who planteth a Vineyard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 7.</note>
                  <hi>and eateth not</hi> (if he can) <hi>of the fruit it yields him? Does God</hi> indeed <hi>take Care for Oxen, in his forbidding them to be muzzl'd whilst they are</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vers. 9.</note>
                  <hi>treading out the Corn?</hi> or is it registred in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture <hi>for our sakes only? No doubt for our sakes this thing is written, that he who plougheth should</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> Vers.10 </note>
                  <hi>plough in Hope, and he who thrasheth in hope should be partaker of his Hope.</hi> If we did not live in <hi>Hope</hi> of a Redemption from the Dead, from the Land of Forgetfulness, the dark Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirements of the Grave; and did not stand in some <hi>Awe</hi> of a <hi>Day of Judgment;</hi> We should <hi>run</hi> upon Damnation, (as many do,) without the least Touch of <hi>Regret,</hi> or <hi>Scruple;</hi> yea with <hi>greediness,</hi> and <hi>delight,</hi> because with <hi>carnal Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.</hi> We should not macerate our selves with <hi>Mortification</hi> and <hi>Self-denial.</hi> We should not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204239:11"/> beat down our Bodies, and keep them under. We should not <hi>crucifie our flesh, with the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and Lusts,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> injoyns. But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>crown our selves with Rose-buds; and drink</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wisd. 2. 7, 8, 10, 11, 12.</note>
                  <hi>Wine in Bowles; and stretch our selves upon beds of Ivory; and oppress the Poor man for being righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous;</hi> and poison the Husband, to find access unto the Wife; laugh at <hi>Conscience,</hi> and <hi>Sin,</hi> as nothing else but a couple of <hi>Ecclesiastical Words;</hi> and <hi>call our strength the Law of Justice.</hi> In a word, we should say with the incredulous <hi>Corinthians,</hi> v. 32. (if we <hi>deny'd</hi> the <hi>Resurrection,</hi> as some of them it seems did, v. 12.) <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 10. Now in such Times as These, wherein the <hi>Sadducees</hi> and <hi>Herodians</hi> do walk about in new Names, how can we better bestow our Thoughts at <hi>any</hi> season of the year, but more especially at <hi>This,</hi> than on an Article of our Religion, which is so eminently proper as well for <hi>Comfort,</hi> as for <hi>Instruction?</hi> and which as 'tis <hi>difficult</hi> to <hi>believe,</hi> so 'tis as <hi>dangerous</hi> to <hi>doubt of.</hi> Our Apostle in This Chapter does lay in Provisions against them <hi>Both.</hi> Whilst he indeavours by many Arguments to make the Difficulty <hi>Null;</hi> and in the doing of that, to <hi>prevent</hi> the Danger. For the removing of the <hi>Difficulty,</hi> He first of all proves that <hi>Christ is</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:204239:12"/>
                  <hi>Risen,</hi> and Thence he argues that <hi>we must Rise.</hi> The present Text I am upon is fitly resolv'd into an <hi>Enthymeme,</hi> in order to it. That <hi>Christ is risen from the Dead,</hi> is the <hi>Antecedent;</hi> and his being the <hi>first-fruits of them that slept,</hi> contains within it This <hi>Sequel, that we must Rise.</hi> For 'tis plain, the <hi>First-fruits</hi> is a word of <hi>Relation</hi> to all the <hi>Sheafs</hi> of the <hi>Harvest;</hi> and does evidently allude <hi>unto the Sheaf of First-fruits</hi> in the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> which was to be <hi>brought</hi> unto the <hi>Priest,</hi> as soon as <hi>Harvest</hi> was <hi>begun,</hi> that in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the People who were to <hi>reap,</hi> He might <hi>wave it before the Lord upon the morrow after the Sabbath.</hi> Upon which very <hi>day</hi> of their <hi>waving the Sheaf, an He-lamb without blemish was to be offer'd unto the Lord.</hi> This significant Institution of <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Moses</hi> (Levit. 23. 10, 11, 12.) was clearly alluded to by <hi>Abigail</hi> in that excellent Address she made to <hi>David;</hi> wherein she told him <hi>that his Soul should be bound in the Bundle of Life before the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 29. And what else could be the <hi>end,</hi> or <hi>final Cause</hi> of this <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony,</hi> which God was pleas'd to have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by <hi>all</hi> that would enter into <hi>Canaan,</hi> but that the <hi>Harvest</hi> might be <hi>all sanctified</hi> in the particular <hi>Sanctification</hi> of that <hi>one sheaf?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 11. And (that out of this <hi>Legal</hi> or <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Sheaf</hi> we may <hi>thrash out</hi> some Christian
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204239:12"/>
                  <hi>Evangelical Wheat,)</hi> we must know that All This was but a <hi>shadow of Things to come;</hi> and <hi>This day is that Scripture fulfilled in our Ears.</hi> For <hi>Yesterday</hi> was the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> which <hi>This Day</hi> advanced from <hi>Last</hi> to <hi>First,</hi> and from <hi>Bodily</hi> to <hi>Ghostly.</hi> That was a weekly <hi>Commemoration</hi> of the <hi>Creation</hi> of the World; This of the <hi>Redemption,</hi> or <hi>Re-Creation,</hi> and in particular of our Saviour's <hi>Resurrection from the Dead.</hi> Every <hi>Sunday</hi> in the Year is <hi>Commemorative</hi> of <hi>This,</hi> and therefore call'd <hi>the Lord's Day,</hi> but not the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> (unless by a few well-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people, for want of Knowledge, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration;) For <hi>Easter-Day</hi> (by way <hi>of Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence,) is the Morrow after the Sabbath, (Levit.</hi> 23. and <hi>The He-Lamb without Blemish is Jesus Christ.</hi> He is the <hi>Offering,</hi> and the <hi>Priest,</hi> and the <hi>Sheaf of First-fruits.</hi> And so intimate is the relation between <hi>the Sheaf of First-fruits,</hi> and all the rest of the <hi>Crop</hi> or <hi>Harvest,</hi> that our Apostle thinks fit to <hi>argue</hi> both backwards and forwards, in the negative and the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative, from the <hi>one</hi> unto the <hi>other.</hi> First on the <hi>one</hi> side in the Negative; <hi>If there is no Resurrection of the Dead, Then is Christ not risen.</hi> (v. 13.) And again, <hi>If the Dead rise not, Then is not Christ raised.</hi> (v. 16.) Next on the <hi>other</hi> side in the affirmative; <hi>if the first-fruit is holy,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:204239:13"/>
                  <hi>the Lump is also holy:</hi> and if the <hi>Root,</hi> then the <hi>Branches. (Rom.</hi> 11. 16.) Whereof the meaning must needs be this; that Christ is risen from the Dead, not as a <hi>private</hi> and <hi>separate</hi> person, only for <hi>himself,</hi> and his own <hi>single Interest;</hi> but he is risen the <hi>First-fruits</hi> of the <hi>general Harvest; that as by Man came Death, so by Man might also come the Resurrection of the Dead:</hi> (v. 21.) <hi>that as in Adam All dyed, so All in Christ might be made alive.</hi> (v. 22.) 'Tis therefore added by our Apostle, <hi>He is become the First-fruits</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>of them that slept.</hi> Whereby He gives us to understand, that as the <hi>Death</hi> of our Lord has <hi>destroy'd</hi> Death, so his <hi>Rising from the Dead</hi> has given us All a Capability to <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over</hi> it: the Grave is now but our <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitory,</hi> which had been otherwise our <hi>Bed of Death;</hi> or <hi>Beth Abaddon, the House of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyer.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Greek, <hi>Coemeterium</hi> in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, <hi>Cemetiere</hi> in French, and <hi>Cimitiero</hi> in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, do each of them literally import, not so much <hi>a Church-yard,</hi> as a <hi>Place to Sleep in:</hi> our Bodies, lying in the Grave, do not <hi>perish,</hi> but <hi>lye Dormant,</hi> like <hi>Trees</hi> in <hi>Winter;</hi> and like <hi>Trees</hi> do <hi>take Root</hi> too. The Place which is <hi>consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> for Burials (we may say) is God's <hi>Nursery;</hi> wherein our <hi>Bodies</hi> are conserved for His <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> For what is our <hi>Rising</hi> from the <hi>Dead,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:204239:13"/> but our being <hi>Transplanted</hi> from thence to <hi>Paradise?</hi> to flourish as <hi>Trees</hi> of <hi>Immortality</hi> about the <hi>River of Life?</hi> (Rev. 22. 1, 3.) The <hi>Grains</hi> of <hi>Corn</hi> which a man <hi>soweth cannot pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly be quickned, except they dye:</hi> Their <hi>Death</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 12. 23.</note> is evidently their <hi>Privilege;</hi> and a necessary <hi>step</hi> to their <hi>Improvement.</hi> What are the <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes</hi> but the <hi>Sepulchres,</hi> wherein the Grains do lye <hi>buried?</hi> Nor can any Trees <hi>live,</hi> unless their <hi>Roots</hi> have their <hi>Interment.</hi> And thus it is with <hi>us</hi> too, who are as <hi>Trees</hi> with the <hi>Root upwards.</hi> We cannot <hi>rise from the Dead,</hi> unless we <hi>dye:</hi> Unless our <hi>Heads</hi> are <hi>under Ground,</hi> we cannot <hi>shoot upwards</hi> to <hi>life eternal;</hi> for which our <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Dissolution</hi> are unavoidable <hi>Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications:</hi> So that we cannot but confess, if we contemplate our <hi>Resurrection,</hi> that whilst we are lying in our <hi>Graves,</hi> (as I said a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) we do but <hi>sleep</hi> like <hi>Trees</hi> in <hi>Winter,</hi> when their <hi>Sap</hi> goes to the <hi>Root,</hi> where it lies <hi>dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi> till the <hi>Spring;</hi> which yet, as soon as the Spring begins, do straight <hi>awake,</hi> and <hi>look up,</hi> as it were <hi>opening</hi> their <hi>Blossoms,</hi> instead of <hi>Eyes.</hi> Fitly therefore is it said by our Apostle in this Text, and as fitly is it consider'd on this Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, (this Anniversary Feast of our Saviour's <hi>Rising,) Christ is Risen from the Dead, and become the First-fruits</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>of them that slept.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:204239:14"/>
               <p> §. 12. But in as much as <hi>Our</hi> State depends on <hi>Christ</hi>'s, so as if <hi>Christ</hi> is <hi>indeed</hi> risen, <hi>we</hi> are sure that we <hi>shall;</hi> and if Christ is <hi>not</hi> risen, we are sure we shall <hi>not;</hi> and that the <hi>Sequel</hi> is nothing worth, without the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Antecedent;</hi> let us first of all attend to the <hi>Proof</hi> of <hi>That.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Christ is risen from the Dead,</hi> (the first part of the <hi>Enthymeme,)</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> evinceth in but one Chapter, from Five several <hi>Topicks,</hi> or Heads of Arguing. First from the Verdict of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Confer</hi> Luk. 24. 27. Act. 3. 24. &amp;C. 28. v. 23. Act. 26. 22, 23. Act. 2. 32.</note> the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> (v. 3, &amp; 4.) Next from the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and knowledge of the whole <note n="‖" place="margin">Act. 10. 39, 40, 41. Act. 1. 3.</note> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of the Apostles, who <hi>saw</hi> him after he was risen; (v. 5.) and <hi>more</hi> than <hi>saw</hi> him, for they <hi>conversed</hi> with him at large; some by <hi>Discoursing,</hi> some by <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking</hi> with him, one by <hi>feeling and thrusting his fingers</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>Sides,</hi> to whom in particular is ascribed the <hi>Eleventh Article</hi> of the <hi>Creed,</hi> as fitter for <hi>His</hi> Interposition, than any <hi>other's.</hi> Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 'tis argued by St. <hi>Paul</hi> from the Suffrages and Experiences of above 500 Eye-witnesses at once; (v. 6.) Fourthly from the <hi>Credit</hi> he ought <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> to give to his <hi>own Eyes;</hi> (v. 8.) Fifthly from the <hi>Absurdities,</hi> which needs must follow the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Supposition of <hi>Christ's not rising:</hi> which Absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities he shews us are <hi>gross,</hi> and <hi>many.</hi> For <hi>if</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:204239:14"/>
                  <hi>Christ is not risen,</hi> Then <hi>our Preaching is in vain, and as vain is your Faith.</hi> (v. 14.) Yea upon this profane hypothesis, <hi>That Christ is not risen,</hi> we who are Preachers <hi>of the Gospel, are</hi> (if not For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, yet) <hi>False-witnesses of God.</hi> (v. 15.) <hi>and ye are yet in your Sins.</hi> (v. 17.) And all the Men we call <hi>Martyrs have lost their Sufferings.</hi> (v. 18.) It had been much better for them to have <hi>slept in whole skins,</hi> than to be <hi>torn with wild Beasts,</hi> and <hi>broken upon Wheels, and broyled on Grid-irons, and brayed in Mortars, and sawn</hi> asun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with <hi>rugged Swords,</hi> and tormented with an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a being flea'd alive from head to foot, and all in hopes of injoying by so much <hi>a better Resurrection.</hi> And therefore on a sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal (a blasphemous supposal) that Christ is <hi>not</hi> risen, the most sincere-hearted <hi>Christians,</hi> who have the most <hi>hope</hi> in <hi>Christ,</hi> and have the most <hi>reason</hi> for it, and <hi>choose</hi> to be <hi>persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in This,</hi> because they look for a <hi>Reward</hi> in <hi>another</hi> World, are the veriest fools, and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and in the miserablest Condition of all Mankind. <hi>(v.</hi> 19.) But because, whilst we are <hi>Christians,</hi> we cannot admit of <hi>such Absurdities,</hi> as would destroy the very <hi>Foundations</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity it self,</hi> we cannot choose but conclude, that <hi>Christ is Risen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 13. Thus we have St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Topicks,</hi> from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204239:15"/> which he proves his <hi>Antecedent.</hi> But tho' to <hi>us,</hi> who are <hi>Christians,</hi> These are cogent, and irresistible; yet they are not so to <hi>Others,</hi> who take St. <hi>Paul</hi> for a <hi>Deceiver;</hi> or at least to have been <hi>deceiv'd;</hi> and think no better of <hi>our</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, than <hi>we</hi> do of <hi>Theirs.</hi> Professed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies must be won by <hi>other</hi> ways of Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and more <hi>compulsive</hi> of their <hi>Assent:</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jews,</hi> or <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and whether those <hi>Gentiles</hi> are <hi>Greeks,</hi> or <hi>Romans.</hi> Against the <hi>Jews</hi> we are to argue the certain <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>Christ's Rising,</hi> from that which they <hi>acknowledge</hi> for the <hi>Infallible Word of God:</hi> From the <hi>Types,</hi> and the <hi>Predictions,</hi> and the <hi>Examples</hi> of the <hi>old</hi> Testament, fully <hi>accomplished,</hi> and <hi>fulfilled,</hi> and clearly <hi>parallel'd</hi> in the <hi>New.</hi> Sufficient <hi>Types</hi> of it they have in the <hi>Lyon's Den,</hi> and the <hi>fiery Furnace; Daniel</hi> rising out of the first, and the <hi>three Children</hi> out of the Second. They have a <hi>clear Type</hi> in <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen</hi> 22. &amp; <hi>Hob.</hi> 11.</note>
                  <hi>Isaac,</hi> in <note n="‖" place="margin">Gen. 37. &amp; Ch. 39. &amp; Ch. 41. <hi>Jon.</hi> 1. &amp;c. 2. <hi>Matt.</hi> 12, 39, 40.</note>
                  <hi>Joseph</hi> somewhat a <hi>clearer,</hi> and the <hi>clearest</hi> of all in <hi>Jonah;</hi> in whom was typified both the <hi>Substance,</hi> and the <hi>Day</hi> of Christ's Rising. Amongst their manifold <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> I shall but instance in two or three. First in that of the Prophet <hi>Hosea. After two days will he revive us, and the third he will raise</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hos. 6. 2.</note>
                  <hi>us up, and we shall live in his sight.</hi> Next in that of the Prophet <hi>David, My flesh shall rest in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 16. 10. Act. 2. 25.</note>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:204239:15"/>
                  <hi>hope. Thou shalt not leave my Soul in Hell, nor suffer thine Holy one to see corruption.</hi> Unto which <note place="margin">Act. 13. 33. Psal. 2. 7.</note> that of <hi>Esay</hi> may well be added; <hi>Thy dead men shall live, together with my dead Body shall they arise; Awake and sing ye that dwell in the Dust.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 26. 19.</note> They have <hi>Examples</hi> from the Old Testament, <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Kings 13. 21.</note> in the Man who was <hi>revived,</hi> and even <hi>rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed</hi> out of his <hi>Grave</hi> too, by being hastily cast down into the <hi>Sepulchre</hi> of <hi>Elisha.</hi> Such a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterious force there was (by the will of God) in the very <hi>dead Bones</hi> of that holy Prophet. <note n="*" place="margin">2 Kings 4. 34.</note> In the <hi>Shunamite's dead child,</hi> rais'd to life by <hi>Elisha,</hi> whilst Himself was yet living. And long before in the <hi>dead Son</hi> of the Widow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> who by the <hi>Prayers</hi> of <hi>Elijah</hi> was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <note place="margin">1 Kings 17. 21, 22, 23.</note> to life. To these Convictions of the <hi>Jews</hi> we may add the <hi>confessions of</hi> Josephus <hi>himself,</hi> (one of the learnedst of all their Writers;) that <hi>Jesus Christ, having been crucified, was seen alive the third day after: And that he doubted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>seph de Antiq. Jud. l.</hi> 18. 4. 6.</note>
                  <hi>'twere lawful, to reckon Christ a meer Man.</hi> Yea the profess'd and sworn <hi>Enemies</hi> of our Saviour's Resurrection did clearly <hi>prove</hi> it, and <hi>preach it up,</hi> by their utmost Indeavours to <hi>cry it down.</hi> And this may be easily made appear from Matters of Fact related to us, in the <hi>two last Chapters of St. Matthew.</hi> Upon which I shall <note place="margin">Matt. 27. 63, 64, 65, 66. &amp; ch. 28. 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> the rather insist awhile, the more <hi>advantageous</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:204239:16"/> I think it is, to <hi>catch</hi> an <hi>Enemy</hi> in his <hi>own Trap;</hi> to make his <hi>own</hi> Weapon <hi>worst</hi> him; to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn</hi> and countermine him with his own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved <hi>Lyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 14. The first Indeavour of the Jews was quite to <hi>hinder</hi> Christ's Rising, by <hi>fraud,</hi> and <hi>force.</hi> And when they found <hi>That</hi> project <hi>vain;</hi> they next indeavour to <hi>conceal</hi> it from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Knowledge. Had not their Care been very singular to <hi>bury</hi> his <hi>Rising,</hi> as well as <hi>Him,</hi> They had not found the <hi>Truth</hi> of it, as by that means they <hi>did;</hi> and might have said, with some <hi>colour,</hi> he had been stoln out of his Grave. But (by the providence of God's confounding the subtilty of these Serpents,) see the <hi>Folly</hi> of their <hi>craft;</hi> the <hi>Inadvertency</hi> of their <hi>care;</hi> and the general <hi>Benefit</hi> of their <hi>Envy. The Priests and Pharisees come together unto Pilate.</hi> They <note place="margin">Matth. 27. 62.</note> confess they do <hi>remember,</hi> Jesus had said being alive, <hi>that after three days he would rise again.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 27. 63.</note> They pretend an apprehension, a fear, and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie, <hi>that his Disciples would steal him away by night; and give it out among the people, that he is risen from the Dead.</hi> Which if the People should once believe, they would presently turn Christians; <hi>and so the last Error should be worse than the first.</hi> Therefore they ask (what <hi>Pilate</hi>
                  <note place="margin">64.</note> grants them) <hi>a Band of Soldiers</hi> to guard the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204239:16"/> Sepulchre; and to keep it from plunder un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til <hi>the third day.</hi> Nor contented with this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision, <note place="margin">65.</note> they roll <hi>a Stone over the Sepulchre</hi> of exceeding great weight; <hi>and make it sure</hi> with <note place="margin">60.</note> plates of Iron; and seal it up with their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Seals too; that if it shall possibly be <hi>rifled,</hi> it may not yet possibly escape their knowledg. By all which means it comes to pass, that they <hi>themselves</hi> are made <hi>sure</hi> of our blessed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's <hi>Rising;</hi> to which their <hi>Stone,</hi> and their <hi>Seals,</hi> and their <hi>Plates of Iron,</hi> and especially their <hi>Watchmen,</hi> do all bear Witness. The <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men tell the chief Priests</hi> what things had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <note place="margin">Matth 28. 11.</note> They make relation of the <hi>Earth-quake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2.</note> and the <hi>Angel;</hi> and how for <hi>fear</hi> of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel <hi>they quak'd themselves too.</hi> In such an exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence <note place="margin">4.</note> as this, What should the <hi>Pharisees</hi> and <hi>chief Priests</hi> do? They are shamefully driven by the necessities they are in, to <hi>bribe</hi> the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <note place="margin">12.</note> into a <hi>Lye.</hi> To bribe them (I say) not with <hi>large money alone;</hi> but with a <hi>Promise of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">14.</note>
                  <hi>Impunity</hi> from <hi>Pontius Pilate.</hi> And what but This should their Lye be, (which carries its <hi>Traytor</hi> in its own <hi>Forehead,) His Disciples came by night, and stole him away whilst we slept.</hi> Mark <note place="margin">13.</note> their <hi>confession</hi> that Christ is risen, in the <hi>Act</hi> of their <hi>denying</hi> it: And a <hi>discovery</hi> of their Malice, in their Indeavours of <hi>concealment.</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:204239:17"/> Their Tongues betray them, whether they <hi>slept,</hi> or <hi>slept not;</hi> for if they slept in good earnest, how could they <hi>tell,</hi> (being <hi>awake,)</hi> what was done whilst they were <hi>sleeping?</hi> But if they <hi>slept not;</hi> what was it which induced them to <hi>Say</hi> they slept? They did not <hi>lye,</hi> only to <hi>lye;</hi> but as thinking it was <hi>expedient.</hi> Did they <hi>see</hi> the Disciples stealing Christ out of his Grave? or did they <hi>not?</hi> First, if they <hi>did;</hi> then they were either broad <hi>awake</hi> when they pretended to have <hi>slept,</hi> which is one Contradiction; or else they had a faculty to <hi>see</hi> in <hi>sleeping;</hi> which is <hi>another:</hi> or if secondly they <hi>saw it not;</hi> (and that for this reason, <hi>because they slept;)</hi> how could they <hi>testifie</hi> as <hi>Watchmen,</hi> what was <hi>done,</hi> and who <hi>did</hi> it? Again, either <hi>All,</hi> or only <hi>some</hi> of their Number slept. If only <hi>some;</hi> why did not <hi>they</hi> who were <hi>awake,</hi> if <hi>not strong</hi> enough to <hi>resist,</hi> rouze up their <hi>fellows</hi> to their <hi>Assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance?</hi> or if they were strong enough of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; why would they suffer to be <hi>done,</hi> what they <hi>watcht</hi> on set <hi>purpose</hi> to keep the <hi>weapon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less</hi> and the <hi>weak</hi> from the <hi>doing of?</hi> But if they say, <hi>they All slept;</hi> Then their Testimony is <hi>null;</hi> and the utmost that they can do, is to relate <hi>their own Dreams.</hi> They <hi>dreamt</hi> (forsooth) whilst they were <hi>sleeping,</hi> that Christ was <hi>stoln</hi> out of his Sepulchre; and they <hi>dreamt</hi> his <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:204239:17"/> stole him. Tho' they were <hi>sleeping</hi> all the while, yet they dreamt <hi>what</hi> was done, and they dream't <hi>who</hi> did it. Let the Case be what it will, we see it every way tends to our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, though 'tis most for our Advantage, <hi>they did not sleep;</hi> and were <hi>brib'd</hi> with <hi>large mony,</hi> to <hi>say</hi> they slept. Poor wretched Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings! they only said, <hi>as they were order'd.</hi> They only did, as they were <hi>hired.</hi> They only perform'd what they had <hi>promis'd,</hi> and had been very well <hi>paid for.</hi> And this <hi>Bribery</hi> of the <hi>Sanhedrim was commonly reported among the Jews,</hi> until the Time wherein St. <hi>Matthew</hi> compos'd his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel. <hi>(Matt.</hi> 28. 15.)</p>
               <p>§. 15. Against the <hi>Gentiles</hi> we are to argue, by <hi>other</hi> ways of Conviction, than have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto sufficed against the <hi>Jews. They</hi> must be argued with from their <hi>own Principles,</hi> whether of <hi>Nature,</hi> or of <hi>Philosophy,</hi> of <hi>humane Reason,</hi> or <hi>common Sense.</hi> From the Confession of their <hi>own Writers,</hi> that the Thing is <hi>not Impossible;</hi> and from <hi>some,</hi> that it is <hi>True.</hi> All in reason to be referr'd to another Subject of Discourse. I only add at this present, that <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> and many <hi>others,</hi> the most incomparably lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned amongst the Heathen, have been <hi>effectually</hi> converted to the <hi>Discipleship of Christ,</hi> and to a belief of <hi>Christ's Rising,</hi> even by reading his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204239:18"/>
                  <hi>Divinity</hi> in the <hi>Lives</hi> and the <hi>Deaths</hi> of such as <hi>own'd</hi> him. The <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Martyrs</hi> has been found very often, as well the <hi>Gospel Cement,</hi> as <hi>the Seed of the Church.</hi> How many Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes have been wrought upon by the <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 4. 33.</note>
                  <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Miracles;</hi> or by the powerful <hi>operations</hi> of invisible <hi>Grace;</hi> the Holy <hi>Acts of the Apostles</hi> have made apparent; and so have all the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Histories of the Church.</hi> Even the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euseb. Hist. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>
                  <hi>Tiberius</hi> was so convinc'd of <hi>Christ's Rising,</hi> by some Accounts he had of it from <hi>Pontius Pilate;</hi> that he proposed <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> to the <hi>Roman Senate,</hi> as very worthy of being numbred among their <hi>Gods.</hi> But having spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken enough already in behalf of the <hi>Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, [That Christ is risen from the Dead,]</hi> espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially speaking, as I do, to a <hi>Christian Audience,</hi> a <hi>Congregation of Believers,</hi> who are not now to be <hi>converted,</hi> but only <hi>established</hi> in the Faith; I shall <hi>deliberately</hi> abstain from <hi>other</hi> Topicks of Discourse, until <hi>the Sequel</hi> of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thymeme</hi> shall have its <hi>due Place</hi> in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration: Which being sit to be the Subject of a whole hours Discourse, must by conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence be deferr'd till another Time; whilst I conclude with some good Lessons from what already hath been deliver'd.</p>
               <p>§. 16. If <hi>Christ is risen from the Dead,</hi> in spite
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204239:18"/> of all their fraud and force, who, as soon as they had kill'd him, us'd their utmost Indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to <hi>keep</hi> him <hi>down;</hi> Then it concerns us to contemplate his infinite <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>All-suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience,</hi> as well as his <hi>wisdom</hi> and <hi>goodness</hi> in it. To <hi>kill,</hi> is <hi>easie;</hi> (every <hi>Toad</hi> can do <hi>That;)</hi> But it is not so easie to make <hi>alive.</hi> This is one of God's Works; not communicable to <hi>any,</hi> unless by <hi>Miracle.</hi> Such a Miracle it is, for any one Man to raise <hi>another</hi> from the Dead: and This by miracle has been communicated to <hi>Some.</hi> But for any meer man <hi>to raise himself</hi> from Death to life, is communicable to <hi>None;</hi> no not by <hi>Miracle.</hi> This is so much the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege of <hi>God alone,</hi> He cannot give it to any other; and so our Saviour's <hi>Resurrection</hi> is a strong proof of his <hi>Divinity,</hi> against the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> who are so rife in these days. Three I noted under the Law, who being Dead were rais'd to life, by the Prophets of the <hi>Old</hi> Testament. And besides a great number who are not specified in the <hi>New;</hi> we read of <hi>Five</hi> such examples as are particularly <hi>nam'd.</hi> Our Saviour rais'd his Friend <hi>Lazarus;</hi> the young <note place="margin">Joh. 11. 39. Luk. 7. 12.</note> man of <hi>Naim;</hi> and the Daughter of <hi>Jairus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 8. 55.</note> But 'tis more to our purpose, (because our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was <hi>more</hi> than Man,) that <hi>Dorcas</hi> was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <note place="margin">Act. 9. 40.</note> by St. <hi>Peter;</hi> and <hi>Eutychus</hi> by St. <hi>Paul;</hi> who <note place="margin">Act. 20. 10.</note>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:204239:19"/> were <hi>meer men</hi> assisted by the miraculous Gift of God. Yet None of these Thaumaturgicks, neither <hi>Elijah,</hi> nor <hi>Elisha,</hi> neither St. <hi>Paul,</hi> nor St. <hi>Peter,</hi> (no, no more, than either <hi>Eutychus,</hi> or <hi>Dorcas,)</hi> could raise <hi>Themselves</hi> out of their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres, or state of Death. And accordingly when our Saviour reviv'd the Dead man at <hi>Naim,</hi> (being <hi>laid out</hi> upon the <hi>Bier,)</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <note place="margin">Luk. 7. 14, 16.</note> trembled with astonishment, concluding <hi>Christ a great Prophet; and that was all.</hi> They did not <hi>from thence</hi> infer his <hi>God-head.</hi> But for one and the same Person <hi>to raise himself</hi> out of his Grave, demonstrates <hi>That Man</hi> to be <hi>no meer Mortal;</hi> It demonstrates <hi>That Man</hi> to be <hi>God Incarnate; God manifest in the Flesh; God and Man in one Person,</hi> by an union hypostatical; God who <hi>spake by the Prophets;</hi> not a <hi>Great Prophet only,</hi> as <hi>some</hi> esteem'd him.</p>
               <p>§ 17. Now from a Serious Contemplation of so much <hi>Power,</hi> as was <hi>extended</hi> to our Lord in his <hi>Resurrection,</hi> we ought to gather unto our selves a Christian <hi>Considence</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> in all our <hi>fallings,</hi> how <hi>great</hi> soever our <hi>Falls</hi> may be; not into <hi>Poverty</hi> only, or <hi>Sickness,</hi> but <hi>Death it self.</hi> If <hi>Christ is risen from the Dead,</hi> malgré the utmost opposition of Men and Devils; as easily breaking the <hi>Bands</hi> of Death, as <hi>Samson</hi> did his <hi>green Withs;</hi> it follows then
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:204239:19"/> that we <hi>Christians,</hi> (that is, <hi>Imitators of Christ,)</hi> are of all men the most <hi>happy;</hi> as having the least cause to <hi>fear,</hi> what <hi>Men</hi> or <hi>Devils can do unto us.</hi> 'Tis true, in reference to the <hi>Danger</hi> of <hi>doing</hi> evil, <hi>happy is the man that feareth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways.</hi> But in reference to the <hi>danger</hi> of <hi>Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> evil, and that because we <hi>refuse</hi> to do it, <hi>woe</hi> be to the man that is most <hi>afraid.</hi> For he either <hi>distrusts</hi> God's <hi>Power,</hi> or <hi>suspects</hi> his spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial <hi>providence,</hi> or <hi>despairs</hi> of his <hi>Love,</hi> or <hi>doubts</hi> at least of his <hi>Promises,</hi> and makes <hi>some Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of his <hi>Veracity;</hi> forgets the <hi>Precept</hi> of the Almighty, however frequently promulg'd both in the Old and New Testament. First in the <hi>Old, Fear ye not the reproach of men, nor be afraid</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 51. 7. 8.</note>
                  <hi>of their revilings:</hi> and that for this reason, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Moth shall eat them up like a Garment, and the Worm like wooll.</hi> And again in the New, <hi>Fear not them that can kill the Body:</hi> and that for this reason, <hi>because they are not able to hurt the Soul.</hi> 'Tis a thing worthy of observation, how God <hi>upbraids</hi> his People's Cowardize, and seeks to <hi>shame</hi> them out of their fears. <hi>Who art thou that should'st be afraid of a man that shall dye, and be made as grass? And forgettest thy Maker, who hath stretched out the Heavens, and hath laid the Foundations of the Earth? (Isa.</hi> 51. 12, 13.) for a <hi>Servant,</hi> and a <hi>Soldier,</hi> and withal
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204239:20"/> a younger <hi>Brother</hi> of Jesus Christ, (who <hi>is not ashamed to call us Brethren,</hi> says the Apostle,) to be afraid of his <hi>fellow-Creature,</hi> whose life is in his <hi>Breath,</hi> and whose Breath is in his <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strils,</hi> and whose Foundation is in the <hi>Dust;</hi> to fear a Man that shall <hi>dye,</hi> and <hi>be food for Worms,</hi> and <hi>not at all</hi> to fear <hi>Him,</hi> or to fear him <hi>less,</hi> who can <hi>kill,</hi> and make <hi>alive,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy for ever,</hi> and make us <hi>feel</hi> our selves <hi>dying</hi> to all Eternity, without the <hi>benefit</hi> or the <hi>hope</hi> of a <hi>Dissolution;</hi> This is such an <hi>unworthiness,</hi> as ought not in justice to be <hi>indur'd.</hi> For 'tis implicitly to <hi>deny,</hi> that <hi>Christ is risen from the Dead;</hi> and to abet the Jewish Slander, <hi>That his Disciples stole him away whilst the Watchmen slept.</hi> Yea to stand in <hi>more fear</hi> of our Lord's <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> than of <hi>Himself;</hi> cannot but come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Notion of <hi>flat Idolatry,</hi> and is a <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Abjuration</hi> of His <hi>Divinity.</hi> To <hi>disbelieve</hi> our Lord's <hi>Death,</hi> or to <hi>doubt</hi> of his <hi>Rising</hi> from it, or of his Rising as the <hi>First-fruits</hi> of a <hi>General Harvest;</hi> And <hi>so</hi> to doubt of these things, as to <hi>sink</hi> under the <hi>load</hi> of our <hi>suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> for him, or else to <hi>cast</hi> it from off our <hi>Shoulders,</hi> as if we <hi>suspected</hi> that <hi>Christ himself</hi> can neither <hi>succour</hi> us in <hi>this</hi> World, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite us in the <hi>Next;</hi> This is such a Dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the <hi>Immensity</hi> of his <hi>Power,</hi> and the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204239:20"/>
                  <hi>Veracity</hi> of his <hi>Word,</hi> that I cannot tell how we can <hi>more provoke</hi> him. This may therefore sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest a reason of that strange thing at the first appearance, why St. <hi>John</hi> in his Revelations does rank the <hi>fearful</hi> and <hi>unbelieving</hi> as the great <hi>Ringleaders in Hell,</hi> preceding the <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers,</hi> and <hi>Sorcerers,</hi> and <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and <hi>Liars,</hi> who yet are all to have their portion of <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Brimstone;</hi> because a Man's <hi>Fearfulness</hi> and <hi>Distrust</hi> are apt to be the <hi>Causes</hi> of all the rest; his <hi>Misbelieving</hi> and <hi>Disbelieving,</hi> are univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally the <hi>Flood-gates of all Impiety.</hi> Not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Christ is risen, or <hi>so faintly</hi> to believe it, as to have but a kind of <hi>Suspicion</hi> of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays the <hi>Succours</hi> of the Soul, and stands in an absolute <hi>opposition</hi> to <hi>Ghostly strength;</hi> and makes a Man to be <hi>as wicked,</hi> as the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Flesh,</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> will have him. For in the feebleness of a Man's <hi>Faith</hi> the principal <hi>strength</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> lies. And when we have <hi>Traitors</hi> within our <hi>City,</hi> as well as <hi>weak parts</hi> in our very <hi>Walls,</hi> Temptations take us by way of <hi>Storm;</hi> and <hi>break in</hi> upon us like <hi>Conquering Torrents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 18. There are multitudes of People who seem to have a <hi>strong Faith</hi> in the <hi>Death</hi> of Christ; (believe he <hi>suffer'd</hi> for their <hi>Sins;</hi> That he did by all means, and for <hi>theirs alone;)</hi> but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:204239:21"/> do not seem to <hi>have</hi> an Interest, (nor to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> that they have any,) in the Power and strength of his <hi>Resurrection.</hi> For if at any time they are <hi>troubled,</hi> they are <hi>distress'd</hi> too: if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted a little, they straight conclude they are <hi>forsaken:</hi> or if a little <hi>cast down,</hi> they poorly reckon they are <hi>destroy'd.</hi> All in a perfect <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety</hi> to the Christians of the first Times, who were Christians <hi>in deed,</hi> and not in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Profession</hi> only. For St. <hi>Paul</hi> speaking of <hi>Them</hi> in a conjunction with <hi>Himself, We are troubled</hi> (says He) <hi>on every side, yet not in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress.</hi> Sufficiently <hi>perplexed,</hi> but <hi>not</hi> at all <hi>in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 8, 9.</note>
                  <hi>Despair. Persecuted</hi> we are, but <hi>not forsaken.</hi> And however <hi>cast down,</hi> yet <hi>not destroy'd.</hi> Now from <hi>whence</hi> had they this Constancy, Support, and Courage, but (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> does there say) <note place="margin">Verse 13.</note> from <hi>the Spirit of Faith?</hi> or from the <hi>stedfast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of their <hi>Belief,</hi> that <hi>Christ is risen from the dead?</hi> for so he speaks in the next Verse, <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he who raised up the Lord Jesus from the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">14.</note>
                  <hi>Dead, shall raise up us also by Jesus, and shall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent us with you.</hi> This was the <hi>use</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> made in his <hi>Second</hi> Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> even of this very <hi>Doctrine</hi> which he teacheth them in the First. <hi>Christ is risen from the Dead.</hi> That's his <hi>Doctrine.</hi> From which he raises this <hi>use,</hi> (a use of <hi>Comfort</hi> and <hi>Christian Courage,) Not to</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:204239:21"/>
                  <hi>faint in Tribulations, altho' the outward man pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verse 16.</note> Be it so <hi>that we are always bearing about in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 10, 11.</note>
                  <hi>our bodies the dying of the Lord Jesus;</hi> Be it so <hi>that we are daily deliver'd unto Death for Jesus sake;</hi> yet since the Raiser up of <hi>Jesus</hi> shall raise up <hi>Ʋs</hi> also, and shall <hi>present us unto himself</hi> in the <hi>Face</hi> of Jesus, <hi>therefore we faint not,</hi> (says our Apostle;) but <hi>tho' our outward man perish, our Inward man</hi> notwithstanding <hi>is renewed day by day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 19. This is That our Lord <hi>Loves,</hi> our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a right and proper <hi>Ʋse</hi> of his Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Not only believing it as a <hi>story;</hi> but <hi>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting</hi> to it, as a <hi>Support.</hi> He cannot <hi>indure</hi> to have his <hi>Faithfulness</hi> suspected, or his <hi>Truth</hi> call'd in question, or his <hi>Omnipotence</hi> doubted of. His being <hi>Risen from the dead,</hi> he would have us still <note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 8.</note>
                  <hi>Remember,</hi> and often <hi>revolve</hi> within our selves; He would have us often <hi>ruminate,</hi> and <hi>chew</hi> upon it by Meditation; <hi>lest at any time we be wearied, and faint in our Minds.</hi> Had he only been <hi>Crucified, Dead,</hi> and <hi>Buried,</hi> Then all our <hi>Comfort</hi> had been cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; all our <hi>Faith</hi> had been as dead; and our <hi>Hope</hi> buried. For even a <hi>Dog,</hi> being <hi>alive,</hi> does far surpass a <hi>dead Lyon.</hi> How <hi>sad</hi> and <hi>Hopeless</hi> were the good Women, whilst they only look't <hi>downwards,</hi> and saw the Body of Christ <hi>interr'd?</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:204239:22"/> All their <hi>Hope</hi> was, in their looking <hi>upwards;</hi> in seeing their <hi>Master</hi> when he was <hi>Risen.</hi> And this will be our own best method; not to look on his <hi>Grave,</hi> unless it be as it is <hi>empty;</hi> and to <hi>inforce</hi> upon our selves the Angels say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>two Maries, Why seek ye the Living</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 28. 6.</note>
                  <hi>among the Dead? He is not Here; for he is Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen.</hi> The surest way to <hi>run with Patience the Race of life that is set before us,</hi> is thus to be <hi>looking up to Jesus the Author and Finisher of our Faith, who for the Joy that was set before him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 1, 2.</note>
                  <hi>endured the Cross, despised the shame, and now is sitting on the right hand of the Throne of God:</hi> Incessantly interceding for us, as a well-beloved Son with a Father of Mercies, to whom be Honour and Adoration for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>§. 20. Again, if Christ is so <hi>risen,</hi> as hath been hitherto made apparent; and if we believe it, without the least doubt, or Hesitation; Then let us consider the chiefest <hi>ends</hi> of his Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, in which our selves are most concern'd. That so we may examin, and prove our own selves, whether those ends have been accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished in us, or not. Now the Apostle tells us plainly, <hi>That to this very end Christ dyed, and rose, and revived, that he might be Lord both of the dead and living,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 9. All the fruit which he reap't in his own behoof both in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204239:22"/> his suffering of Death, and in his rising from the Dead, was, that he might have the full prerogative to lord it <hi>over</hi> us, and <hi>in</hi> us: that we might not <hi>live</hi> unto <hi>our selves,</hi> nor <hi>dye</hi> unto <hi>our selves;</hi> (v. 7.) <hi>but that whether we live, we might live unto the Lord; or whether we dye, we might dye unto the Lord:</hi> and the reason of it is evident, because <hi>whether we live, or dye, we are the Lord's,</hi> (v. 8.) not ours, but <hi>his; for he hath bought us with a price.</hi> (1 Cor. 6. 20.) Our life, and our death, whatsoever we have, and whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we are, whatsoever we are able to do, or suffer, we ought not to value them at all in any other consideration, than as by them we may be serviceable in some good Measure to Jesus Christ. When we live in a course of <hi>Sin,</hi> we flatly <hi>say</hi> by our <hi>works,</hi> what the Jews did in <hi>words,</hi> Nolumus hunc, <hi>we will not have this man reign over us.</hi> (Luke 19. 14.) <hi>He shall not be a Lord for us; we will not keep his statutes, nor be observant of his Laws. We like the statutes of</hi> Omri, <hi>and will live by the Law which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant in our members.</hi> This is the language of our <hi>Doings;</hi> when we walk, and <hi>walk on,</hi> in a <hi>Tract</hi> of <hi>Sin.</hi> Let our <hi>Forms of Godliness</hi> be what they will, we do <hi>frustrate</hi> the end of his Dying for us, and defeat him of his purpose in <hi>rising</hi> up from the <hi>dead.</hi> The proper ends
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204239:23"/> of Christ's <hi>Death</hi> and his <hi>Resurrection</hi> are very fitly represented in the <hi>two parts</hi> of <hi>Baptism;</hi> both alluded to by St. <hi>Paul, Colos.</hi> 2. 12. We are <hi>buried</hi> with Christ in <hi>Baptism,</hi> and in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism are <hi>risen</hi> with him. But <hi>Both through Faith of the operation of God, who hath raised him from the dead.</hi> The going <hi>into the water,</hi> relates to Christ's <hi>Burial;</hi> and shews us our obligation of <hi>dying to Sin;</hi> nailing the <hi>Body</hi> of our Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions to our Blessed Saviour's <hi>Cross;</hi> and not only so, but laying them down in his Grave too; never so to rise again, as to have any <hi>Dominion,</hi> or <hi>Power</hi> over us. The <hi>coming out of the water,</hi> relates to Christ's <hi>Resurrection,</hi> and shews us our obligation of <hi>rising</hi> again to the <hi>life of righteousness;</hi> never returning again to <hi>Sin,</hi> any more than Christ Jesus did return into the <hi>Grave;</hi> but still ascending higher and higher, by improvements of Grace, till we <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend</hi> (as he did) unto a perfect consummation of <hi>Bliss</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi> Thus we see our very <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism</hi> does teach us the <hi>uses</hi> we are to make, both of the <hi>dying</hi> of Christ, and of his <hi>rising</hi> from the dead. It is a way of Accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with which St. <hi>Paul</hi> is so well pleased, that he is pleas'd to repeat it in his Epistle to the Romans. <hi>We are buried with him by Baptism in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Death; that like as Christ was raised from the</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:204239:23"/>
                  <hi>Dead, so we also should walk in newness of life: Rom.</hi> 6. 3. Now when as Christians we are <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd,</hi> we do not <hi>dwell</hi> under the water; we are not <hi>down'd.</hi> Just as when our Lord was <hi>buried,</hi> he did but <hi>sojourn</hi> in the Grave; did not lye in it so long, as <hi>to see corruption.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6. 12.</note>
                  <hi>Let not Sin therefore reign in our mortal Bodies;</hi> That's the <hi>Ʋse</hi> we are all to make of it. If un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily we have <hi>dipp't</hi> into Sin; let us not consentingly <hi>lye under</hi> it, till we are <hi>drown'd.</hi> Or if it proves so that we are <hi>dead</hi> in tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passes and Sins; yet let us <hi>rise</hi> by repentance to <hi>newness</hi> of life. Again, when <hi>once</hi> we are <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd,</hi> we are not baptiz'd any more; we do not pass a <hi>second time</hi> under the water; and Christ being <hi>raised from the Dead, dyeth no more; Death hath no more Dominion over him. (Rom.</hi> 6. 9.) We therefore being rais'd from the death of <hi>Sin,</hi> must <hi>sin no more; Sin</hi> must have <hi>no more Dominion over us.</hi> This is the <hi>Ʋse</hi> we are to make of that Allusion. And when these Uses are duly made, we have hit the end of Christ's <hi>dying,</hi> and of his <hi>rising</hi> from the Dead. And therefore,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we may know by this, our <hi>ghostly state and condition;</hi> whether or no we have an Interest in the Death and Resurrection of Jesus Christ. If not in the <hi>later,</hi> we can have
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204239:24"/> none in the <hi>former</hi> to do us good. For our Sins by Christ's <hi>Death</hi> are made but <hi>apt</hi> to be <hi>pardon'd;</hi> they are not <hi>actually pardon'd,</hi> unless by force of his <hi>Resurrection,</hi> and of his media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for us at the right hand of God. He <hi>dyed</hi> for our <hi>sins,</hi> that is, because we had sin'd, and he would <hi>Satisfie</hi> the <hi>justice</hi> we sin'd against. But he <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 4. 25.</note> rose again for our <hi>Justification,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to us <note n="‖" place="margin">Act. 5. 31.</note>
                  <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Remission</hi> of Sins. Yet this the Apostle hath taught us for our Instruction, <hi>that if we have been planted together in the likeness of Christ's Death, we shall be also in the likeness of his Resurrection.</hi> (Rom. 6. 5.) Which is as much as to say, That if we have sincerely <hi>forsaken sin,</hi> (in imitation of <hi>Christ's Death,)</hi> and thereby have been <hi>grafted</hi> into the Body of Christ Jesus, becoming part of the <hi>same Tree</hi> with him, and partaking with him who is the <hi>Root</hi> of the very same <hi>Juice;</hi> we shall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly bring forth the very same <hi>fruits;</hi> and so at last we shall partake of the very same <hi>Harvest.</hi> I say the <hi>same fruits,</hi> as I say the <hi>same Harvest,</hi> though not in <hi>perfection,</hi> at least in <hi>kind. Our fruit will be unto holiness, and the end everlasting life,</hi> Rom. 6. 22. <hi>The Love of Christ will constrain us</hi> (if it <hi>abide</hi> in us indeed) <hi>not to live unto our selves, but unto him who dyed for us, and rose again,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 14, 15. That was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204239:24"/> St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s way of trying, whether or no we <hi>love</hi> Christ, and have attained unto the <hi>Power</hi> of his <hi>Resurrection.</hi> From whence it follows, (which is a sad, but unavoidable Consequence,) that if we live unto <hi>our selves,</hi> and not intirely unto Christ, we fall short of the <hi>End</hi> for <hi>which he dyed and rose again.</hi> If we are not <hi>Purified</hi> in the sense of St. <hi>John,</hi> and become <hi>zealous of good works</hi> in the sense of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> we are not Christ's <hi>peculiar people, Tit.</hi> 2. 11. If we are not <hi>new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> we are <hi>not in Christ,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 17. What then remains for the avoiding of these sequels, and for the certain <hi>Attainment</hi> of that high privilege of being Christ's <hi>peculiar people,</hi> but that we become as <hi>new Creatures?</hi> that <hi>we pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie our selves?</hi> that we be <hi>zealous of good works?</hi> that we live no longer unto <hi>our selves,</hi> but unto him who <hi>dyed for us, and rose again from the dead?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To him therefore who is able to keep us from falling; and to raise us when we are down; and to present us being risen before the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of his Glory with exceeding Joy; To the only wise God our Saviour, who dyed for our sins, and rose again for our Justification, and became the first-fruits of them that slept, be ascribed by us and by all the World, Blessing, and Glory, and Honour, and Power, and Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Thanksgiving, from this day forwards for ever more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:204239:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>§. 1. IN the former Chapter I treated con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a Change in the Body of <hi>Christ;</hi> and took my Rise for that purpose, from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 20. <hi>Christ is risen from the Dead.</hi> Now in as much as <hi>he is</hi> risen, that <hi>we may</hi> rise; And that if we rise <hi>not,</hi> we are <hi>no whit the better</hi> for His being risen: I have thought it most useful, as well as most pertinent and Methodical, to transfer my Meditations from <hi>our Lord's</hi> Body unto <hi>our own;</hi> and so to shew the great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, which the <hi>Change</hi> of <hi>His</hi> Body shall make in <hi>ours.</hi> Not a <hi>Change, quatenus ipsum,</hi> or meerly as it is a <hi>Change;</hi> for even <hi>All</hi> shall be <hi>changed,</hi> without exception, or reserve: whether children of the Devil, or Sons and Daughters of Grace and Glory. <hi>Herod,</hi> as well as <hi>John;</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> as well as <hi>Peter;</hi> and <hi>Hymenaeus,</hi> as well as <hi>Paul;</hi> All <hi>mankind</hi> shall have a <hi>Change,</hi> but not a change unto the <hi>Better;</hi> for most will find it unto the <hi>worse.</hi> Our Saviour's <hi>Flock</hi> is a <hi>little</hi> one, compared with the <hi>greatness</hi> of Satan's <hi>Herd;</hi> and the way to Heaven is but <hi>narrow,</hi> in comparison with the <hi>broad</hi> one which leads to Hell; <hi>the Most</hi> will rise, only to fall: They will <hi>rise</hi> out
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204239:25"/> of a Pit of but <hi>seven foot deep,</hi> that they may <hi>fall</hi> into a <hi>Bottomless,</hi> and <hi>Boundless</hi> Pit. Expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to us by <hi>a Lake, which ever-more burns with Fire and Brimstone.</hi> A most <hi>tremendous</hi> Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, (and more to be deprecated than <hi>None,)</hi> which makes so <hi>lamentable</hi> a Change in the Body of Man. To be changed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by <hi>Christ,</hi> as <hi>Christ</hi> was changed by <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,</hi> from the <hi>Torments</hi> of the Cross, and the <hi>Obscurity</hi> of the Grave, unto a ravishing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Bliss,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> we must be quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and season'd with the Duties here injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed throughout this Chapter. <hi>We must rejoyce in the Lord,</hi> (v. 1.) and so keep <hi>Easter</hi> as a <hi>good Time,</hi> or as <hi>an Holy▪day indeed.</hi> We must <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of evil workers,</hi> (v. 2.) must not have the least fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness. <hi>We must not have confidence in the flesh,</hi> but <hi>worship God in the Spirit,</hi> (v. 3.) <hi>must reckon all things but Dung, for the excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> (v. 8.) we must learn <hi>to know Christ, and the power of his Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, being conformable unto his Death,</hi> (v. 10.) <hi>forgetting those things that are behind, and reaching forth unto those things that are before,</hi> we must press towards the mark, for the price of the high Calling of God in Christ Jesus, (v. 13, 14.) In a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204239:26"/> word, we must be men whose <hi>Conversation is in Heaven,</hi> (v. 20.) St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words are, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> does import, that <hi>Heaven</hi> it self is that <hi>City,</hi> which <hi>we</hi> in <hi>Christ</hi> are made <hi>free of.</hi> And by conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence we must <hi>live</hi> as so many <hi>Citizens of Heaven,</hi> in opposition to the Muckworms, <hi>whose God is their Belly, and whose glory is in their shame, and who mind earthly things,</hi> (v. 19.) Here indeed we have <hi>a City,</hi> but not <hi>a City to abide in; for we seek one to come:</hi> even a City having <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 14.</note> Foundations, the Mystical <hi>Mount Sion, the City</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 22.</note>
                  <hi>of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem.</hi> There dwells our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and our <hi>Prince,</hi> There sits our <hi>Advocate,</hi> and our <hi>Judge.</hi> There we <hi>ought</hi> to be <hi>already,</hi> at least in our <hi>Minds,</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations.</hi> We must contemplate those things which will lead us <hi>Thither.</hi> We must regulate our Lives by the <hi>Laws</hi> of that City. Our <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity</hi> must be the <hi>Practice,</hi> not only the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession</hi> of heavenly life and Conversation. And when once we have attain'd to this degree of Perfection, (by making use of that Grace our Lord has given us,) then we may say touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our selves without Vanity or falshood, (as once St. <hi>Paul</hi> of his <hi>Ephesians,) we are not strangers, and foreigners,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Fellow-Citizens of the Saints, and of the Houshold</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 19.</note>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:204239:26"/>
                  <hi>of God;</hi> Then we may boast with <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> and with <hi>Seneca's Wise Man, Potiore nostri parte</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Senec. Epist.</hi> 41.</note>
                  <hi>illic sumus unde descendimus:</hi> Our <hi>Better</hi> part is still <hi>There,</hi> from whence we derived our Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal; and from whence we look with <hi>long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> (not with <hi>Terror,</hi> or <hi>Consternation,)</hi> for the most glorious and final Advent of our Lord Jesus Christ; <hi>who shall change our vile Body, that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 21.</note>
                  <hi>it may be fashioned like unto his glorious Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 2. A Promise carrying with it its own As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance: for 'tis founded in his <hi>Omnipotence,</hi> his <hi>mighty Power, who is able</hi> (saith St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the next words after this Text) <hi>to subdue all things unto Himself.</hi> And 'tis a Promise made up of as many Parts, as Logicians commonly reckon in the whole Predicament of Action. As,</p>
               <p>First, the <hi>Action it self:</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he will <hi>transfigure,</hi> (so the Greek;) or he will <hi>change,</hi> (so the <hi>English.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>the Agent:</hi> and That is briefly imply'd in the Pronoun <hi>Who;</hi> but expressed to us at large in the Verse precedent, by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Patient,</hi> or the <hi>Subject,</hi> or the <hi>Recipient</hi> of the Action: and That is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> not the Spirit, but the <hi>Flesh.</hi> Many Heathens did belive the Immortality of the <hi>Soul;</hi> But <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he shall change <hi>our Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:204239:27"/>
               <p> Next the <hi>Terminus à quo,</hi> the abject <hi>Term</hi> or <hi>Condition,</hi> from which our Body is to be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,) from its state of <hi>Humility,</hi> (so the Greek,) or of its <hi>Vileness,</hi> (so the English.) A <hi>Vile</hi> Body it is, as being evermore abnoxious to all the miseries upon Earth; and again, a <hi>Vile</hi> Body, as being <hi>sown in Dishonour,</hi> and <hi>in Corruption,</hi> wherein the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 43.</note> Maggots and other Vermin will have the picking of its Eyes out, and make their Nests within its skin.</p>
               <p>Lastly, the <hi>Terminus ad quem,</hi> the Glorious <hi>Term,</hi> or <hi>Condition,</hi> into which 'tis to be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, into a <hi>likeness</hi> or <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> with the <hi>Body of Christ's Glory,</hi> (so the Greek,) or <hi>like unto his Glorious Body,</hi> (so the English.)</p>
               <p>Thus we see what shall befall us at the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Resurrection.</hi> A miraculous <hi>Change</hi> shall be wrought upon us. We see by <hi>whom,</hi> and from <hi>whence,</hi> and to what admirable <hi>Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi> and after what <hi>manner</hi> we shall be <hi>changed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 3. But I must first of all speak to <hi>the change it self,</hi> without relation to any <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance</hi> wherewith the change is to be <hi>cloath'd.</hi> And I must render such <hi>Reasons</hi> for it, as may serve for so many <hi>Arguments</hi> or <hi>Corroborations</hi> of our Belief. For when St. <hi>Paul</hi> preaching at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:204239:27"/> did but nakedly <hi>affirm</hi> the Resurrection of the Dead, without an addition of <hi>Reasons</hi> for it, most of his Auditors fell to <hi>mock</hi> him. All their <hi>use</hi> of the <hi>Sermon</hi> was their <hi>Derision</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 17. 32.</note> of the <hi>Preacher.</hi> And considering we live in an <hi>Iron Age;</hi> an Age whose very <hi>Iron</hi> has gather'd <hi>Rust</hi> too; which is a sign that we are fallen into those <hi>last dregs of Time,</hi> whereof 'twas said by our Saviour by way of Prophecy, <hi>when the Son of Man cometh, shall he find Faith upon the Earth?</hi> (that is to say, <hi>He shall Not;)</hi> I say considering these things; the World has need of being convinced, that there is really such a thing as a <hi>Resurrection.</hi> Men are such <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducees</hi> in their <hi>Actions,</hi> such arrant <hi>Herodians</hi> in their <hi>Lives,</hi> that 'tis hard to think them <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> in <hi>Heart,</hi> or <hi>Head,</hi> or in any thing more, than the <hi>bare Profession.</hi> For <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Manners</hi> do hold proportion with one another. When Faith is very well <hi>rooted,</hi> not only in the <hi>Heads,</hi> but the <hi>Hearts</hi> of men, it will infallibly <hi>shoot forth</hi> into excellent good <hi>Fruit,</hi> as well as <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> But do we not live amongst some, whose Hearts are so <hi>full</hi> of <hi>Infidelity,</hi> and so much more than <hi>Brimfull,</hi> as not to be able to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> it from <hi>running over?</hi> Are there not some, whose very <hi>Hearts</hi> are <hi>breaking out</hi> often at their <hi>Mouths,</hi> and their <hi>Fingers ends,</hi> whilst they
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:204239:28"/> stick not to say and write, that <hi>they were born at all adventure, and that they shall dye as they were born?</hi> that <hi>their Bodies shall become Ashes, and their Souls vanish as the soft air, and that Both shall be hereafter, just as if they had never been?</hi> Such as <hi>These</hi> are to be <hi>humbled,</hi> and kept in <hi>Awe</hi> by dreadful <hi>Assertions</hi> and <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satives</hi> of the two last Articles in our Creed, <hi>the Resurrection of the Body, and the Life Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 4. <hi>Others</hi> on the other hand are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly fed with <hi>Hope,</hi> that <hi>what they now sow in Tears, they shall reap in Joy:</hi> And that their <hi>Body</hi> shall be as <hi>Precious,</hi> as now 'tis <hi>Vile.</hi> That he who at present <hi>goeth on his way weeping, shall come again with great Gladness</hi> at the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Harvest,</hi> and shall <hi>bring his sheaves with</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 19.</note>
                  <hi>him. If in this life alone we had hope in Christ,</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> argues to the <hi>Corinthians,) we were of all men in the worst Condition;</hi> especially when we suffer the <hi>greatest</hi> evils, rather than consent to commit <hi>the least.</hi> As good be <hi>any thing,</hi> as a <hi>Christian;</hi> were it not for <hi>this change.</hi> A <hi>persecuted</hi> Saint would be good for nothing. <note place="margin">2 Macc. c. 6. &amp;c 7. Heb 11. 35.</note> Unto what <hi>end</hi> did <hi>Eleazar</hi> refuse the offers of a <hi>Deliverance,</hi> if (after all) he may not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy by so much <hi>a better Resurrection?</hi> or to what purpose did our Apostle <hi>fight the good</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:204239:28"/>
                  <hi>sight of Faith</hi> through all imaginable hardships, if there is no such thing at last, as a <hi>Crown of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 32.</note>
                  <hi>Righteousness?</hi> we might <hi>call the</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Mal. 3. 15, 17.</note>
                  <hi>proud happy, and bless the workers of Iniquity,</hi> in case there were not a Day to come, <hi>when God will bind up his Jewels.</hi> Death would indeed be <hi>the King of Terrors,</hi> (as <hi>Bildad</hi> told his friend <hi>Job,)</hi> if to <hi>dye</hi> were to <hi>Perish,</hi> and to be <hi>shut out of the World.</hi> Lord! what a melancholick Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <note place="margin">Job 18. 14.</note> should a Man make upon his <hi>Grave,</hi> wherein he cannot escape his being a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>(eaten of Worms</hi> when he is <hi>dead,</hi> as <hi>Herod</hi> was whilst he was <hi>living,)</hi> were he not able to <hi>look beyond it,</hi> and say with the Confidence of <hi>Job</hi> to his insulting friend <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad,</hi> I absolutely <hi>Know my Redeemer liveth?</hi> It <note place="margin">Job 19 25, 26, &amp;c.</note> being revealed to me from Heaven, and deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imprinted upon my Heart, <hi>that he shall stand</hi> (as a Triumpher) <hi>in the last day upon the Earth: and tho' Worms, after my skin, shall destroy this Body, yet in my Flesh shall I see God: and not with other, but with these same Eyes.</hi> This was spoken by a <hi>Gentile,</hi> (for such was holy <hi>Job</hi> in the Land of <hi>Ʋz,)</hi> not from the meer strength of <hi>Reason,</hi> or the Reserches of Philosophy; but from the Dictates of Divinity, and supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Revelation, which made him <hi>infallible</hi> in his <hi>Believing</hi> (what he therefore call'd his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:204239:29"/>
                  <hi>Knowing,)</hi> the <hi>Resurrection of his Flesh</hi> in the Day of Judgment. So that in <hi>Job</hi> we have an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of that <hi>divine Faith,</hi> which is said to be the <hi>Evidence of things not seen, and the substance of things hoped for,</hi> Heb. 11. 1. Had he not spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as an <hi>Enthusiast,</hi> and from the whisperings of <hi>the Spirit,</hi> St. <hi>Jerome</hi> could never have said with truth, what yet he did with great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, that <hi>no man living since Christ</hi> has so <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nullus tam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertè post Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum, quàm ista ante Christum, de Resurrectione loquitur.</hi> S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. in locum.</note> explicitly and so plainly expressed this Article of our Creed <hi>[the Resurrection of the Body,]</hi> as He who liv'd an <hi>Idumaean,</hi> as well before <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> as <hi>before Christ,</hi> who was not born of the Virgin till 1600 <hi>years after.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 5. Now to establish our own <hi>Assurance</hi> of <hi>Faith and Hope,</hi> that our <hi>Bodies</hi> shall not be <hi>lost,</hi> but rather safely <hi>laid up,</hi> and kindly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted (as to a <hi>Guardian)</hi> to the close Custody of the Earth, and only dissolv'd into the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> as certain <hi>Repositories</hi> or <hi>Vessels,</hi> from which they will be <hi>forth-coming</hi> upon the sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the last Trumpet, exactly marshalled and disciplin'd in Rank and File, at the great and general muster of the Lord God of Hosts, who will no more make us a <hi>Militant,</hi> but (from thenceforth) a <hi>Triumphant</hi> Army, no longer to <hi>sight,</hi> but to be <hi>crown'd</hi> (for having fought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Christ's Banner;) Let us premise a few Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:204239:29"/> as <hi>Fortifications</hi> of our <hi>Belief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 6. The <hi>first</hi> of these is to be drawn from the Consideration of our <hi>Creation:</hi> Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which <hi>God</hi> said to <hi>Adam, Thou shalt return unto the Ground, for out of it wast thou taken.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 19.</note>
                  <hi>Dust thou art, and to Dust shalt thou return.</hi> There we see how our <hi>Beginning</hi> affords us an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of our <hi>End:</hi> and how our <hi>End</hi> yields us an Argument, whereby to assert our <hi>New Beginning.</hi> For if <hi>once</hi> out of the Ground, why not <hi>again?</hi> if <hi>created</hi> out of the <hi>Earth,</hi> why not <hi>restor'd?</hi> It cannot certainly be so <hi>hard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Difficilior est mutatio à non esse simplici, quàm à non esse Tali.</note> or so <hi>strange</hi> a thing, to be <hi>recover'd</hi> out of the <hi>Dirt,</hi> into which (before we were) we could not have had a <hi>Dissolution.</hi> Admit our <hi>Death</hi> were a <hi>Reduction</hi> into an indigested <hi>Chaos;</hi> and from thence into that ancient and primitive <hi>Nothing,</hi> out of which the <hi>Rude Chaos</hi> was first <hi>Created;</hi> yet still a <hi>Second</hi> Result from <hi>Nothing,</hi> would be as possible as a <hi>First:</hi> And if we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a fesibility in the <hi>Creation</hi> of our Bodies, a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation</hi> of the same, we can never stick at. He who could <hi>make</hi> us out of Nothing, can out of Nothing <hi>remake</hi> us. This is a Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence undeniable from the Hypothesis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd, in case 'twere every whit as true, as we know 'tis false. But we are taught by plain <hi>Experience,</hi> (the Irresistible Mistriss of our As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,)
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:204239:30"/> that what we commonly call <hi>Death,</hi> is indeed nothing more than a <hi>Dissolution.</hi> A <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution</hi> is nothing more, than an <hi>unloosing of the Compages;</hi> not a <hi>Nulling</hi> of the <hi>Ingredients,</hi> whereof a Body is made up. A <hi>taking asunder</hi> of our materials; not a <hi>total cessation</hi> of them. We have a clearer comprehension of what we <hi>shall be</hi> when we are <hi>Buried,</hi> than 'tis possible for us to have of what we <hi>were,</hi> e're we were <hi>Born.</hi> And with This the generous <hi>Mother</hi> (in the <hi>second</hi> Book of the <hi>Maccabees)</hi> excited her <hi>Children</hi> to their <hi>Martyrdoms,</hi> which <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Tyrant prepared for them. <hi>I cannot tell you</hi> (my dearest Sons) <hi>how ye came into my womb.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Macc. 7. 22, 23, &amp;c.</note>
                  <hi>I neither gave you your Breath; nor form'd your Members. Neither is it I, but the Creator of the World,</hi> by whom ye are what ye are; by whose assistance from above, <hi>ye regard not your lives for his Laws sake; and who will also, of his own mercy, give you Breath and life again. O my Sons, have pity on me;</hi> and suffer bravely those Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <note place="margin">Ver. 27, 28, &amp;c.</note> which now attend you. <hi>Look on the Heaven and the Earth, and consider God made them of things that were not; and fear not this Tormentor.</hi> Now I proceed, with that woman, to argue Thus: When <hi>Earth</hi> was taken out of <hi>Nothing,</hi> and a Man's <hi>Body</hi> out of the <hi>Earth;</hi> 'tis plain the <hi>Body</hi> of Man was <hi>Nothing,</hi> at one
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:204239:30"/> or two <hi>Removes</hi> at most: And 'tis much a greater step from Nothing to <hi>Something,</hi> than from <hi>one</hi> thing to <hi>Another,</hi> or from the <hi>Same</hi> unto <hi>It self.</hi> So that if we can <hi>believe</hi> the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Body, sure its <hi>Resuscitation</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>doubt of.</hi> We have the <hi>word</hi> of God affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, as well the <hi>one,</hi> as the <hi>other.</hi> And the later (to common Reason) is less astonishing, than the <hi>former.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 7. A second Argument is to be drawn from the <hi>Dignity</hi> of a <hi>Man</hi> above other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. God was pleas'd to make Man but <hi>little lower than the Angels,</hi> giving him Mastery or <hi>Dominion over the work of his hands.</hi> Touching the <hi>other Creatures,</hi> he said, <hi>Let there be light, and there was light. Let there be a Firmament, and so it was.</hi> He did not say, <hi>Let there be Man, and there was Man;</hi> But <hi>faciamus, Let us make him;</hi> and let us make him <hi>after our Likeness.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26.</note> Nor did he only form <hi>Man of the Dust of the Ground;</hi> But also <hi>breath'd into his Nostrils the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 7.</note>
                  <hi>Breath of life.</hi> And can we imagin it to be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that God will suffer his <hi>Noblest</hi> Creature to perish for ever in the Earth? to lose <hi>one</hi> part of his <hi>two Essentials?</hi> That <hi>Vaginam Afflatûs Dei,</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> somewhere calls it,) That choice <hi>Repository,</hi> or <hi>Case,</hi> in which he was pleas'd to <hi>sheath</hi> his <hi>Breath?</hi> That goodly <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:204239:31"/> or <hi>Tent,</hi> wherein it pleased himself to <hi>dwell,</hi> by an <hi>Incarnation?</hi> No sure (says <hi>Job,</hi> concerning God, to God himself,) <hi>He will have a Desire unto the work of his own Hands.</hi> He who <note place="margin">Job 14. 15.</note>
                  <hi>Breathed</hi> into <hi>our Nostrils the Breath of life,</hi> will never so <hi>blow upon</hi> us with the <hi>Breath of his Displeasure,</hi> as wholly to <hi>blast</hi> what he has <hi>planted</hi> in this his low and inferiour <hi>Nursery;</hi> But will infallibly <hi>transplant</hi> us (in due time and <hi>season)</hi> to flourish as <hi>Trees of Immortality about the River of Life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 21. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>§. 8. A Third Argument may be taken from the changes which are wrought on Inferiour Creatures: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the world <hi>without</hi> us is full of <hi>changes;</hi> and many <hi>Changes</hi> we observe of the world <hi>within</hi> us. Things <hi>go out,</hi> and <hi>come in,</hi> shifting their <hi>Properties,</hi> or their <hi>Places,</hi> and many times their very <hi>Shapes;</hi> and then return (as in a Circle) to the Condition they were in, at their <hi>setting out.</hi> The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture tells us, <note n="*" place="margin">Isa. 40. 6. 1 Pet. 1. 24.</note>
                  <hi>All Flesh is Grass.</hi> Experience tells us, <hi>All Grass is Flesh.</hi> There being <hi>a change and Resurrection</hi> of the <hi>one</hi> out of the <hi>other.</hi> For all manner of <hi>Flesh,</hi> being putrified and corrupted, does serve to fatten and feed the <hi>Earth.</hi> The Earth becomes fruitful, and brings forth <hi>Grass.</hi> The Grass becomes Food for the Flesh of <hi>Beasts.</hi> The Flesh of Beasts becomes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:204239:31"/> Food for the Flesh of <hi>Men.</hi> And we know the Flesh of Men is again turn'd into the <hi>Earth.</hi> Thus we see there is a <hi>Circle</hi> of several chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; all as <hi>remarkable,</hi> as they are <hi>obvious.</hi> All flesh is grass, at the first setting out; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at long running, all grass is flesh. Such <hi>Circular motions and mutations</hi> we might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve (if we had Time) in most things else: Not only in all the <hi>Families,</hi> but <hi>Forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> in the world. There is observable in <hi>Polybius</hi> an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Circulation of Conditions or Forms of Politie, whereof the first and best is <hi>Monarchy;</hi> which sooner or later is corrupted into <hi>Tyranny;</hi> That again into <hi>Oligarchy;</hi> and This into <hi>Democraty;</hi> out of which comes <hi>Ochlocraty;</hi> and <hi>Cheirocraty</hi> out of <hi>That.</hi> Brutish strength in <hi>This last</hi> gives Law to Justice. And the <hi>sole measure of Right,</hi> is either the <hi>length</hi> of a Man's <hi>Sword,</hi> or the <hi>strength and the skill</hi> of the <hi>Hand</hi> that <hi>holds</hi> it. This <hi>Cheirocraty</hi> is indeed <hi>Anarchy;</hi> (a word in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by <hi>Polybius</hi> to import the same thing;) of which when Men are <hi>sick enough,</hi> not to be able to indure it; then they flye by way of Refuge to the Wings of a <hi>Monarch</hi> for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation. Such are the Changes which we observe, (taught by the wisest of Historians amongst the Heathen,) in the <hi>Cycle</hi> of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:204239:32"/> and Commonwealths. And Thus the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of the year do ever <hi>fall,</hi> and <hi>rise up,</hi> into one another. The Day <hi>dyes</hi> every Night, and is <hi>renewed</hi> every Morning. The Spring <hi>expires</hi> into the Summer; and This into the Autumn; That is lost into the Winter; which again perisheth into the Spring. Thence the Year got its <hi>Title</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (a thing becoming <hi>endless,</hi> by still <hi>expiring into It self;)</hi> and thence a <hi>Snake</hi> is made its <hi>Embleme,</hi> by taking his <hi>Tail</hi> into his <hi>Teeth.</hi> Nor is the <hi>Vicissitude</hi> of the <hi>Seasons</hi> of more Remarque in this Case, than the Multitude of Creatures <hi>peculiar</hi> to them. For (not to instance in other Things,) How many Thousands of Inanimate or Sense<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Creatures, which have been buried in the Earth since last <hi>December,</hi> do now injoy a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection</hi> this present <hi>April?</hi> Say then thou <hi>Sadducee,</hi> thou <hi>Jenxuan,</hi> thou <hi>Stupid</hi> Sinner. Dost thou imagin that when thou dyest, thy <hi>Grave</hi> is thy <hi>Dwelling-place for ever?</hi> And that thy Bed is there made in <hi>perpetual Darkness? Thou Fool</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>That which thou sowest, is not quicken'd except it dye.</hi> That which thou takest to be the <hi>End,</hi> is but the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of its Existence; or at least a <hi>Transition,</hi> from a very much <hi>worse,</hi> to a <hi>better</hi> state. Is it not pity a Man of Reason should be <hi>thus</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:204239:32"/> sent to School to the <hi>meanest</hi> Creatures? A <hi>Grain of Wheat</hi> is able to <hi>Teach</hi> thee the <hi>hardest</hi> Article of thy <hi>Creed.</hi> For tho' thou shalt bury it every <hi>Autumn,</hi> yet it will <hi>Rise</hi> every <hi>Spring;</hi> yea as soon as it is <hi>putrified,</hi> it will <hi>peep</hi> out of its <hi>Furrow;</hi> and that as well to <hi>thine,</hi> as its <hi>own</hi> Advantage. Nor could <hi>it perpetuate</hi> its being what now it is; did it not live, and dye by <hi>Turns.</hi> After the very same manner, our Graves are so many <hi>Furrows;</hi> wherein our <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> as so many <hi>Grains,</hi> are not only <hi>Interr'd,</hi> but also <hi>sown</hi> (says St. <hi>Paul)</hi> by the hand of <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 42, 43, 44.</note> Providence; in expectation to be <hi>gather'd</hi> at God's Great <hi>Harvest; gather'd as Wheat into his Garner, whilst the Chaff is burnt up with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable Fire.</hi> Whilst we live in <hi>This</hi> world, the case is plain, we are all <hi>Mortals;</hi> But we are far from being such in the world <hi>to come.</hi> From whence it logically follows, that we are <hi>qualified</hi> by our End, for a new Beginning. And that our <hi>Death</hi> is but a <hi>Door</hi> to a <hi>Life of Glory.</hi> It is our Saviour's own Doctrin both in the <hi>Protasis,</hi> and <hi>Apodosis:</hi> and with much more advantage, than I have given it. <hi>Except a Corn of Wheat fall into the Ground and dye, it abideth alone:</hi> It is a fruitless, and worthless, monastick thing; like a Barren dry Tree which incumbereth the Ground; fit for nothing, but
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:204239:33"/> to be burnt. <hi>But if it dye, it bringeth forth much fruit: (Joh.</hi> 12. 24.) There lyes its Interest, and its honour; Its <hi>Dying</hi> is its <hi>Introduction</hi> to its <hi>Fertility,</hi> and <hi>Increase.</hi> This he applies unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and calls his being <hi>murder'd,</hi> his being <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified</hi> on Earth: (v. 23.) which cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a reference to the <hi>Conversion of the Gentiles,</hi> (whose Posterity we are,) and other <hi>glorious</hi> effects, as well of his <hi>Death,</hi> as his <hi>Resurrection.</hi> He did not <hi>Rise,</hi> till he was down. Nor can <hi>we</hi> be <hi>quick'ned,</hi> except <hi>we dye:</hi> And what we vulgarly use to call the <hi>Last</hi> day of our <hi>Life,</hi> is indeed the very <hi>First</hi> of our <hi>Immortality.</hi> So far it is from being a <hi>Miracle,</hi> for so <hi>miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> a <hi>Change</hi> to be wrought upon us; that <hi>a Want</hi> of This Miracle, would of all miracles be the <hi>Greatest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 9. A fourth Argument may be rais'd from the Consideration of our <hi>Redemption;</hi> which God was pleased to bring about, by humbly taking upon him the Nature, not of <hi>Angels,</hi> but of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and by consequence of <hi>Adam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 16, &amp;c.</note> and in Him of all <hi>Mankind.</hi> Nor did He take it on him by <hi>Halves;</hi> not the Nature of <hi>half</hi> a man; not <hi>one</hi> part, without the <hi>other;</hi> But he assum'd the <hi>whole</hi> Nature; the Nature of the <hi>Body,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Soul.</hi> The Word was <note place="margin">Joh. 1. 14. Act. 2. 30. 1. Pet. 3. 18. &amp; 4. 1.</note> made <hi>Flesh,</hi> and dwelt among us. He suffer'd
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:204239:33"/> for us <hi>in the Flesh.</hi> It was his <hi>Flesh,</hi> which was Crucified, dead, and buried. And what was it but his <hi>Flesh,</hi> which rose again the Third day? yea even <hi>after</hi> his Resurrection, the most In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous of the <hi>Twelve</hi> did thrust his Fingers into his <hi>Flesh; Handle me, and see,</hi> (said our Lord to <hi>Thomas) for a Spirit hath not flesh and bone, as ye see me have.</hi> Now such as was <hi>Christ</hi>'s Resurrection, such must be the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of <hi>them that are Christ</hi>'s. For he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the <hi>First-fruits;</hi> which shew the Nature of <hi>the whole Crop.</hi> And the First-fruits of them that <hi>slept;</hi> Nor is it the <hi>Spirit,</hi> but the <hi>Flesh,</hi> in reference to which we are said to <hi>sleep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 10. A fifth Argument (like the former) does offer it self from our <hi>Adoption;</hi> and from the intimate Relation between the <hi>Head,</hi> and the <hi>members.</hi> In the <hi>sixth Chapter</hi> of the <hi>first Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> we find as great a share of Honour, done by St. <hi>Paul</hi> unto our <hi>Bodies;</hi> as may very well satisfie the highest Ambition of our <hi>Souls. The Body is for the Lord, and the Lord for the Body.</hi> (v. 13.) <hi>Know ye not that your Bodies are Members of Christ?</hi> (v. 15.) <hi>Know ye not that your Body is the Temple of the Holy Ghost?</hi> (v. 19.) Nay <hi>ye are not your own, but are bought with a Price: therefore glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God in your Body, because it is not yours, but</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:204239:34"/>
                  <hi>God's</hi> (v. 20.) From all which Premises we may well argue Thus. <hi>1st,</hi> If Christ is that <hi>Head,</hi> whereof our <hi>Bodies</hi> are the <hi>members;</hi> the Body of <hi>Christ</hi> cannot be <hi>perfect,</hi> without the Addition of <hi>our own.</hi> Head and Members are <hi>Relata secundum esse;</hi> whereof the one cannot subsist without relation to the other. Next, if our Body is for the Lord, and the Lord for the Body; Then must our Body be raised up, if not for <hi>our</hi> sake, yet for <hi>the Lord's. 3dly,</hi> If our Body is the <hi>Holy Ghost's Temple;</hi> Then he will not <hi>destroy</hi> it, unless it be to <hi>rear it up;</hi> that so the <hi>Glory of the later Temple</hi> (in this sense also) <hi>may much exceed</hi> that of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: That what is sown in <hi>Corruption,</hi> may be raised in Incorruption; that what is sown in <hi>Dishonour,</hi> may be raised in Glory; that what is sown in much <hi>weakness,</hi> may be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed again in Power; that what is sown a <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> Body, may be raised a Spiritual body. The <hi>second</hi> Temple of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> did not so much excel the <hi>first,</hi> as a man's <hi>Body,</hi> being <hi>raised,</hi> will excel its <hi>old self. 4ly,</hi> and lastly, if God expects to be <hi>glorified</hi> both in our <hi>Body,</hi> and in our <hi>Spirit,</hi> and that because they are Both <hi>His;</hi> Then God Himself must needs <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risie,</hi> as well the <hi>one,</hi> as the <hi>other.</hi> But the <hi>Grave cannot praise him; Death cannot celebrate him;</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:204239:34"/> They that go down unto the Pit cannot shew forth his Truth; if there is no such thing at all as a <hi>Resurrection.</hi> We might expostulate, like the <hi>Psalmist,</hi> were it not for <hi>this Change; Dost thou show wonders among the Dead? or shall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal 88. 10, 11, 12.</note>
                  <hi>the Dead give thanks unto thee? shall thy loving kindness be shewed in the Grave? or thy Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in Destruction? shall thy wond' rous works be known in the Dark? or thy righteousness in the Land where all things are forgotten?</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 6. 5.</note>
                  <hi>No man remembreth thee in Death; and who will give thee thanks in the Pit?</hi> It follows therefore unavoidably; that seeing God will be <hi>glorified,</hi> as well in our <hi>Body,</hi> as in our <hi>Soul, He will change our vile Body, that it may be fashioned like unto his Glorious Body.</hi> And we may say with our Apostle, that <hi>as the whole Creation groaneth and travelleth in pain until now, so we our selves do also groan within our selves, waiting for the Adoption, to wit, the Redemption of our Body. (Rom.</hi> 8. 23.)</p>
               <p>§. 11. A sixth Argument is to be urged (to All who are not <hi>Antiscripturists)</hi> from the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Testimonies</hi> and <hi>Pledges,</hi> which are exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to us in Scripture, of a <hi>Corporeal Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> In the <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> we read of <hi>Women who received their Dead raised to life</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 35.</note>
                  <hi>again,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (says the original) <hi>by way of</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:204239:35"/>
                  <hi>Resurrection.</hi> She of <hi>Sarepta</hi> was <hi>one;</hi> and the <note place="margin">1 King. 17. 21.</note>
                  <hi>Shunamite</hi> was <hi>another. Dorcas</hi> was raised by <note place="margin">2 Kin. 4. 34, 35.</note> St. <hi>Peter;</hi> and <hi>Eutychus</hi> by St. <hi>Paul;</hi> the Youth <note place="margin">Act. 9. Acts 20. Luke 7. 14.</note> of <hi>Naim</hi> by <hi>Christ Himself;</hi> who called <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> out of his Sepulchre, from a state of <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 11. 43, 44.</note> as well as <hi>Death.</hi> These he raised when he was <hi>living,</hi> but many <hi>more</hi> when he was <hi>Dead;</hi> as St. <hi>Matthew</hi> tells us. For many <note place="margin">Matth 27. 51, 52, 53.</note>
                  <hi>Graves</hi> were then <hi>opened,</hi> and <hi>many Bodies of Saints which slept arose.</hi> Yea no sooner was our Lord <hi>Risen,</hi> than the Dead Bodies so reviving <hi>went as far out of their Graves, as the Holy City;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Notum est Illud Thaddaei apud Euseb. Hist. l.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <hi>and there appeared unto many, who were quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to attest</hi> their <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Burial.</hi> These were the <hi>Earliest</hi> of that <hi>later Crop,</hi> or that <hi>Harvest</hi> of men reviv'd, who followed <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>First-Fruits.</hi> For however some of These, in point of Time went <hi>before</hi> him according to <hi>the Flesh,</hi> yet they were raised by <hi>His</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, who was <hi>the Lamb slain from the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the World.</hi> Add to this our Saviour's <hi>parable</hi> in the 16. of St. <hi>Luke;</hi> where <hi>Dives</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>Abraham's Bosom,</hi> (for so the Jews express't <hi>Paradise)</hi> desired the <hi>Cooling</hi> of his <hi>Tongue</hi> with <hi>Lazarus</hi> his <hi>Finger.</hi> Both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the <hi>Resurrection</hi> of all Men's <hi>Bodies;</hi> which a <hi>Tongue</hi> and a <hi>Finger</hi> must needs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. So we are bid <hi>to fear Him who can cast</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:204239:35"/>
                  <hi>both Body and Soul into Hell.</hi> And if there are <hi>Bodies</hi> of men in <hi>Hell,</hi> much more in <hi>Heaven;</hi> in as much as the <hi>Reward</hi> of God's <hi>Loyal</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, must rather <hi>exceed,</hi> than <hi>fall short,</hi> of the <hi>Punishments</hi> inflicted on his <hi>Rebellious</hi> ones.</p>
               <p>§. 12. A seventh Argument for the proving a <hi>Resurrection</hi> of the Body, (and that without the help of Scripture, or <hi>supernatural</hi> Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,) may be naturally supply'd from the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality</hi> of the <hi>Soul.</hi> For if the <hi>Soul</hi> and the <hi>Body</hi> must fare alike, (which from the <hi>Justice</hi> of the Almighty 'twill not be difficult to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince;) then either the <hi>Soul</hi> ought to be <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> to fare <hi>no better</hi> than the <hi>Body;</hi> or else the <hi>Body</hi> must be <hi>Immortal,</hi> to fare <hi>as well</hi> as the <hi>Soul.</hi> The <hi>Immortality</hi> of a dead <hi>Body</hi> cannot possibly be effected, but by the means of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection.</hi> The <hi>Immortality</hi> of the <hi>Soul</hi> will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from hence; that every thing in the World must have a <hi>Center. That</hi> alone is our <hi>Center,</hi> which gives a <hi>Rest</hi> and satisfaction to all our Tendencies, and <hi>Desires.</hi> And nothing less can give us <hi>That;</hi> than <hi>an eternal</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding weight of Glory.</hi> An absolute endlesness of life; and consummation of Injoyments; wherein are <hi>Pleasures unexpressible for ever more.</hi> But no such thing in <hi>This</hi> World, is to be <hi>had,</hi> or <hi>hoped for;</hi> and therefore such there
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:204239:36"/> must be in the World <hi>to come.</hi> It's true, the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> are at odds, what <hi>kind</hi> of Appetite it is, which <hi>all</hi> men have to a <hi>Summum Bonum;</hi> to a <hi>Perfection</hi> of <hi>Beatitude;</hi> to an <hi>Eternity of Happiness,</hi> or <hi>endless Bliss.</hi> Whether such an Appetite is <hi>supernatural,</hi> or <hi>natural;</hi> whether <hi>elicit,</hi> or <hi>innate;</hi> whether <hi>potential</hi> only, or <hi>actual; Durandus</hi> and <hi>Scotus</hi> going <hi>one</hi> way; <hi>Paludanus,</hi> and <hi>Sotus</hi> quite <hi>another;</hi> (which yet they take to be the same,) <hi>Cajetan</hi> a <hi>Third; Ferrarius</hi> a <hi>Fourth;</hi> and <hi>Vasquez</hi> somewhat dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vasquez in</hi> 1. 2<hi>dae. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Q.</hi> 5. <hi>Art.</hi> 8.</note> from All before him. But <hi>all agree</hi> upon the Main; that all rational Creatures have a Tendency of their Appetites to <hi>endless Bliss;</hi> An <hi>Abhorrence</hi> of <hi>Extinction;</hi> and a <hi>Desire</hi> of <hi>Immortality;</hi> as that is ever-more attended with the <hi>perfection</hi> of <hi>Delight.</hi> And <hi>no Vacuum</hi> being allowable, in <hi>Grace,</hi> or <hi>Nature;</hi> 'Tis plain our <hi>Souls</hi> cannot be <hi>adequate</hi> unto the <hi>Object</hi> of our <hi>Desires,</hi> unless by being as <hi>Immortal,</hi> as that is <hi>Infinite,</hi> and <hi>Immense.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 13. But because I put a stress upon the <hi>Justice</hi> of the Almighty, in saying our <hi>Bodies</hi> and our <hi>Souls</hi> are to <hi>fare alike;</hi> therefore this our seventh Argument is to be fortified with an eighth. And because <hi>Divine Justice</hi> is both <hi>Vindicative,</hi> and <hi>Distributive,</hi> as it respects its <hi>Two Objects,</hi> whereof the one is of <hi>Punishment,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:204239:36"/> and the other of <hi>Reward;</hi> Therefore This my last Topick is to consist of <hi>Two Branches;</hi> and I must argue from both apart.</p>
               <p>In respect of the former, <hi>Abraham</hi> took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him his Confidence to <hi>expostulate</hi> with his <hi>Maker;</hi> tho' in a modest and meek <hi>Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment</hi> of his own being but <hi>Dust</hi> and <hi>Ashes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 23-25.</note>
                  <hi>Wilt thou destroy the Righteous with the wicked? That be far from thee. Shall not the Judge of all the Earth do right?</hi> And by a parity of reason, we our selves who are also but <hi>Dust</hi> and <hi>Ashes,</hi> may reason the Case with our Creator in fear and reverence. Will not God punish the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the wicked? Will He be rather an <hi>Accepter</hi> of any man's <hi>Parts,</hi> than of his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son?</hi> Shall not the Body be a <hi>Partaker,</hi> as well in <hi>Suffering,</hi> as in <hi>Sin?</hi> The Flesh is <hi>accessary</hi> at least to <hi>All</hi> the Sins that are committed; and it seems in <hi>many</hi> of them to be the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Malefactor.</hi> As when the <hi>Flesh lusteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 17.</note>
                  <hi>the Spirit:</hi> and when <hi>a Law in the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers does wage a War against a Law in the mind.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 23.</note> There are (apparently enough) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>peculiar Sins of the Body;</hi> such as <hi>Drunkenness,</hi> and <hi>Whoredom,</hi> which the <hi>Devil</hi> cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, because of his being <hi>All Soul.</hi> And <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>peculiar sins of the Soul;</hi> such as <hi>Envy,</hi> and <hi>Maliciousness, Pride,</hi> and <hi>Arrogance,</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:204239:37"/> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> which are the <hi>filthiness of the Spirit,</hi> as <hi>carnal uncleanness</hi> is of the <hi>Flesh:</hi> And these were the sins of the lapsed <hi>Angels,</hi> which had <hi>no Bodies at all;</hi> for they were <hi>sinners</hi> even in <hi>heaven,</hi> before they were or could be doom'd to be <hi>Devils in Hell.</hi> And the Rule in our Law, [that no legal Process can be made against an <hi>Accessary,</hi> in case the <hi>Principal Offenders</hi> cannot be caught or appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, because The <hi>Principal</hi> in the <hi>Offence</hi> ought to be <hi>first</hi> in the <hi>Inditement,]</hi> does thus far hold in the Court of Heaven; that the <hi>Spirit</hi> of a man shall not go <hi>solely</hi> into Hell, for the <hi>Lustings of his Flesh against</hi> his Spirit. His <hi>mind</hi> shall never be tormented to all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity <hi>without his Members,</hi> for the <hi>Warring</hi> of his <hi>Members against his mind.</hi> The Righteous Judge of all the World will neither punish the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary,</hi> and let the <hi>Principal</hi> go free; Nor suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the <hi>Spirit</hi> as a <hi>Principal</hi> to bear the whole <hi>Brunt</hi> in the <hi>Condemnation,</hi> when <hi>the Flesh</hi> as an <hi>Accessary</hi> has had its <hi>Share</hi> in the <hi>Transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</hi> Neither the <hi>Flesh</hi> nor the <hi>Spirit</hi> shall suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>singly,</hi> for Sins committed by Both <hi>conjoyn'd.</hi> So that the <hi>Bodies</hi> of the <hi>Impenitent</hi> must needs be rais'd out of their Graves, that they may have an equal share in the sad eternity of their <hi>Souls.</hi> That God may render to every <hi>Man,</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:204239:37"/> (who is compounded of <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body,)</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 6.</note> to his Deeds. That Sinners having <note n="*" place="margin">Mar. 9. v. 43. to v. 48.</note>
                  <hi>Hands and Feet</hi> may be cast into Hell. That every one may receive the things done in his <hi>Body,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. where 'tis observable how much the <hi>Greek</hi> is more emphatical than the <hi>English.</hi> Our <hi>English</hi> Bibles do only read, [that every one may receive the Things done <hi>in</hi> his Body,] as if the <hi>Soul</hi> only had done them, and the Body had been the <hi>Work-house</hi> wherein she acted. But the <hi>original</hi> says better, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that every one may receive, <hi>or carry away as his Reward</hi> (for <hi>That</hi> is imported by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) the Things done <hi>by</hi> his Body, as <hi>by</hi> a very special <hi>Instrument,</hi> and <hi>cause</hi> of working; Not a meer <hi>Work-house,</hi> or <hi>Shop</hi> to <hi>work in.</hi> Yea there are not only <hi>Manuscripts,</hi> but <hi>Printed</hi> Copies, (and particularly that of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Se the most Learned Dr.</hi> Hammond, <hi>on</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 10.</note> the <hi>Complutenses,)</hi> which have in stead of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is to say, the <hi>pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar</hi> and <hi>proper</hi> things of the Body; as when the <hi>Body</hi> is the <hi>Principal,</hi> not a meer <hi>Accessary</hi> in Sin. And Thus a <hi>Bodily Resurrection</hi> may be inferred from the former, the Almighty's <hi>Corrective,</hi> or <hi>Vindicative Justice,</hi> to whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone <hi>Vengeance of right belongs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In respect of the Later, his <hi>Justice Distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butive,</hi> as he is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a Rewarder</hi> (by way
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:204239:38"/> of eminence) of them who <hi>diligently seek him,</hi> we are not only to argue His <hi>raising up</hi> our Vile Bodies, But his advancing them <hi>to the Better;</hi> from the state of their <hi>Vileness</hi> to that of <hi>Glory.</hi> For <hi>shall not the Judge of all the world do what is equitable, and Right?</hi> Is it not equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and Right, (in regard of That <hi>Covenant</hi> which God in Christ has made with us,) that every one of our <hi>Bodies</hi> should have its Part in the <hi>Wages,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Work</hi> of our <hi>Master Christ?</hi> Shall the Body of St. <hi>Peter</hi> be shamefully <hi>Crucified</hi> in <hi>This</hi> world, and shall it not be <hi>glorified</hi> in <hi>That to come?</hi> Shall the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of <hi>other</hi> Martyrs who were condemned to the <hi>Grid-iron,</hi> be made to <hi>shine</hi> no whit the <hi>brighter</hi> for being <hi>burnt?</hi> when we crucifie our selves by a Mortification of our Affections, whether with <hi>Watching,</hi> or <hi>Fasting,</hi> or other Austerities of Life, what is it but the <hi>Body</hi> which is deprived of its <hi>Delights?</hi> for we know the <hi>Pale Cheek,</hi> and the <hi>Hollow Eye,</hi> the <hi>akeing Head,</hi> and the <hi>shirt of Sackcloth,</hi> are things too gross, and too passive, to touch the <hi>Soul;</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less it be by her <hi>Partnership</hi> in the Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>Body.</hi> And shall our <hi>Bodies</hi> be rewarded for all their <hi>Watchings,</hi> with nothing more than an <hi>endless sleep?</hi> or be <hi>imprison'd</hi> within the Grave, as a Recompence sufficient
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:204239:38"/> for all their <hi>Bonds?</hi> Shall the <hi>Absence</hi> only of <hi>Pain</hi> become the uttermost Amends for their <hi>loss of Pleasure?</hi> It cannot be. For God is <hi>swift to shew Mercy,</hi> and <hi>slow to wrath:</hi> Nor is He said to be a <hi>God ready to punish, but a God rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to pardon,</hi> Nehem. 9. 17. His Punishments are commonly <hi>below</hi> our Merits, whereas his Rewards are still <hi>above</hi> them. When 'tis said by the Psalmist of those two Attributes, God's <hi>Mercy,</hi> and his <hi>Justice,</hi> that the one reacheth unto the <hi>Heavens,</hi> and the other unto the <hi>Clouds;</hi> Tho' 'tis not meant that one Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute is more <hi>extensive</hi> than the other, (for Both being <hi>Infinite,</hi> must needs be <hi>equal;)</hi> yet it implies He's more delighted in <hi>exhibiting</hi> the <hi>one,</hi> than in <hi>executing</hi> the <hi>other.</hi> And All I argue from it is <hi>This,</hi> that if the <hi>Bodies</hi> of the <hi>Impenitent</hi> shall be raised up in <hi>Justice,</hi> to be cast into <hi>Hell;</hi> much more will God in <hi>Mercy,</hi> raise up the <hi>Bodies</hi> of the <hi>Repentant,</hi> to the end they may receive their Reward in <hi>Heaven.</hi> 'Tis true He is (what he is call'd) <hi>A Consuming Fire.</hi> 'Tis true, that <hi>Vengeance is His, and He will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay it;</hi> enough to keep us (one would think) from <hi>Carnal Security,</hi> and <hi>Presumption.</hi> But 'tis as true, that to defend us from too much <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> and <hi>Despair,</hi> He sets Himself out in the most <hi>winning,</hi> and most <hi>exhilarating</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:204239:39"/> to be imagin'd: As the <hi>Father of Mercies, the God of All Consolation, the Lord God that Healeth us, the Saviour and Deliverer in whom we Trust;</hi> In a word, the <hi>Rewarder of such as diligently seek him.</hi> This is the Office He delights in; He loves to be <hi>laying up Crowns of Righteousness;</hi> He loves to be saying, <hi>Well done good and faithful Servants, enter you into the Joy of your Lord;</hi> and so by a consequence unavoidable, He loves to <hi>change our Vile Body, that it may be fashioned like unto his Glorious Body, according to the mighty</hi> [Irresistible] <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereby he is able to Subdue All things unto Himself.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 14. And this would lead me (if I had Time, or if 'twere useful to be tedious, which I think can never be,) from the <hi>Change</hi> we hope for, to the <hi>Author</hi> of it. From the <hi>Action</hi> to the <hi>Agent,</hi> briefly imply'd in the Pronoun <hi>Who,</hi> the first syllable of the Text; and <hi>expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed</hi> to us <hi>at large</hi> in the next words going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. But that being reserved for another Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of your Patience, I shall conclude and dismiss the present Subject of my Discourse, with indeed a very <hi>short,</hi> but yet a very <hi>suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> Use, and Application of the whole. This I shall ground in a Reflection on what I said in the Beginning; that <hi>Men as Men</hi> shall have
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:204239:39"/> a <hi>Change</hi> of their Moulder'd Bodies, But not a change <hi>unto the better.</hi> Every Body shall be rais'd by the <hi>Power</hi> of Christ, as of a <hi>Judge;</hi> But every Body shall not be rais'd by the <hi>Love</hi> of Christ, as of a <hi>Saviour.</hi> Many Bodies shall <hi>so</hi> be raised, as ardently to wish they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver risen. They will be found to be so <hi>vile,</hi> by being polluted with <hi>Impenitence,</hi> and <hi>obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> as not to be capable of the Change which now we speak of. And therefore They will long to have the <hi>Mountains fall on them;</hi> and will intreat the <hi>Hills to cover them; to hide them from the Face of Him that sitteth upon the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb.</hi> Now to the end we may <hi>escape</hi> such a <hi>deplorable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection,</hi> as well as <hi>attain</hi> unto a <hi>better;</hi> we must consider that <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> is but <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally</hi> a Saviour, <hi>who will change our Vile body, and fashion it like unto his Glorious Body,</hi> Not by a <hi>peremptory Volition</hi> to make us happy, let our Life and Conversation be what it will: He will not do it <hi>so irresistibly,</hi> as in <hi>spite of our selves,</hi> and our own <hi>Impenitence,</hi> and even <hi>whether we will or no;</hi> But he will do it irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistibly with <hi>this proviso,</hi> that we prepare our selves for it, and <hi>begin</hi> the Great work of our <hi>last Change</hi> whilst we are <hi>here.</hi> (as for example.) He whose <hi>Body</hi> is made <hi>Vile,</hi> either by <hi>Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenness,</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:204239:40"/> or <hi>Swearing,</hi> by <hi>Fornication,</hi> or <hi>Adultery,</hi> by <hi>Rebellion,</hi> or <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> by <hi>Hypocrisie,</hi> or <hi>Fraud,</hi> or any other the like uncleanness, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther carnal, or spiritual,) must not <hi>stay</hi> for his change until the general Resurrection; but <hi>Presently change his Vile body,</hi> (from this very instant wherein I speak,) and make it <hi>like the Queen's Daughter,</hi> all <hi>glorious within;</hi> by emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Temperance,</hi> and <hi>Sobriety;</hi> by <hi>inoffensive Communication;</hi> by words which are <hi>edifying,</hi> and useful, and <hi>ministring Grace unto the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> by <hi>chast and exemplary Converse; by regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and honest, and upright Dealing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 15. Which <hi>change of Body</hi> cannot begin, but by <hi>a change of Soul first.</hi> For as the Lines in any Body of any figure in Geometry, do not naturally flow from the <hi>Perimeter</hi> to the <hi>Center;</hi> but from the <hi>Center</hi> to the <hi>Perimeter;</hi> so the <hi>Thoughts</hi> of our <hi>Hearts</hi> come not <hi>first</hi> from our <hi>Actions;</hi> but our <hi>Actions</hi> are <hi>first</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the <hi>Thoughts</hi> of our <hi>Hearts.</hi> And by consequence our <hi>Thoughts</hi> must be bestow'd from hence <hi>forwards,</hi> upon <hi>Objects</hi> more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, and more divine than <hi>heretofore.</hi> We must be at <hi>Enmity with the World,</hi> whose fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and friendship for the time past we may have <hi>coveted</hi> and <hi>courted</hi> with too much zeal: and we must <hi>settle our Affections on Things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:204239:40"/> We must be all of such <hi>changed and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured</hi> Minds, as to <hi>love</hi> the <hi>good</hi> things we have at any time <hi>loath'd;</hi> and so as to <hi>loath</hi> the <hi>ill</hi> things we have ever <hi>lov'd.</hi> This is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to change our Minds,</hi> in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel-Notion of <hi>Repentance;</hi> which of all words in Scripture is best express't by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, says the Baptist, <hi>Repent,</hi> or <hi>change your minds,</hi> for the Kingdom of heaven is at hand. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (says our Saviour) <hi>Repent,</hi> or <hi>change your minds,</hi> and believe the Gospel. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, says St. <hi>Peter, Repent,</hi> or <hi>change your minds,</hi> that your Sins may be blotted out. <hi>If any man is in Christ</hi> (says St. <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Corinthians) he is a new Creature:</hi> That is to say, <hi>he has changed his</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17.</note>
                  <hi>mind. Old things</hi> (says he again) <hi>are passed away, and behold all things are become new.</hi> (v. 18.) Here's <hi>a change,</hi> with a witness, of every man and woman who is <hi>in Christ:</hi> And <hi>in Christ</hi> we must be, before our <hi>Bodies</hi> can be <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied;</hi> or so much as be rid of their present <hi>Vileness.</hi> Our <hi>state</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> must be founded in one of <hi>Grace.</hi> The Sacrament of the Lord's Supper is not only a <hi>sign,</hi> but a <hi>means</hi> of Grace. We do not only receive it, as a token that we have <hi>some;</hi> but also to the end we may abound <hi>more and more.</hi> What we call a <hi>Communion</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, is indeed a <hi>Communication</hi> (as the word
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:204239:41"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> does most significantly import,) <hi>of the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 16.</note>
                  <hi>Body and Blood of Christ,</hi> with all the Benefits of his Passion. It is not only an <hi>Index,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so an <hi>Instrument of Conveyance.</hi> It helps to <hi>change our vile body,</hi> through the Vertue which it derives from the <hi>body of Christ.</hi> It is not only a <hi>Seal</hi> of our <hi>Christian Faith;</hi> But also an <hi>Earnest</hi> and a <hi>Pledge</hi> of our <hi>Resurrection.</hi> If we approach the Lord's Supper, with a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> Repentance of all our Sins; with a <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Repentance</hi> of all we <hi>know,</hi> or can <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member;</hi> and with a <hi>general</hi> Repentance of all we <hi>know not,</hi> or have <hi>forgotten;</hi> (for when we have repented the most we can, we must be fain to cry out with the holy Psalmist, <hi>O cleanse thou us from our Secret Sins;)</hi> with love and charity to our Neighbours, (as well our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies as our Friends;) and with unfeigned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions of Better life; (which must consist in <hi>fearing God, and in keeping his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;)</hi> If I say we <hi>thus</hi> approach, and <hi>thus</hi> receive the Lord's Supper; He will so spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually <hi>feed</hi> us with his <hi>Crucified Body,</hi> as to <hi>crucifie</hi> in us also <hi>the body of Sin.</hi> And having removed so great a <hi>Weight,</hi> as would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise press us down to the <hi>lowest Hell;</hi> He will transform us into <hi>Citizens, and Saints of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:204239:41"/>
               <p> Where with Angels, and Arch-Angels, and all the Hierarchy of Heaven, we shall spend our <hi>whole Time</hi> (I should rather have said our <hi>Whole Eternity)</hi> in singing Hosannahs and Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujahs; <hi>Blessing, Glory, Honour, and Power, to Him that liveth for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>§. 1. HAving discoursed in the first Chapter, of the <hi>Change</hi> which was made in the Body of <hi>Christ;</hi> I proceeded in the second, from our <hi>Lord</hi>'s Body, unto our <hi>own;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to shew the great Advantage, which the Change of <hi>his</hi> Body shall make in <hi>ours.</hi> A Change which I proved by many such Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and perswasives, as I did hope would All suffice for <hi>Fortifications</hi> of our <hi>Belief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It now remains that I advance, from The <hi>Change</hi> we hope for, to the <hi>Author</hi> of it: from the <hi>Action,</hi> to the Agent, briefly imply'd in the Pronoun <hi>Who,</hi> the first syllable of the Text; and expressed to us at large in the next words going before: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</hi> If the eight Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments going before have not <hi>won</hi> our Assent,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:204239:42"/> we have a Ninth still behind which will <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> it. Our greatest Assurance of the <hi>Action</hi> is from the Condition of the <hi>Agent;</hi> who being <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>The Lord,</hi> si therefore <hi>Able</hi> to do the work; and being <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>The Saviour,</hi> is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Willing.</hi> His being <hi>the Christ,</hi> speaks his <hi>Power;</hi> His being <hi>the Jesus,</hi> his <hi>Propensity.</hi> Tho' <hi>Christ</hi> does signific <hi>a Lord,</hi> and <hi>Jesus</hi> a <hi>Saviour;</hi> yet without fear of a Tautology, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presseth the Agent's Nature, by All Four Names; <hi>our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</hi> 'Tis <hi>He</hi> shall change our Vile Body; 'Tis <hi>He</hi> shall make it like to his Glorious Body.</p>
               <p>'Tis He shall do it in <hi>Three Respects.</hi> First, <hi>He,</hi> as he is <hi>God.</hi> Secondly, <hi>He,</hi> as he is <hi>Man.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>He,</hi> as <hi>Mediator</hi> 'twixt God and Man. <hi>He,</hi> in respect of his <hi>Divine;</hi> and <hi>He,</hi> in respect of his <hi>Humane</hi> Nature; and <hi>He,</hi> in respect of his <hi>Single Person,</hi> into which his <hi>two Natures</hi> are Both <hi>united.</hi> As he is <hi>God,</hi> we have his <hi>Power;</hi> as he is <hi>Man,</hi> his <hi>propensity;</hi> as God and Man in <hi>one person,</hi> his <hi>peculiarity</hi> to the work. He is, as <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Efficient</hi> Cause of our Resurrection; as <hi>Man,</hi> the <hi>Exemplary;</hi> as Both united, the <hi>Meritorious.</hi> And thus we have the subdivision of the first syllable in the Text, the Pronoun <hi>who.</hi> So that now I am to argue, from the <hi>Three-fold</hi> Capacity of the <hi>Agent;</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:204239:42"/> both that he <hi>can,</hi> and that he <hi>will,</hi> and that 'tis <hi>fit</hi> he <hi>should</hi> raise up our mouldered Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. The first as <hi>God;</hi> the next as <hi>Man;</hi> the third as <hi>Mediator.</hi> After which when I shall prove, not only that it <hi>may,</hi> but <hi>must</hi> be Thus, by vertue of an <hi>Obligation</hi> which he in <hi>mercy</hi> hath been pleased to lay most strictly upon himself; I shall (I think) have done the All which Flesh and Blood can desire, in order to our having a <hi>full Assurance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 2. First to consider him as <hi>God,</hi> is <hi>ipso facto,</hi> to stop the Mouth of all our <hi>Diffidences,</hi> and <hi>Doubts.</hi> For that <hi>God (who was in Christ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling the world unto himself)</hi> hath obliged himself by <hi>promise,</hi> to be the Author of our last and our greatest Change; and that the Thing which he hath promis'd, He can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and bring to pass; cannot but satisfie us more (if we have any <hi>Christian Faith)</hi> than <hi>a Thousand Reasons.</hi> When God was about to promise <hi>Abraham,</hi> that <hi>He would make him the Father of many Nations, and that Kings should come out of him;</hi> He prepared <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Faith</hi> with this Expression of Himself, <hi>I am the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 1.</note>
                  <hi>God.</hi> Where the word <hi>Almighty</hi> does carry a world of <hi>weight</hi> with it; enough to dissipate the Doubts of the weakest <hi>Didymus.</hi> So when <hi>Sarah</hi> could not <hi>believe</hi> that she should
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:204239:43"/> bring forth a Son, being already as good as Dead, (both <hi>old,</hi> and <hi>barren;)</hi> The Angel up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided her Incredulity, by putting her in mind of God's <hi>Omnipotence: Is any thing too hard for the Lord? Gen.</hi> 18. 14. where 'tis observable, how he answers one Question with Another. <hi>Sarah laughed within her self; shall I have plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure now I am old, my Lord being old also? But why</hi> (saith the Angel) <hi>did Sarah laugh?</hi> and laughing, ask such a Question? <hi>Is there</hi> any thing in the world too hard for <hi>God?</hi> hath he not <hi>promis'd?</hi> and is he not able to <hi>make it good?</hi> Dares <hi>Sarah</hi> measure <hi>his</hi> Power, by the pitiful narrow limits of Her <hi>Conception?</hi> Let it suffice that he is <hi>God;</hi> and that by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>God,</hi> he must needs be True. Let it suffice that being God, he must needs be <hi>Almighty,</hi> as well as <hi>True.</hi> Let it suffice that <hi>he</hi> has said it, who can do <hi>above all we can ask or think.</hi> So the <hi>Angel</hi> thought fit to argue; and so must <hi>we.</hi> If we find our selves <hi>doubting</hi> the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Flesh; and <hi>as loth</hi> to have our Bodies again committed to the Dust, as if we thought they should <hi>never Rise;</hi> we must en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter <hi>our own</hi> Distrusts, just as the Angel en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter'd <hi>Sarah</hi>'s: And reason thus within our selves, Can any change of our Bodies be too difficult for the <hi>Almighty?</hi> Or can <hi>he</hi> who is
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:204239:43"/> Almighty, be any other than <hi>All-sufficient?</hi> Cannot he call us out of the <hi>Earth,</hi> who call'd the <hi>Earth</hi> out of <hi>Nothing?</hi> What was <hi>Sarah</hi> in her old Age, but a Clod of unfruitful and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren <hi>Earth?</hi> a great deal fitter to <hi>bury</hi> Isaac, than either to <hi>breed</hi> him, or <hi>bring</hi> him <hi>forth.</hi> From whence 'tis obvious thus to argue. If God was able of such a <hi>Stone, to raise up Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unto Abraham;</hi> He is as able out of the <hi>Earth</hi> to raise up <hi>Abraham</hi> unto <hi>Himself. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (says the Text) was <hi>as good as Dead,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, flatly <hi>Dead as to the office of Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> in this particular respect, he was as dead as the Dirt he trod on,) when yet an Issue sprang from him, as numerous as the Stars. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 12. And thence it was he did not scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>to offer up his Dear Isaac</hi> at God's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; because he knew that God was <hi>able to raise him up from the Dead.</hi> (Vers. 19.) yes he knew it by experience; <hi>as having received him from the Dead.</hi> (v. 12. &amp; 19.) From whence it follows unavoidably; that <hi>Abraham's Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> is no whit stranger than <hi>Isaac's Birth;</hi> because in the <hi>first</hi> is nothing <hi>more</hi> than a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle; and in the <hi>second</hi> nothing <hi>less.</hi> For let us go on to make Demands, in imitation of the Angel. Cannot <hi>he</hi> who makes the <hi>Phoenix</hi> to flourish out of her own Funerals, and bids
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:204239:44"/> the <hi>Tulip</hi> spring forth from the noysomest <hi>Dunghill,</hi> put such a <hi>Spirit</hi> into our <hi>Ashes,</hi> as shall be able both to <hi>unite,</hi> and <hi>refine</hi> them too? Not only <hi>Raise</hi> our vile Bodies; but <hi>Change</hi> them also as they are <hi>rising?</hi> Cannot <hi>he</hi> who has ordain'd, that Clouds shall rise out of the Ocean, And falling down into the Rivers, shall return into the Ocean from whence they Rose, command our Souls to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inspirit our Moulder'd Bodies? Cannot He who <hi>could do every thing in the five last Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Job,</hi> do <hi>This one thing</hi> in the Third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Philippians?</hi> Methinks that <hi>Enoch</hi>'s <hi>Translation,</hi> and <hi>Elias his mounting up</hi> in a fiery Chariot, and the wonderful <hi>Reflorescence</hi> of <hi>Aaron's dead Rod,</hi> yea every Tree <hi>dying in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and <hi>living</hi> again the next <hi>Spring,</hi> should be sufficient to convince us of God's Ability even with Ease, to raise again our dead Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and that with a greater force of reason, than this last Instance; For <hi>we</hi> have a <hi>great</hi> Accompt to give; whereas <hi>Aaron's dead Rod</hi> and the <hi>Trees</hi> have <hi>None.</hi> He who buries each Day in the shadow of Death, (for such is the darkness of the Night,) and again does con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the shadow of Death into the Morning, is the very same <hi>He, who turneth Man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction; and saith, Come again ye children of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 90. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:204239:44"/>
               <p> §. 3. But let us argue from this Topick of Christ <hi>as God,</hi> a little more fully, and by degrees. First <hi>as God</hi> he is <hi>omniscient,</hi> and therefore knows where to find us; whether <hi>drown'd,</hi> or <hi>burnt,</hi> or deeply <hi>Hid</hi> within the <hi>Earth,</hi> or else <hi>hung up</hi> in the Empty <hi>Air,</hi> as Malefactors and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs are wont to be. Although our Bodies are made a Prey to the Crows and Harpyes, and being crumbled into Dust, are scatter'd abroad by the four Winds; yet <hi>he</hi> who is <note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 139. 6.</note>
                  <hi>every where</hi> according to his <hi>Essence,</hi> and cannot choose but see <hi>every thing</hi> according to his <hi>Omniscience,</hi> does keep a Register of our <hi>Ashes;</hi> as well as of our <hi>Actions,</hi> and <hi>idle words.</hi> If the <hi>hairs of our head</hi> are number'd by him, (as our Saviour tells us they are, <hi>Matt.</hi> 10. 13.) he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not sure but keep account of the several noble parts of the <hi>Head it self.</hi> If the <hi>Tears</hi> of God's Servants are said to be put into his <hi>Bottle;</hi> sure the <hi>members</hi> of our Bodies must needs be recorded in his <hi>Book.</hi> And for this we have Scripture, as well as Reason. For as one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet says, He has a <hi>Book of Remembrance;</hi> so <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 16.</note> Another does assure us, <hi>That all our Members are written in it.</hi> That we have from <hi>Malachi;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 139. 16.</note> and This from <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 4. Again, as God is Omniscient, and Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipresent, whereby to <hi>know</hi> and to <hi>find out</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:204239:45"/> our Scattered Atomes; and find them out <hi>without seeking;</hi> so is he equally <hi>Omnipotent,</hi> and <hi>All-sufficient;</hi> whereby to <hi>rally</hi> them all up into <hi>Rank</hi> and <hi>File,</hi> in excellent <hi>unity,</hi> and <hi>order.</hi> That Almighty one, who is <hi>able to subdue all things unto Himself,</hi> (in the next words af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my Text,) can <hi>kill Destruction;</hi> can bury Death in a <hi>Regress,</hi> of parts deprived, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Habits;</hi> can <hi>lead Captivity it self a Captive.</hi> And here perhaps I may fitly note, (before I argue any farther from this Topick,) that set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aside God's Omnipotence for a Time; Some would make the <hi>Resurrection</hi> a kind of <hi>Natural Change;</hi> supposing an <hi>Aptitude</hi> in the <hi>Body,</hi> to be re-united unto the <hi>Soul;</hi> and an <hi>Appetite</hi> in the <hi>Soul,</hi> to be re-married unto the <hi>Body.</hi> As if having formerly been acquainted by long and intimate Converse there were in Both a <hi>Disposition</hi> to meet again in one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. And truly the reason of the Conceipt does not want its Plausibility. For besides that the <hi>Soul</hi> may find its way back into the <hi>Body</hi> with greater ease, by being much more <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent</hi> from after the Time of her <hi>Separation;</hi> we know the <hi>Matter</hi> and the <hi>Form</hi> being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>asunder,</hi> cannot add to the <hi>Completion</hi> of Common <hi>Nature;</hi> as they do being united into the dignity of a Person: because the <hi>End</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:204239:45"/> of their <hi>Being</hi> is to be mutually helpful by their <hi>conjunction;</hi> and assisting to the <hi>Ʋniverse</hi> of order'd Bodies, by adding a <hi>prop</hi> to its <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi> Others had an opinion, that after a notable Revolution of 49000 years, Every Creature shall return into That very State, wherein it was in its beginning. So that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to This Hypothesis, (when that <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonick Year</hi> is come, which is called by the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonists, <hi>Annus Magnus,)</hi> I again shall be speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing These very words; and you again shall be attending in Those very Places you now are in. Which, however but a <hi>Conceit,</hi> and the meer child of Imagination, does shew in the <hi>Heathens</hi> a <hi>Disposition</hi> to the <hi>Christian's Belief</hi> of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection:</hi> and that All shall grow <hi>Young,</hi> by being <hi>buried</hi> in reality; as <hi>Aeson</hi> did by being boyl'd in the Poet's <hi>Bath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 5. But notwithstanding, in respect of the two Essential <hi>Parts</hi> to be <hi>Re-united,</hi> the Restau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our Persons may seem agreeable to <hi>Nature;</hi> yet we cannot find out a <hi>Principle,</hi> from whence This union may be <hi>effected,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less we return to the point we left; and with the <hi>strangeness</hi> of the <hi>work,</hi> compare the <hi>omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence</hi> of the <hi>Author.</hi> For <hi>then</hi> 'tis the fitter to be <hi>believ'd,</hi> the harder 'tis to be <hi>comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> It being natural to our <hi>Faith,</hi> (if truly
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:204239:46"/> Christian, and divine,) to be <hi>the Evidence of things Not seen.</hi> Else there would not be such <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 1.</note> a <hi>difference,</hi> as 'tis evident there is, betwixt <hi>Philosophy,</hi> or <hi>Science,</hi> and True <hi>Religion.</hi> God is omnipotent as to All things, which are <hi>not evil;</hi> and do not imply a <hi>Contradiction.</hi> But a change of our Vile Bodies from a very much <hi>worse</hi> to a <hi>better</hi> state, is so far from being evil; that 'tis excellently <hi>Good:</hi> and so far from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying a Contradiction, that 'tis naturally <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient;</hi> (for several reasons already given;) yea 'tis morally <hi>Necessary,</hi> (as hath already been made apparent,) and supernaturally <hi>easie;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' <hi>Miraculous.</hi> For <hi>Miracles</hi> are Natural, to him who is <hi>above</hi> Nature. And all our human <hi>Impossibilities</hi> are reconcileable with <hi>Facility;</hi> to him at whose will and pleasure they owe obedience. Therefore change us he <hi>can,</hi> who is <hi>Omnipotent;</hi> and <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> is Omnipotent, in regard of his Divinity. 'Tis <hi>He</hi> shall change our Vile Body. 'Tis <hi>He</hi> shall do it as he is <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>first</hi> Capacity of the <hi>three</hi> I lately mention'd.</p>
               <p>§. 6. Next consider him as he is <hi>Man;</hi> and so we have his <hi>Propensity</hi> to this great work, which to the act of our Changing, is just as requisite as his <hi>Power.</hi> For 'tis <hi>one</hi> thing to be <hi>able</hi> to do this or that; and quite <hi>Another</hi> to be <hi>willing:</hi> It is as weak arguing <hi>à potentiâ ad</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:204239:46"/>
                  <hi>actum,</hi> as 'tis good and true Logick, to argue <hi>ab Actu ad Potentiam.</hi> Tho' God <hi>can</hi> create a Thousand worlds, besides <hi>This;</hi> it does not follow, that he <hi>will:</hi> And so from <hi>Christ</hi> as he is <hi>God,</hi> we can only evince that we <hi>may</hi> be chang'd; whereas from <hi>Christ</hi> as he is <hi>Man</hi> too, we prove we <hi>shall</hi> be. We are taught by his <hi>God-head,</hi> not to doubt of the <hi>Possibility;</hi> But the Conjunction of his <hi>Manhood</hi> gives us assurance of <hi>the Act.</hi> As <hi>God,</hi> He is easily the <hi>Efficient,</hi> if He sees fit; But as <hi>Man,</hi> He saw it fit to be the <hi>Exemplary</hi> Cause of our Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For as <hi>Man, he was touched with a feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 15.</note>
                  <hi>of our Infirmities.</hi> As Man, he was qualified to be <hi>made like unto his Brethren;</hi> and in that He himself hath suffer'd being tempted, he is <hi>willing,</hi> as well as <hi>able, to succour Them that are</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 17, 18.</note>
                  <hi>tempted.</hi> As man he <hi>dyed,</hi> and rose again; that being <hi>lifted up,</hi> He might <note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 12. 32.</note>
                  <hi>draw us up after him;</hi> and become <hi>the First-fruits of them that slept.</hi> As God indeed he had an <hi>Active;</hi> but as <hi>Man,</hi> a <hi>passive</hi> Power: And so he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by an <hi>Example,</hi> that our Bodies <hi>can</hi> be <hi>raised;</hi> as well as by his <hi>God-head,</hi> that <hi>he</hi> can <hi>raise</hi> them. 'Tis no Diminution to his <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence,</hi> that He Himself cannot <hi>do,</hi> what can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not possibly be <hi>done.</hi> And therefore to shew us a <hi>passive</hi> power which lies in our Bodies,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:204239:47"/> of being <hi>rais'd,</hi> by raising up his own Body, whose Nature was the same with ours; must needs facilitate our Faith of a Resurrection. There is a passage in St. <hi>John</hi> of great remark on this occasion; where 'tis said by our Lord Himself, the power of <hi>executing Judgment</hi> is given by the Father to the Son; <hi>because he is the Son of Man. (Joh.</hi> 5. 27.) And <hi>at the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his voice,</hi> (as the Son of Man,) <hi>the Dead shall come forth out of their Graves.</hi> (v. 28, 29.) And indeed there was a fitness, that what we lost by the <hi>First Adam,</hi> we should recover by the <hi>Second:</hi> That as in <hi>Adam</hi> all dyed, so All in <hi>Adam</hi> too (the <hi>second Adam</hi> I mean) should be made alive. That <hi>as by man came Death, so by man might come the Resurrection of the Dead.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>§. 7. Having thus argued from the <hi>Agent,</hi> implyed by the word <hi>who,</hi> in two respects, to wit of his <hi>divine,</hi> and his humane Nature; I am to argue in the <hi>third</hi> place, from his whole individual <hi>Person;</hi> into which his two Natures are Both united. For if we consider our Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Saviour in <hi>Both</hi> Capacities <hi>Conjoyn'd;</hi> and as a fit <hi>Mediator</hi> 'twixt God and Man; we shall find, in conjunction with his <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensity,</hi> his more especial <hi>propriety</hi> and <hi>peculia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> to the work of our Resurrection. For as he is <hi>such,</hi> he is our <hi>Head;</hi> and 'tis <hi>natural</hi> for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:204239:47"/> the Head, to consult and procure the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of the <hi>Members.</hi> Indeed the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers can never perish, whilst their Head is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live; because of the Intercourse and Amity which is reciprocated between them. 'Tis true, if the Head be <hi>under</hi> water, a man must inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably be <hi>drown'd,</hi> tho' all his <hi>Body</hi> should be <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove</hi> it: But how can a Man be ever drown'd, so long as his <hi>Head</hi> is <hi>above</hi> the Water? After the very same manner; if <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> who is our <hi>Head,</hi> had suffer'd his <hi>Body</hi> in the Grave <hi>to see Corruption;</hi> and had left it quite <hi>behind</hi> him when he ascended into Heaven; Death would have <hi>triumph'd</hi> over our Bodies; Nor could we have said without shame, <hi>O Grave, where is thy Victory?</hi> But now let our <hi>Bodies</hi> lye never so low in the cold Bosom of the Earth; we cannot possibly be <hi>lost,</hi> whilst <hi>Christ our Head</hi> is above the Heavens. That things may live whilst they are buried, we are able to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate by <hi>Worms,</hi> and <hi>Fishes,</hi> which live the better by being buried. Yea there are several living Creatures, which, <hi>unless</hi> they be buried, can <hi>never</hi> live. And whilst <hi>our Head</hi> is out of the Earth; our Grave can be no more, than <hi>a Bed of Rest. Sleep</hi> there may be, but not <hi>Destruction.</hi> (for Then to <hi>dye,</hi> were to <hi>perish,)</hi> Nor can the <hi>last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingness</hi> of our Sleep make it cease to be sleep,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:204239:48"/> so long as it is not <hi>everlasting.</hi> The Death of Beasts is Destruction, because their Souls are as material, and so as mortal as their Bodies; and because they are not accountable for Vice, or Vertue. But in Christians as Christians, and Men as Men, whose Souls are <hi>immaterial,</hi> and so <hi>immortal,</hi> and who have a future account to give of what is <hi>done in the Body;</hi> what greater diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence can there be, betwixt the short <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Sleep,</hi> and the long <hi>sleep</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> than what is meerly <hi>numerical</hi> betwixt <hi>two Brothers?</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the one is of a nobler, and longer <hi>Duration</hi> than the other? if <hi>Sleep</hi> is <hi>good</hi> in <hi>it self,</hi> It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not possibly be the <hi>worse</hi> for being <hi>durable;</hi> and uniterrupted with an <hi>Awake,</hi> until the general <hi>Resurrection.</hi> Duration and Quietness do rather add to the <hi>Value</hi> of it. Were Glass as <hi>durable</hi> as Silver, it would perhaps be as <hi>precious</hi> too. 'Tis fitly said of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> not that he dyed, <hi>but fell asleep,</hi> Act. 7. 60. And as Sleep is <hi>refreshing,</hi> not only <hi>harmless</hi> unto our Bodies; so when the Trumpet shall sound its last <hi>Alarm,</hi> we shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake out of our Graves, like so many <hi>Giants refreshed with Wine,</hi> (as the Psalmist speaks;) and good Reason too. For Jesus Christ as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator has highly <hi>merited</hi> our Rising; tho' <hi>we</hi> have <hi>not.</hi> He having perfected on his Cross, the Redemption of our <hi>Bodies,</hi> as well as Souls.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:204239:48"/> Tho' <hi>we</hi> deserve not at all to be united unto our <hi>Head;</hi> yet our Head deserves richly, to be united unto his <hi>Members.</hi> He arose for Our Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing; not for his <hi>own.</hi> Alas, Blessed Saviour! it had been much better for <hi>Him,</hi> to have left his Body in the Grave, and that for ever; were it not that He was to raise it, to become the <hi>First-fruits of them that slept.</hi> The <hi>Hypostatical Ʋnion</hi> being a Dignity, not to <hi>His,</hi> but <hi>our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> For <hi>Him</hi> to be cloathed with Flesh and Blood, would be at least a <hi>Disparagement,</hi> tho' not a <hi>Detriment</hi> to his God-head; were it not that he is <note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 12. 23-28.</note>
                  <hi>glorified</hi> by <hi>our Salvation.</hi> But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once assumed our humane Nature, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming <hi>flesh of our flesh, and bone of our bone;)</hi> he will as naturally attract <hi>our</hi> Bodies unto his <hi>own,</hi> as a <hi>Load stone</hi> draws the Atomes of Steel or Iron, however <hi>lost</hi> and <hi>unseen</hi> in an Heap of Ashes. The Reason given is from a <hi>Sympathy</hi> between those <hi>Minerals:</hi> And a <hi>Sympathy</hi> still ariseth from a mutual Participation of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry same Spirit. Now that <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> our <hi>Head</hi> does <hi>sympathize</hi> with his Members, the Scripture tells us most expresly, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is the word there us'd to express it by. And that his Members do partake of the very same Spirit, is very sufficiently imply'd by that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> unto the <hi>Romans, If the Spirit of him</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:204239:49"/>
                  <hi>who raised up Jesus from the Dead dwell in us, He who raised up Jesus from the Dead, shall also quicken our Mortal Bodies. (Rom.</hi> 8. 11.)</p>
               <p>§. 8. Being now satisfied of the <hi>Agent,</hi> as God, and Man, and Mediator; both that he <hi>can,</hi> and that he <hi>will,</hi> and that 'tis <hi>fit he should</hi> raise up our Moulder'd Bodies; There is but <hi>one</hi> thing more remaining which Flesh and Blood can <hi>desire,</hi> whereby to establish <hi>a full Assurance;</hi> to wit an <hi>Absolute Necessity,</hi> not only that it <hi>may</hi> be, but over and above that so it <hi>must</hi> be. And that the <hi>freest</hi> of all <hi>Agents</hi> hath been pleas'd to put himself under an <hi>Absolute Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity,</hi> may appear even from hence; that he hath given us such a <hi>Promise,</hi> as makes the thing promised to become a <hi>due Debt.</hi> For He hath enter'd into a <hi>Covenant;</hi> and put himself under an <hi>Obligation.</hi> He hath set his <hi>Seal</hi> to it, even the blood of the new Testament. He hath committed it to <hi>writing;</hi> and that in two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct <hi>Testaments;</hi> the <hi>Old,</hi> and <hi>New.</hi> It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the <hi>Old</hi> by two Authentick and <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Notaries, Isaiah,</hi> and <hi>Daniel;</hi> first by <hi>Isaiah; Thy Dead men shall live, together with my dead</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 26. 19.</note>
                  <hi>body shall they arise; awake, and sing ye that dwell in Dust.</hi> Next by <hi>Daniel; They that sleep</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 12. 2.</note>
                  <hi>in the Dust of the Earth shall awake; some to everlasting life; some to shame, and everlasting</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:204239:49"/>
                  <hi>Confusion.</hi> Thus by <hi>Writing</hi> in the <hi>old</hi> Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and thus in the <hi>New</hi> by word of <hi>Mouth.</hi> For from our Saviour's own <hi>Mouth</hi> These words were taken; <hi>All that are in the Graves</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 5. 29.</note>
                  <hi>shall hear his Voice, and come forth:</hi> And this is recorded by St. <hi>John,</hi> an authentick <hi>Notary of Heaven.</hi> Now because <hi>it is impossible for God to lye;</hi> therefore his giving us a <hi>Promise,</hi> is the binding of himself to a full <hi>Performance.</hi> For if the Promise is <hi>absolute,</hi> it must be <hi>absolutely</hi> performed. And if <hi>conditional,</hi> it must as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be performed upon the performance of the <hi>Conditions</hi> on which the promise was made; as if it were made <hi>without</hi> condition. And see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was his good pleasure, to put himself under an <hi>Obligation;</hi> He not only <hi>may,</hi> but <hi>must</hi> discharge it. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, we expect it. We seize on Bliss by a <hi>Prolepsis.</hi> We take it for granted. Our Eyes and Hearts are set upon it. I will not say in <hi>this</hi> sense, what was said by our Saviour in quite another, <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven suffereth violence, and the Violent take</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 11. 10.</note>
                  <hi>it by force;</hi> but this I will say, without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modesty, or scruple; that through Faith which is <hi>the Substance of things hoped for,</hi> our Dependances and Hopes <hi>take hold</hi> of Heaven. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, from whence <hi>we look for the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, the Lord Jesus Christ, who shall change our</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:204239:50"/>
                  <hi>Vile Body, that it may be fashioned like unto his glorious Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 9. And so I pass from <hi>the Agent</hi> to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>the Subject</hi> on which he <hi>acts:</hi> to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it (I say) not simply in it self, but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with its two <hi>Terms; à quo,</hi> and <hi>ad quem,</hi> from which, and to which, our Body is to be <hi>changed.</hi> The Term <hi>from</hi> which, is a state of <hi>Vileness;</hi> the Term <hi>to</hi> which, is a state of <hi>Glory.</hi> We have them Both expressed plainly in the two clauses of the Text; <hi>He shall change our vile Body,</hi> there's the first: and fashion it like to his <hi>Glorious</hi> Body; there's the second. And first let us consider it in its <hi>Nadir</hi> (as I may say,) or its <hi>Hypogeum;</hi> in the state of its <hi>vileness,</hi> or <hi>Humiliation:</hi> that our deep consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of what it <hi>is,</hi> may make us piously <hi>Ambitious</hi> of what it <hi>shall</hi> be.</p>
               <p>§. 10. Our Body is Vile, and Contemptible, in <hi>Six</hi> respects. First in respect of its <hi>Original;</hi> For it was <hi>taken out of the Ground:</hi> and so was <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 19.</note> the Daughter of the same <hi>Dirt,</hi> into which was first <hi>breathed the Breath of life. Those walls</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 7.</note>
                  <hi>of Mudd</hi> which keep up our <hi>Cottages</hi> and our <hi>Barns,</hi> are exceedingly near <hi>of kin</hi> to the most <hi>delicate</hi> of our <hi>Bodies:</hi> they being descended of the same <hi>Parent;</hi> tho' not indued with the same <hi>Power.</hi> The Dust we <hi>shake from off our</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:204239:50"/>
                  <hi>Feet</hi> with the greatest scorn, may justly flie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our <hi>Faces;</hi> and plead equality of Extraction with All that scorns it. 'Tis true indeed we have a <hi>Treasure;</hi> But we have it (saith our Apostle) <hi>in Earthen Vessels.</hi> Which Earthen Vessels are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 8.</note> from no higher Principle; (that is) They are made of no better stuff, than the <hi>Pitchers</hi> which are design'd for the most despicable Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments. Tho' in regard of our <hi>Immodesty</hi> our <hi>Foreheads</hi> may be of <hi>Brass;</hi> and tho' our <hi>Hearts</hi> may be of <hi>Iron,</hi> in regard of our <hi>Obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> and tho' in regard of our <hi>Inhumanity,</hi> our Bowels may be of <hi>steel;</hi> yet in regard of our <hi>Original,</hi> our <hi>Feet</hi> (like <hi>Dagon</hi>'s) are of <hi>Clay:</hi> and, like <hi>Dagon,</hi> they are as liable to fall in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The <hi>Top</hi> of our Building is but <hi>Rottenness;</hi> and our <hi>Foundation is in the Dust.</hi> We may fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sit down with <hi>Job,</hi> on the <hi>noysom Dunghill;</hi> and say to <hi>Corruption, Thou art our Father; to the Worm, thou art our Mother;</hi> to <hi>Putrefaction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 17. 14.</note> thou art our <hi>Sister;</hi> and to the <hi>Mire,</hi> thou art our <hi>Niece.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 11. Next, the <hi>Body</hi> of Man is <hi>vile,</hi> in respect of the means of its <hi>Derivation:</hi> as being pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted in its <hi>Birth,</hi> and <hi>Conception</hi> too. It has a certain degree of <hi>Vileness,</hi> which cannot <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> be <hi>express't,</hi> unless it be by a <hi>Concealment;</hi> (as <hi>Sem</hi> went backwards, and cast a Mantle
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:204239:51"/> upon his Father;) for even <hi>This</hi> is a kind of Expression too; because the modesty of our <hi>Silence</hi> imports the <hi>Vileness</hi> to be so great, that 'tis <hi>shameful</hi> to discover <hi>how great</hi> it is. 'Tis but agreeable then to reason, that we should All be born <hi>weeping;</hi> and not arrive without <hi>Crying,</hi> at a <hi>Valley of Tears;</hi> for that our <hi>Souls</hi> are <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqu'd</hi> in so vile a <hi>Bottom,</hi> in so turbulent a <hi>Vessel,</hi> as makes our <hi>life</hi> to be subjected to <hi>Storms</hi> and <hi>Tempests:</hi> Which yet would not be, were it not that our <hi>Souls</hi> have such a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement unto our <hi>Bodies.</hi> For we are <hi>born to such Troubles</hi> of Storm and Tempest, (even as naturally says <hi>Job) as the sparks fly upwards;</hi> and were it not for the <hi>Body,</hi> we could no more be <hi>born,</hi> than <hi>see Corruption.</hi> In which respect also it is a <hi>Vile</hi> Body.</p>
               <p>§. 12. Again, the Body of Man is Vile, in respect of its <hi>Duration;</hi> which is exceedingly uncertain, as well as <hi>short. Short</hi> it is even by <hi>Nature;</hi> for <hi>as soon as we are Born, we presently draw towards our End.</hi> And how many ways are there, whereby to frustrate the <hi>Intentions</hi> and <hi>Ends</hi> of Nature? How many are there in the World whose very <hi>Alpha</hi> is their <hi>Omega?</hi> How many who have their <hi>Exit,</hi> before their <hi>Entrance</hi> into the Theatre? who are not born till after their Burial, in the Sepulchre of the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:204239:51"/> Womb wherein they draw their first Breath? How many come <hi>into</hi> the world, (as <hi>Cato</hi> did into the <hi>Theatre,)</hi> as 'twere on purpose to go <hi>out</hi> of it? And even to <hi>us,</hi> who live <hi>longest,</hi> (as weary of the <hi>world,</hi> as the world of <hi>us,)</hi> the term of life is so <hi>uncertain;</hi> that our Souls have not a <hi>Lease,</hi> but are <hi>Tenants at Will</hi> unto our Bodies; Apt to be turn'd out of their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, at very <hi>little</hi> or <hi>no warning:</hi> even at what hour soever our <hi>Landlord</hi> pleaseth. A Term so <hi>secret,</hi> and so <hi>uncertain,</hi> that tho' we <hi>know</hi> it to be <hi>short,</hi> and <hi>to fade away suddenly like the Grass,</hi> (as the Psalmist speaks,) yet we know not <hi>how</hi> short it is. For hence we pray that <hi>God will teach us how to number our days; that he will certifie and inform us, how much or how little we have to live.</hi> Hence it is we pray <note place="margin">Psa. 90. 3. &amp; 12.</note> so often, (by the Appointment of our Church,) against <hi>sudden Death:</hi> that so we may <hi>feel</hi> our selves dying, and not be taken by a <hi>Surprize:</hi> and that at what time soever our Judge shall serve us with an Arrest, he may find us well provided and duly preparing to receive him; that he may find us upon our knees; in the Exercise of our Faith, and the Act of Prayer. And is not That a <hi>Vile</hi> Body, which makes us liable to an <hi>uncertain</hi> and <hi>sudden Death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 13. Fourthly, 'tis a <hi>Vile Body,</hi> in respect of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:204239:52"/> the <hi>Diseases;</hi> (to wit the Anguish of some, and the loathsomness of others,) which are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally born and bred within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. For (not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist on such Diseases as are the <hi>Meazles,</hi> and the <hi>Pox, Erysipelas's</hi> and <hi>Oedema's, Carbuncles</hi> and <hi>Cancers, Biles</hi> and <hi>putrefying Sores,)</hi> There is not an Artery, or a Vein, which is not a room in Nature's Work-house, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> was <hi>Plato</hi>'s word for it,) wherein our <hi>Humours</hi> (like so many <hi>Cyclopses)</hi> are forgeing Instruments of Mortality; <hi>Such</hi> Instruments of Mortality, as every moment of our lives are able to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry us into our Graves. An ordinary <hi>Apoplexy,</hi> or <hi>Epilepsie,</hi> a little <hi>Impostume</hi> in the Brain, or but a <hi>Rising of the Lights,</hi> (which is as sudden, and as surprising, as either of them,) is as suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient as a Blunderbuss, to kill a Man of sound Health; and to lodge him <hi>ex tempore</hi> in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> or <hi>Hell,</hi> even before he has the leisure to cry for Mercy. And is not That a <hi>Vile Body,</hi> which makes a Man obnoxious to All the Miseries upon Earth, and at last, without Warning, sends him <hi>possibly</hi> to Hell?</p>
               <p>§. 14. Fifthly, 'tis a <hi>Vile Body,</hi> in respect of its <hi>Dissolution;</hi> wherein 'tis so much more noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som than <hi>other</hi> Bodies, that it confessedly stands in need of a <hi>deeper Burial.</hi> For tho' 'tis said, <hi>a Live Dog is better than a Dead Lion;</hi> yet the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:204239:52"/> Body of such a Lion, and most <hi>other</hi> Bodies of other Beasts, are good for something when they are slain; and accordingly yield Mony, alive, or dead. Whereas the Dead Body of <hi>man</hi> is nothing but <hi>Rottenness</hi> and <hi>Stench;</hi> fitly kept under Ground, for fear the Air should be <hi>infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,</hi> and so become unsafe to breath in. The <hi>Worms indeed will feed sweetly on it, (Job</hi> 24. 20.) But hardly any thing else will indure to <hi>touch</hi> it. And is not That a <hi>Vile Body,</hi> but for which we could not <hi>dye,</hi> much less be subject to <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction?</hi> Yes, but we are not yet arriv'd at the utmost Degree of the Body's <hi>Vileness.</hi> For in the <hi>five respects</hi> aforesaid, the Body of Man is not <hi>simply,</hi> but <hi>comparatively</hi> Vile. And so is <hi>Heaven,</hi> which is God's <hi>Throne,</hi> in case we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it with God <hi>Himself.</hi> The Stars of the Firmament are not Pure in <hi>His sight:</hi> In which 'tis <note n="*" place="margin">Isa. 6. 2.</note> said the Flaming <hi>Seraphim</hi> did cover their <hi>Faces,</hi> and their <hi>Feet;</hi> The first importing their <hi>fear</hi> to <hi>see</hi> him, the second their <hi>shame</hi> to be so much as <hi>seen</hi> by him. <hi>Both</hi> expressing, by an <hi>Hebraism,</hi> the <hi>Absolute</hi> Glory of the Creator, and a <hi>Comparative</hi> kind of <hi>Vileness</hi> in all his Creatures. And therefore notwithstanding what I have hitherto said against it, the Body of Man is no otherwise, than <hi>comparatively Vile;</hi> It is not <hi>absolutely</hi> so, because it is of <hi>God's</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:204239:53"/>
                  <hi>making.</hi> For <hi>God saw every thing that he had</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 31.</note>
                  <hi>made, and behold it was very Good.</hi> But nothing is absolutely <hi>Vile,</hi> which is <hi>very good.</hi> From whence it hitherto follows, that our <hi>English</hi> Translation is too severe for the <hi>Original.</hi> It being There, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not our <hi>Vile</hi> Body, but the Body of our <hi>Humility,</hi> or rather of our <hi>Humiliation.</hi> And therefore,</p>
               <p>§. 15. Sixthly, as well to justifie our <hi>English</hi> Translation, as to convince the <hi>Body</hi> of Man of its <hi>Real Vileness;</hi> we must consider it as it is <hi>sullied</hi> with the <hi>leprosie of Sin.</hi> For <hi>That</hi> is it which makes it filthier than <hi>filthy Rags;</hi> It's being put unto the <hi>vilest and filthiest Ʋses.</hi> Our <hi>Body</hi> indeed is extreamly <hi>Vile,</hi> not as <hi>God,</hi> but as <hi>We</hi> have made it. As made by <hi>God,</hi> it is a <hi>Temple,</hi> or <hi>House of Prayer;</hi> We are They who have made it a <hi>Den of Thieves;</hi> A Cage of unclean and filthy Birds; (I mean) of dishonourable and vile Affections. What said St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians? Know ye not that your Bodies are Temples of the Holy Ghost?</hi> 'Tis true, the Body is a <hi>Temple,</hi> as to its primitive Designation; But so much of it is now imploy'd in <hi>making Provision for the Flesh,</hi> (to fulfil the lusts thereof,) that there is hardly room left for <hi>any Sacrifice;</hi> excepting <hi>That</hi> only, which is still <hi>offer'd unto the Belly.</hi> By too much eating, we pervert this primitive
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:204239:53"/> Temple into a Kitchen; by too much drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, into a Cellar; by too much of Both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Sink; by too much <hi>Pride,</hi> 'tis made a Theatre of <hi>Vanity;</hi> and by an excess of <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suality;</hi> a very Charnel-house of <hi>Lust.</hi> In a word, the Devil himself does never <hi>lay siege</hi> unto the <hi>Soul;</hi> He could not <hi>out-wit</hi> or <hi>over-reach</hi> us, did he not <hi>plough with our Heifer;</hi> And did he not <hi>fight</hi> with our <hi>weapons,</hi> He could not <hi>hurt</hi> us. So that the Members of our Bodies are truly <hi>Vile,</hi> in being yielded up <hi>as Instruments of unrighteousness unto Sin:</hi> the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not so properly the <hi>Instruments,</hi> as the <hi>Weapons</hi> of unrighteousness. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 13. And this alone was the <hi>Vileness,</hi> to which the Body of our Saviour could not possibly be obnoxious. He could hunger, and thirst, and weep, and bleed, and faint, and dye, and suffer all our Infirmities, <hi>This one excepted.</hi> This alone was that Vileness, for which St. <hi>Paul</hi> did beat, and buffet, and bring his Body into Subjection. This alone was that Vileness, by which the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the rich Glutton, however cloath'd <hi>in fine linnen,</hi> as well as <hi>Purple,</hi> became incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably <hi>fouler</hi> than that of <hi>Lazarus;</hi> however apparel'd in noysom <hi>Sores.</hi> In that <hi>Parable</hi> of our Saviour, the Body of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> full of Sores, was <hi>clean</hi> enough to be carried <hi>by the Angels</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:204239:54"/> of God into <hi>Abraham's Bosom;</hi> which yet was utterly inaccessible to that of <hi>Dives.</hi> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of which is very obvious. For no man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving can be <hi>really</hi> (that is <hi>morally)</hi> defiled, by what is cast <hi>upon</hi> the Body; nor by what is put <hi>into</hi> it. <hi>But Those things</hi> (saith our Lord) <hi>which proceed out of the mouth, and come forth from the Heart, Those are the things which defile a man:</hi> Matt. 15. 18. <hi>For out of the Heart proceed evil Thoughts, Murders, Adulteries, Fornications, Thefts, False-witness, Blasphemies:</hi> And such as <hi>These</hi> are the Things, by which the <hi>Body</hi> is made <hi>Vile.</hi> (v. 19. &amp; 20.) If <hi>Poverty</hi> in <hi>France</hi> may be called by a Proverb <hi>a kind of Leprosie,</hi> because it is as much <hi>shun'd,</hi> as any Leprosie is, or can be; how much better may we say it touching the <hi>Leprosie of Sin?</hi> which, tho' it is not, yet it <hi>ought</hi> to be, much more loathed. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>if any Brother shall be infected</hi> even to <hi>Scandal,</hi> we may not <hi>sit with him at Meals;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 11. nor so much as <hi>keep him company;</hi> no nor bid him <hi>God speed,</hi> 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3. 14. And such was the Psalmist's Resolution; <hi>I will not sit with vain Persons; I will not have Fellowship with the ungodly. He that telleth Lies shall not tarry in my Sight.</hi> For as the great <hi>Sin of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> is like a <hi>Pest,</hi> so the <hi>Scandalous Sinner</hi> is like a <hi>Pest-house;</hi> not to be <hi>touch't</hi> with a pair
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:204239:54"/> of Tongs; and hardly to be <hi>seen</hi> without an <hi>Amulet.</hi> He who is of a poor and a contrite Spirit, whose <hi>Religion</hi> does not stand in a <hi>form of Godliness</hi> without the <hi>Power,</hi> who <hi>Visits the Fatherless and Widows in their Affliction, and keeps himself unspotted from the World,</hi> has the <hi>cleanest,</hi> and the <hi>purest,</hi> and so the <hi>beautifull'st</hi> Body to be imagin'd. Whereas the Body of the most <hi>delicate Corinthian Harlot</hi> (such as was the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Lais,)</hi> how lovely soever it may appear to a carnal Eye, is nothing better than a <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid,</hi> tho' <hi>painted Sepulchre.</hi> That it appears to be so beautiful, is but a Deception of the sight. For He who cannot see rightly, having his <hi>Eyes</hi> full of <hi>Dirt,</hi> can much less do it, having his <hi>Eyes</hi> full of <hi>Adultery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 16. Now by how much the <hi>Viler</hi> the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Man is, (in this chief Notion of the word <hi>Vile,)</hi> the fitter 'tis to become <hi>fewel for the unclean fire of Hell;</hi> which, as it never <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumes,</hi> so it never <hi>purifies.</hi> And therefore <hi>such</hi> a Vile Body shall only partake of a <hi>Resurrection;</hi> not of that <hi>Blessed Change</hi> which here is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised in the Text. There is a very wide Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the <hi>Twofold Resurrection</hi> in the fifth Chapter of St. <hi>John,</hi> whereof the one is of <hi>Life,</hi> the other of <hi>Damnation.</hi> The <hi>Vilest Body</hi> is good enough, to be cast into a <hi>Lake</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:204239:55"/>
                  <hi>of fire and brimstone:</hi> But to be qualified and fitted for an Inhabitant of Heaven; 'tis plain the Body must be <hi>changed,</hi> as well as <hi>rais'd.</hi> It must be <hi>changed in such a manner,</hi> as to have nothing at all left of its former <hi>Vileness.</hi> It must be <hi>changed</hi> so far forth, as to be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>transfigur'd.</hi> It must be <hi>transfigur'd</hi> in such a manner, as to be <hi>fashioned</hi> or conformed to the <hi>Body</hi> of Christ: and <hi>transfigur'd</hi> in such a <hi>measure,</hi> as to resemble <hi>Christ</hi>'s Body in <hi>point</hi> of <hi>Glory:</hi> Not as it came unto the Earth, but as it <hi>ascended</hi> into <hi>Heaven.</hi> That is the <hi>Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ad quem,</hi> the utmost Point of Perfection, into which our Vile Body shall be Transferr'd; and deserves to be the Subject of our last Consideration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He shall change our Vile Body, that it may be fashioned like unto his glorious Body:</hi> (so the <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <hi>English:)</hi> or He shall <hi>transfigure</hi> the Body of our <hi>Humiliation,</hi> to be made <hi>fashionable</hi> or <hi>conformable</hi> unto the <hi>Body</hi> of his <hi>Glory:</hi> (so the <hi>Greek.)</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:204239:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Touching the</hi> Terminus ad Quem <hi>of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>§. 1. THough <hi>difficult</hi> Subjects are seldom <hi>pleasant;</hi> yet the state of our Bodies from after the Time of their being glorified, must needs be matter of as <hi>pleasant,</hi> as 'tis of <hi>difficult</hi> Consideration. The Consideration must needs be <hi>pleasant,</hi> because 'tis a kind of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possession</hi> of Things <hi>Invisible,</hi> and <hi>future:</hi> It does accelerate our Happiness; It <hi>anticipates,</hi> and <hi>attracts,</hi> and <hi>draws</hi> Heaven towards us; as 'twere <hi>Anticipates</hi> the Performance of the Rich Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of the Gospel; God alone knows <hi>how long,</hi> before they can possibly be accomplish'd. The very <hi>shadow</hi> of <hi>Real</hi> Happiness yields a Man pleasure for a <hi>Season.</hi> And 'tis a <hi>shadow</hi> at least of Happiness, to <hi>Pass by</hi> Heaven in a <hi>Dream;</hi> much more is it to <hi>insist,</hi> and <hi>dwell</hi> upon it by <hi>Contemplation.</hi> If every <hi>Grain</hi> of pure <hi>Gold,</hi> and every <hi>stricture</hi> of perfect <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> may be thought not unworthy of our Consideration; How much more may each <hi>Glimpse</hi> of the <hi>Glory of God?</hi> The utmost Beauty in the Best <hi>Creature,</hi> is <hi>the Beauty of Holiness:</hi> Which yet is but a <hi>faint Ray,</hi> or <hi>humble Deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:204239:56"/> of <hi>God</hi>'s; and every <hi>Flash</hi> of <hi>God</hi>'s Beauty, is more to be valued than all the World. It put St. <hi>Paul</hi> into such a Trance; that He knew not whether his Soul was <hi>in,</hi> or <hi>out</hi> of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 2. He was so absolutely ecstatical, and as it were <hi>out of Himself,</hi> that he seemed unto himself <hi>caught up into Paradise,</hi> (v. 4.) He was so <hi>giddy</hi> as 'twere with Happiness; as that it made him <hi>divinely Mad. Mad</hi> I am bold to say he was, as authorized by Himself, and his own Expression. He tells us he was not <hi>sui Compos;</hi> he could not say he was <hi>Himself.</hi> But yet he was <hi>divinely</hi> such, <hi>(aestro quodam divino percitus,)</hi> because he was able to say for certain, (as soon as he came to Himself again,) that when he was <hi>not Himself,</hi> he was wholly <hi>Christ</hi>'s. And when he was <hi>beside himself,</hi> it was because he was <hi>in Christ.</hi> Thence he spake of Himself, as of quite <hi>Another Creature. I knew a man</hi> (says he) <hi>in Christ, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout</hi> 14. <hi>years ago, (whether in the Body, or out of the Body, I cannot tell, God knows;)</hi> Not a man <hi>in Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,</hi> but a man <hi>in Christ: or transported in a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion by the Spirit of Christ.</hi> For this I take to be the meaning of That Expression. And the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I so take it, because of what is said in the <hi>first</hi> Verse of that Chapter. <hi>It is not expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for me to glory. I will come to Visions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations of the Lord.</hi> To meditate <hi>deeply</hi> upon
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:204239:56"/> Heaven, and on the ravishing <hi>Mansions</hi> prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for us, (in That <hi>House</hi> of our Father which is in Heaven,) is to try before-hand, and to make an Essay, <hi>what it is to be throughly Happy:</hi> and what it was for St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to have been <hi>cast into a Trance.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 22. 6, 7, 17.</note> To have been <hi>snatch't,</hi> or <hi>caught up</hi> into what he calls <hi>Paradise. (Paradise</hi> in one place, <hi>v.</hi> 4. and the <hi>third Heaven</hi> in another, <hi>v.</hi> 2.) As when a Man intends a Voyage to <hi>Spain,</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi> or any other <hi>foreign part,</hi> which he longs to see, he finds it matter of Satisfaction, first to be travelling thither in <hi>Maps,</hi> and in many delicious <hi>medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> loves to be <hi>reading,</hi> and <hi>discoursing,</hi> and <hi>thinking</hi> of it; goes all over it in his <hi>Wishes;</hi> prepossesseth it in his <hi>Hopes;</hi> and makes it <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent</hi> unto himself in his <hi>Contemplations;</hi> so with a greater force of reason, It is to every Real Christian the greatest Happiness upon Earth, to be able to <hi>Think</hi> himself to Heaven; to <hi>gaze</hi> upon God with the <hi>Eye and Telescope of Faith;</hi> as 'tis the <hi>Evidence of things not seen;</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (as 'tis said of the Patriarchs,) <hi>to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him from a far off,</hi> in the <hi>Arms</hi> of <hi>Hope,</hi> and <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 13.</note>
                  <hi>Expectation.</hi> For <hi>Ʋs</hi> to <hi>remember him in our Beds, and think upon him when we are waking,</hi> (as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> speaks;) for our <hi>Spirits to thirst,</hi> and for our <hi>Flesh to long after him;</hi> yea for <hi>our Souls to hang</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 63. 2, 7, 9.</note>
                  <hi>upon him,</hi> (All which are the Expressions of the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:204239:57"/> 63. Psalm,) as it were <hi>cleaving</hi> to him in love, and <hi>holding him fast</hi> with divine Affection; what else can This be, but even <hi>to go out of our selves?</hi> to be <hi>snatch'd</hi> or <hi>caught up</hi> (with St. <hi>Paul)</hi> into <hi>Paradise?</hi> For where can any Man more properly be said to be, than in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>place of his Conversation?</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> says expresly, in the next Verse before my Text, <hi>Our Conversation is in Heaven; from whence we look for the Saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ.</hi> It must be therefore a great Accession unto the faint measure of Happiness which now we have, to be profoundly made sensible of the full measure of Happiness which here we hope for. Men esteem themselves Rich in a good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, when, though at <hi>present</hi> they have but <hi>little,</hi> they have yet the <hi>Reversion</hi> of great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues. And as 'tis an honour to our Bodies in their present state of <hi>Vileness,</hi> that they are capable of a <hi>Change,</hi> or a <hi>Glorisication;</hi> so we <hi>dispel</hi> the <hi>black Vapours</hi> which may arise from our <hi>Thinking</hi> on what we <hi>Are,</hi> by our most serious <hi>Apprehension</hi> of what we <hi>shall</hi> be.</p>
               <p>§. 2. But, as the state of our <hi>Bodies</hi> from af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the time of their being <hi>Glorified,</hi> is to every faithful Christian a matter of <hi>Pleasant</hi> Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; so is its <hi>pleasantness</hi> much <hi>abated</hi> by the <hi>Difficulty</hi> we find in our Thoughts about it.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:204239:57"/> For St. <hi>John</hi> tells us expresly, that tho' <hi>we are Now the Sons of God; It doth not yet appear what</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 2.</note>
                  <hi>we shall be. This indeed</hi> (saith He) <hi>we know, that when he shall appear, we shall be like him; for we shall see him as he is.</hi> We know already <hi>in Thesi,</hi> we shall be <hi>like</hi> him; (that's true e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough;) But <hi>in Hypothesi, what it is</hi> to be like him; or <hi>how far forth</hi> we shall be like him; is a thing <hi>we know not.</hi> We know that <hi>when Christ who is our life shall appear, we also shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with him in Glory: Col.</hi> 3. 4. When we shall come to be <hi>uncloathed,</hi> to <hi>be cloathed upon with an house from heaven,</hi> we know our <hi>Souls</hi> shall be <hi>apparell'd</hi> with <hi>new-fashion'd Bodies;</hi> and that the <hi>fashion</hi> of our Bodies shall be the same that is <hi>worn</hi> by <hi>Christ;</hi> who shall <hi>change our Vile</hi> Bodies, and <hi>fashion</hi> them like unto his <hi>Glorious Body.</hi> But for the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Degree</hi> of the Glory of Christ's Body, That remains a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a difficult thing to be understood; or rather not so <hi>difficult,</hi> as <hi>incomprehensible.</hi> Our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course in This case must be to rational <hi>Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures;</hi> and those Conjectures are to be made by what we find in God's Word of the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Christ.</hi> (Not from <hi>Aristotle,</hi> or <hi>Plato,</hi> or meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly human Reason;) For such as is, in point of Quality, the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>His</hi> Glory; such the word of God has promised shall be <hi>our own.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:204239:58"/> opposites put together do help to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate one another, let us consider the <hi>Body of Christ</hi> in the lowest pitch of its <hi>Abasement,</hi> and observe in what measure 'twas glorious <hi>Then;</hi> before we judg of the same in its <hi>Exaltation.</hi> For,</p>
               <p>§. 3. During the Time of His <hi>Mortality,</hi> (whilst yet <hi>he emptied himself of Glory,)</hi> his Body was <hi>Glorious</hi> in This respect, that indeed <hi>it was full</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 1. 14.</note>
                  <hi>of Grace.</hi> For Grace is the Preamble of Glory; the Life of Grace is a <hi>Preface</hi> or <hi>Introduction</hi> to That of Glory. <hi>When the Word was made Flesh, and dwelt among us;</hi> his Flesh in <hi>This</hi> respect was <hi>glorious,</hi> that it was pure, and spotless, and as immaculate as <hi>a</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vers. 36.</note>
                  <hi>Lamb:</hi> yes and in this respect also, that it was able to work wonders; as being sometimes <hi>Invisible;</hi> sometimes walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Sea; sometimes curing the most inveterate Diseases, sometimes raising up the Dead; sometimes over-ruling and casting out Devils; once communicating Vertue to the <hi>Hem of his Garment;</hi> which when a Woman had but touch't, He found that <hi>Vertue</hi> was gone out of him; and <hi>she was healed in that very</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 9. 20.</note>
                  <hi>Instant.</hi> Let us go but a step higher, I mean to <hi>Mount Tabor;</hi> and we shall find him <hi>Transfigur'd</hi> in such a manner, <hi>that his Face did shine as the Sun, and his very Raiment was white as the light.</hi> Let <note place="margin">Matt. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> us advance higher yet, from Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> unto
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:204239:58"/> Mount <hi>Sion;</hi> where <hi>(having purged our Sins)</hi> He sate down on the right <hi>hand of the Majesty on high;</hi> and there (if we can) let us imagin, how <hi>bright</hi> his Body must needs be, who Himself is <hi>the Brightness of his Father's Glory, and the express Image of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 3.</note> Here it may therefore be fitly argued <hi>à Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nori ad Majus,</hi> If his <hi>Body</hi> was so <hi>Glorious</hi> whilst here upon Earth, whilst he was yet but in his <hi>Nadir,</hi> his state of <hi>Exinanition;</hi> what must the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of it be in his <hi>Apogaeum?</hi> now that his Body is in its <hi>Zenith,</hi> the utmost pitch of its sublimity? To say <hi>it shines as the Sun,</hi> is a poor Expression; for so it did on Mount <hi>Tabor.</hi> To speak it glorious as the <hi>light,</hi> is at least as short, and an arrant <hi>Meiosis;</hi> for so was the <hi>Garment</hi> of his Body upon the very same Mount. It must content us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to say, (with St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,)</hi> that <hi>now we know but in part;</hi> only This is our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that <hi>when That which is perfect is come, then</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 9, 10.</note>
                  <hi>that which is in part shall be done away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 4. Come we now in the next place from our <hi>Lord</hi>'s Body, unto <hi>our own.</hi> Which that 'twill cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be <hi>transfigur'd,</hi> as well as <hi>rais'd,</hi> is told us expresly in This Text, and deducible from the words wherewith St. <hi>John</hi> declares his <hi>VISION. I saw</hi> (saith He) <hi>a new Heaven, and a new Earth:</hi> (Rev. 21. 1.) <hi>and he who sate upon the Throne, said, Behold, I make all things new.</hi> (v. 5.) Nor can we
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:204239:59"/> think that <hi>our Bodies</hi> shall alone remain <hi>Old,</hi> when <hi>all things else</hi> are made <hi>New,</hi> both Heaven, and Earth. No, they shall be so <hi>renew'd,</hi> and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner so amazing, that being <hi>sown in Corruption, they shall be raised in Incorruption; being sown in Disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, they shall be raised again in Glory; being sown here in weakness, they shall be raised again in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer;</hi> and being but <hi>Natural</hi> Bodies <hi>Now,</hi> they shall be then <hi>Spiritualiz'd.</hi> In a word, <hi>This Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 43, 44, 53.</note>
                  <hi>must put on Incorruption; and this Mortal must put on Immortality.</hi> And this we are told by That Apostle, who was <hi>caught up to the</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 2, 4.</note>
                  <hi>Third Heaven:</hi> Nay, we are told farther yet, <hi>By the only begotten of the Father, who came from Heaven, that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 43. Dan. 12. 3.</note>
                  <hi>the Righteous</hi> (in That Day) <hi>shall shine forth as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi> As the Sun in point of <hi>Quality;</hi> but far <hi>more</hi> glorious in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</hi> For the Sun which is at present so far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced over our Heads, will <hi>then</hi> be dignified enough, in being as far under our Feet. The Light St. <hi>Paul</hi> saw on <hi>Earth,</hi> was <hi>above</hi> the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Sun; not only <hi>equall'd,</hi> but <hi>excell'd</hi> it, <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 13. What then would he have seen, had he been in <hi>Heaven?</hi> when we hereafter shall have heard the beatifick Invitation of God the Son, <hi>[Come ye blessed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you, enter ye into the Joy of your Lord,]</hi> we shall <hi>look down</hi> upon the <hi>Sun,</hi> as a Thing <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:204239:59"/> us; and below us in <hi>lustre,</hi> as well as <hi>Place.</hi> For we shall see <hi>the Face of God;</hi> and whilst we <hi>see,</hi> we shall be <hi>like</hi> him. This is Glory in its Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, for the Righteous man to shine like the <hi>Sun of Righteousness;</hi> in comparison with whom, the <hi>Created Sun of Nature,</hi> is but as <hi>Sackcloth.</hi> And here again we may argue <hi>à minori ad majus,</hi> If the <hi>Face</hi> even of <hi>Moses</hi> did so exceedingly shine forth by seeing God in Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> that He was fain to wear a <hi>Veil</hi> when he went again down to his people <hi>Israel;</hi> and if the Face of St. <hi>Stephen</hi> (even in the Eyes of his bitter Enemies) was like the Face of <hi>an Angel,</hi> before <hi>he saw the Heavens</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 6. 15. &amp; Ch. 7. v. 55, 58.</note>
                  <hi>opened, and Jesus standing on the right hand of God;</hi> How much more shall <hi>we</hi> shine, (on a supposal of our being Sons of God,) when we shall <hi>drink of His Fulness,</hi> to whom the <hi>Sun</hi> in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is but a <hi>shadow?</hi> Even a <hi>Candle</hi> in a dark Night is so <hi>glorious a Body,</hi> as to make in some measure a kind of <hi>Artificial Day,</hi> whilst it <hi>illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates</hi> the <hi>Medium</hi> through which we <hi>see:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the same Candle at <hi>Noon,</hi> when the Sun be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>Vertical,</hi> waxeth so Vile, and insignificant, so far from <hi>helping</hi> us to <hi>see,</hi> that 'tis hardly so much as <hi>seen.</hi> So tho' the <hi>Sun,</hi> when he is <hi>culmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> does even <hi>dazle</hi> us with his brightness, whilst we inhabit <hi>Vile</hi> Bodies, and our Foundation is in the <hi>Dust,</hi> yet when our Bodies shall be made <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly;</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:204239:60"/> when Christ shall <hi>change</hi> our vile Bodies, and <hi>fashion them like unto his glorious Body;</hi> Then the <hi>Sun</hi> will gather <hi>blackness,</hi> and be in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a <hi>Cloud.</hi> For so <hi>dazling</hi> is the Glory of the Lord God of Hosts, to whatsoever Glory it is which is <hi>less than Infinite;</hi> that we may say with the Psalmist in This Sense also, <hi>Clouds and Darkness are round about him.</hi> So very far does the Creator out-shine his Creatures; that as shadows are to pictures, and Foils to Diamonds, and Clouds to the Sun, so the Sun, and the Moon, and All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Luminaries of Heaven, are but as <hi>Clouds,</hi> and thick <hi>Mists</hi> in the sight of <hi>God. Clouds and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness are round about him, tho' righteousness and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are the habitation of his Seat.</hi> We have it from St. <hi>John</hi> in his <hi>Revelations,</hi> that the Sun in God's presence does <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 22. 5.</note> cease to shine; after the manner of a Candle in the presence of the Sun: Or rather as a Glow-worm does cease to shine at Noon-day. Now <hi>This we know</hi> (saith St. <hi>John)</hi> supposing our selves the Sons of God, that <hi>when he shall appear, we shall be like him.</hi> And that for this reason, <hi>because we shall see him as He is.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the same purpose: <hi>Now we see through a Glass, darkly; But Then face to face: Now we know only in part; who then shall know, even as</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 12.</note>
                  <hi>also we are known.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 5. But what is the Reason of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:204239:60"/> that <hi>we shall he therefore like him, because we shall see him as he Is?</hi> The plain reason is, because the <hi>Reflexion</hi> of his Beauty shall be <hi>imprinted</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our persons, whilst we <hi>behold</hi> him. For every Subject which is made capable, (as Then the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Man will be,) does receive the very Image of That which sees it; as well as the Image of what it sees. As for <hi>Example;</hi> or to speak more exactly, for <hi>Illustration,</hi> (since <hi>no Example</hi> can be given of such a Beatifick Vision as now we speak of;) when we look upon a Glass, which by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Polite,</hi> but not <hi>transparent,</hi> reflects the Image of our persons, 'Tis called a <hi>Looking-Glass</hi> very fitly; because in our <hi>looking</hi> upon <hi>It,</hi> It seems to be <hi>looking</hi> upon <hi>Ʋs</hi> too. Face does so answer Face, in point of Motion, form, and figure; that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly such as we are, (whether fair, or foul,) even such a True Glass will represent us. Yet every Glass is not a Mirroir: For we look through it, if pellucid; and if lucid but unpolish'd, we look upon it as on a <hi>Wall;</hi> or any other <hi>Opaque Body.</hi> But when there is quick-silver on one side, and politure on the other; Then to look upon the Glass, is to beget ones own <hi>likeness</hi> by its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion. The like to which may be said (and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps with greater fitness) of the Sun shining up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a River; which being clear, and deep enough, becomes as a Looking-Glass to the Sun. The
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:204239:61"/> Sun, if he had Eyes, might see his <hi>Face</hi> in that River; I mean the Reflexion, or Image of it.</p>
               <p>§. 6. Apply we This now (with fear and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and as far as lawfully we may,) to the Case in hand. When God Almighty shall appear after the general Resurrection, and we together with Him in Glory; we shall not be able to look on God, without his looking upon us too; For so whosoever eyes the Sun, must have the Sun in his eye; and so we may be to one another, at once the Object, and Agent too. As when any two Men do mutually gaze on each others eyes, they do project each others Face to and fro at the same Instant. Now our Persons in Heaven will be so polished, <hi>(when this Corruptible shall have put on Incorruption,)</hi> that we shall be in respect of <hi>God,</hi> what Looking-Glasses are in respect of <hi>Ʋs;</hi> we receiving <hi>his</hi> likeness, as they do <hi>ours.</hi> We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting His <hi>Beauty,</hi> as they do our <hi>wants</hi> of it. We shall be Mirroirs exactly made; a kind of Looking-glasses with Eyes; whilst by <hi>seeing</hi> as we are <hi>seen,</hi> and <hi>representing</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> of what we <hi>see,</hi> we shall therefore be <hi>like</hi> unto God himself, because <hi>we shall see him as he Is.</hi> This is what I have to say of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Expression.</p>
               <p>§. 7. But if to <hi>look</hi> upon God, is to be <hi>like</hi> him, (some may tacitly here object,) not only <hi>We,</hi> but <hi>All things else</hi> shall be like him, on which his
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:204239:61"/> Glory shall be objected. To which I answer, <hi>it does not follow:</hi> For every object is not capable of Reflexion. Diaphanous Bodies (as the Air) do not terminate, but transmit our Rayes. Nor is every Reflexion of the same <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Degree.</hi> For tho' the Beams of the Sun may be reflected from a <hi>Dunghill;</hi> they cannot be <hi>so,</hi> as from a <hi>Diamond.</hi> The more excellent the object, the more of Glory it will receive. Here our Eyes are but <hi>earthy;</hi> and tho' <hi>Refined</hi> earth indeed, yet they are but <hi>once refined:</hi> And by reason of that, (we being now drawn to the Dregs of Nature,) we cannot well <hi>look</hi> upon the <hi>Sun,</hi> unless it be through a <hi>Veil.</hi> Much less are we able to see the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> without the Ruin of the Organ by which we see. This the <hi>Heathens</hi> represented by the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginary meeting of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Semele.</hi> But <hi>we</hi> are taught more exactly by the stupendous (tho' Real) Interview, of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Moses. I beseech thee</hi> (said <hi>Moses</hi> to God himself) <hi>shew me thy Glory.</hi> To <note place="margin">Exod. 33. 18.</note> whom God answer'd, <hi>Thou canst not see my Face; for there shall no man see my Face and live. When my Glory passeth by, I will put thee in a Cleft of the Rock, and I will cover thee with my Hand whilst I pass by. And I will take away my hand, and thou shalt see my Back-parts, but my Face shall not be seen.</hi> A passage of Scripture, which stands in great need of an Explication, as being wholly
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:204239:62"/> spoken by the figure <hi>Anthropopathia;</hi> wherein the <hi>Face of Jehovah</hi> imports the <hi>Causes and Reasons</hi> of God's dispensing his Benefits and Blessings to us; and these are known to <hi>God only.</hi> But the <hi>Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts</hi> seem to signifie the <hi>Blessings and Benefits Themselves,</hi> whereby we <hi>see</hi> Him, who is <hi>Invisible,</hi> in his <hi>effects.</hi> (as <hi>the Heavens declare the Glory of God, and the Firmament sheweth his handy-work.)</hi> Nor do we <hi>see</hi> only <hi>hear</hi> of his wonderous works, but do every day <hi>taste</hi> of his Goodness to us. 'Tis the expression of Holy <hi>David,</hi> speaking of God in his Effects to the Sons of Men. We see our Bodies are <hi>here</hi> so vile, that our Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are destroyable by the Transcendency of their Objects. And tho' we hope to <hi>live</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after <hi>by seeing</hi> God; yet whilst we are groveling here below, <hi>'tis Death to see him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 8. From hence we may make a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, how far our Bodies must be <hi>changed</hi> in the general Resurrection, as well as <hi>rais'd.</hi> Our Eyes must be changed in such a measure of strength and Brightness, as to be able to see our Maker without a skreen, or a Partition. All our Organs must be proportion'd to the Transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of their objects, that the Exuberances of Glory may not be able to overcome them; and that the same, <hi>in that Day,</hi> may become a <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisick,</hi> which would be <hi>now</hi> a <hi>Destructive</hi> Vision.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:204239:62"/> A little wind (we all know) will <hi>fill</hi> the Sails of a little Boat; when a great deal will <hi>over-turn</hi> it. A little Dose of the Grand <hi>Elixir</hi> will quicken a Man when he is dying; when the same <hi>over-dosed</hi> will but kill him with a Recovery. They say the Cataracts of <hi>Nile,</hi> which may be heard many Miles off, are much too loud to be heard at hand. They whom they deafen, cannot perceive such un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionable Noises. For <hi>Sensibile supra senso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium tollit sensationem.</hi> As when a Book of any writing is brought too near to a Man's eye, he is not able to read a Line. So a Competent Light does <hi>refresh</hi> our eyes; when too much of it does but <hi>annoy</hi> them. The <hi>Sun</hi> is but a <hi>dim</hi> thing, in comparison with its <hi>Creator;</hi> and yet it has a Brightness will strike us blind: <hi>Suntque oculis Tenebrae prae tanto Lumine obortae.</hi> Even Darkness is the Product of too much Light. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Eyes must needs receive such an unspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Alteration, when we come to appear face to face before God; as that we may <hi>live,</hi> and be made <hi>happy,</hi> by the <hi>sight</hi> of That Glory, which now would <hi>kill</hi> us by being <hi>seen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 9. Of the many momentous <hi>Lessons</hi> which may be drawn from This Doctrine, let us content our selves with such, as are <hi>short,</hi> and <hi>obvious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First if our Bodies are here so <hi>Vile,</hi> as in seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral respects they have been made appear to be;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:204239:63"/> then let us not value them over-much; let us not love them over-dearly; let us not carry our selves towards them with over-much fondness and delectation. Let us not hate our own flesh, nor yet be amorous of its features; or foolishly indulgent to its Desires. Let us love it in such a manner, as we are bound to love our <hi>Children;</hi> so far forth as to <hi>correct</hi> it, and keep it carefully in <hi>Subjection.</hi> Nothing can be <hi>truer</hi> than that of <hi>Solomon;</hi> and nothing more of use to our present purpose. <hi>He that spareth his Rod, hateth his Child;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 24.</note>
                  <hi>But He that loveth him, chastizeth him betimes.</hi> It is as much a Parent's Duty, to give his Child due <hi>Correction;</hi> as <hi>Food,</hi> and <hi>Rayment.</hi> The <hi>later</hi> being no more needful unto the <hi>Being</hi> of a Child, than the <hi>former</hi> to his <hi>well Being.</hi> For want of the former more especially, the fruit of a Man's Body tends to the Ruin of a Man's Soul. Nor is he said with more Truth to be the <hi>Father</hi> of his <hi>Child,</hi> than he is of his Child's <hi>Destruction.</hi> Is there any Ground so good, as to need no weeding? or will it bring forth Corn enough, without the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of the Plough? No, there's so <hi>much</hi> of a <hi>Brute Beast,</hi> in the best of Flesh and Blood, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Nature, as many times to stand in need of a very strong <hi>Bridle;</hi> and as many times pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly of a very sharp <hi>Spur.</hi> Now this Comparison is to inform us, with what a <hi>severe,</hi> but <hi>wholesom</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:204239:63"/> kindness, we ought to love our own <hi>flesh</hi> in its state of <hi>Vileness;</hi> to make it capable and fit for a state of <hi>Glory:</hi> We must strictly watch over it; and keep it within an hourly Discipline. If we find it grows <hi>Idle;</hi> we must be <hi>Taskmasters</hi> to it, and make it work for its living. If we find it <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctant,</hi> and loth to <hi>labour;</hi> we must feed it for a while with the Bread of <hi>Scarceness,</hi> and beget in it an <hi>Appetite,</hi> to make it capable of more. If we find it grows <hi>wanton</hi> with too good usage; we must carry a <hi>strict hand</hi> over it. We must take St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Rod,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, so beat the Body <hi>black</hi> and <hi>blue,</hi> (for that is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word,) as to keep it <hi>under,</hi> and at <hi>Command.</hi> Whether by fasting, or watching, or other austere Administrations; as Reason shall dictate, and need require. As Vile a Body as it is, we must not let it want any thing, which we find by experience will do it good; whether it be for its <hi>Incouragement,</hi> or for the keeping of it in <hi>Awe.</hi> We must allow it its Times of <hi>Pleasure,</hi> when we think it may tend to its greater <hi>profit;</hi> I mean to its <hi>proficiency</hi> in the doing <hi>God Service.</hi> As there is sure to be a time when we must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily <hi>punish,</hi> so there <hi>may</hi> be a Time to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it</hi> also. For tho' the Body of a Man is the <hi>worst Master in the world;</hi> yet being well disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin'd, 'twill make a <hi>very good Mule;</hi> by patiently
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:204239:64"/> bearing any Burden, which our heavenly Lord and Master shall lay upon it; whether it be the <hi>Yoke,</hi> or the <hi>Cross</hi> of Christ. And therefore the Beast must have its Provender, that it may not <hi>sink</hi> under its <hi>Load.</hi> But still we must have it in our Remembrance; that God appointed the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> to be its <hi>Rider.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</q>
               <p>As the College of <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> (however they were Heathens) were taught to teach us. We must not therefore, even for shame, permit the <hi>Soul</hi> to hold the <hi>stirrup,</hi> whilst the <hi>Vile Body</hi> of our Affections (the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle</hi> words it,) hath unworthily leave given it to mount the <hi>Saddle.</hi> 'Tis true the Flesh must be kept as clean and sweet, as it is possible; and nourished for <hi>labour,</hi> tho' not for <hi>Lust.</hi> But still the <hi>Cost,</hi> and the <hi>Care,</hi> must be proportioned unto its <hi>Vileness.</hi> The Back and Belly must not put us to unproportionable <hi>Charges;</hi> tho' the one must have <hi>food,</hi> and the other <hi>rayment.</hi> Having these two, <hi>Let us therewith be content,</hi> saith St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <note place="margin">1 Tim. 9. 8.</note>
                  <hi>Timothy.</hi> The shortest way and the surest to les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen the <hi>Vileness</hi> of the Body, and withall to make it fit for a <hi>glorious Change,</hi> is both to <hi>feed</hi> it and to <hi>cloath</hi> it with the <hi>Body of Christ.</hi> First to <hi>feed</hi> it. <hi>For his Flesh is meat indeed, Joh.</hi> 6. 55. So said he touching himself, who is himself <hi>the Bread of</hi>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:204239:64"/>
                  <hi>life which came down from Heaven.</hi> (v. 50.) Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly to cloath it. <hi>Put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ;</hi> (said our Apostle to the Christians who dwelt at <hi>Rome.) That is provision for the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 14.</note>
                  <hi>Spirit;</hi> to <hi>feed</hi> upon Christ, is to <hi>put him on.</hi> But to <hi>make any for the Flesh,</hi> for the <hi>fulfilling</hi> of its <hi>Lusts,</hi> and the gratification of its Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; is so to provide for the <hi>Vile Body,</hi> as to render it so much the <hi>Viler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 10. But pass we onwards from the first to the second Use of this Doctrin. For seeing whatsoever the Body <hi>shall</hi> be, It is at <hi>present</hi> exceeding <hi>Vile;</hi> we must not stand in <hi>fear of Them who can destroy the Body only, but are not able to hurt the Soul.</hi> We must only fear <hi>Him, who is able to cast both Soul and Body into Hell.</hi> It is not Vile only in This, that it was taken out of the Dust; and is a Nursery of Diseases; and fit for nothing after Death, unless to be cast unto the Dunghill; (if at least it is fit for That;) But it has a <hi>Moral</hi> Vileness; a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Leprosie of Sin; which makes it liable to the Death which is call'd <hi>Damnation:</hi> And who would care to be bereav'd of such a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicable Body, as is not worthy the Preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? or having a just Ground of Hope, that the Vile Body shall be <hi>Changed;</hi> and changed for the better in all respects; and so <hi>ineffably</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:204239:65"/> for the better, as that we shall injoy an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passibility of our <hi>Senses;</hi> a <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 43.</note> Spirituality of our members; an imperceptibility of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; an impeccability of our Affections; a strange immensity of our Knowledge; and an eternity of our Duration; Who would not say of his Destroyers, in case of Martyrdom for Christ, and the Christian Faith; what <hi>Socrates</hi> said heartily touching his <hi>Anytus,</hi> and <hi>Melitus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Arrian. Epict. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 29.</note>
                  <hi>Kill us they may, but they cannot hurt us?</hi> Who would not be <hi>contented,</hi> with what St. <hi>Paul</hi> was <hi>desirous</hi> of? <hi>to be dissolv'd, and to be with Christ?</hi> Who would grumble or repine at his being <hi>uncloath'd</hi> on a good account, when St. Paul <hi>groaned earnestly,</hi> to be <hi>cloathed upon with an house from Heaven?</hi> and when the later can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had, without the former? For <hi>Death</hi> is the <hi>Door</hi> to a Life of Glory. Immortality cannot <hi>begin,</hi> till this Life is <hi>ended.</hi> Nor is it said by St. <hi>John</hi> in his Revelation, <hi>Blessed are the Living,</hi> who live in Plenty, and Pleasure, and great Applause; But <hi>Blessed are the Dead who die in the Lord.—</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 13.</note>
                  <q>
                     <l>—ultima semper</l>
                     <l>Expectanda dies esto; dicique Beatus</l>
                     <l>Ante obitum Nemo, suprema{que} funera debet.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:204239:65"/> There are so many things do happen between the Cup and the Lip, that no Man living can imagin what a Day may bring forth. Nor can he call his life happy, until he knows how he shall dye. Who would not then be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented <hi>to sowe in Tears,</hi> upon condition of an assurance <hi>to reap in Joy?</hi> Who would not think it an easie Cross, for a Christian (whilst he is here) <hi>to go on his way weeping,</hi> that he may <hi>come again with Joy, and bring his sheaves with him?</hi> Who would not say with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jonah, it is better for me to dye than to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jonah 4. 3.</note>
                  <hi>live?</hi> And with the Royal Ecclesiastes, <hi>The Day of Death is more precious, than the day of ones Birth; It is better to go into the house of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 7. 1, 2, 3, 8.</note>
                  <hi>Mourning, than to abide in the house of Mirth; Sorrow is better than laughter; and better is the End of a thing, than the Beginning;</hi> who (I say) would not close with all These Paradoxes in Scripture, whose <hi>Conversation here is such, as becomes the Gospel?</hi> And to which he knows is <note place="margin">Philip. 1. 27.</note> consequent <hi>a Crown of Righteousness laid up?</hi> That is the word of our Apostle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>henceforth is laid up for me, &amp;c. laid up safely,</hi> as in a <hi>Treasury</hi> of all good things; concerning which St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith, (with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Esa,) Eye hath not seen, nor Ear heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath the heart of man been ever able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isai. 64. 4. Philip. 2. 9.</note>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:204239:66"/> (and much less the <hi>Tongue</hi> to utter,) <hi>the things which God hath prepared for Them that love him.</hi> Who then would place his whole Felicity in a <hi>Valley of Tears,</hi> and in the miser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Contentments of outward Sense, like <hi>Esau</hi> in the <hi>old</hi> Testament, and like <hi>Dives</hi> in the <hi>New,</hi> when with <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Lazarus,</hi> he may be lodged by the Angels in <hi>Abraham's Bosom?</hi> where <hi>God shall wipe away all Tears from our</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 21. 4. Psal. 16. 11.</note>
                  <hi>Eyes;</hi> where <hi>Joy</hi> will shew it self in its <hi>fulness;</hi> and where <hi>there will be pleasures for evermore;</hi> where <hi>Jesus Christ the faithful witness, the first begotten of the Dead, who hath loved us</hi> and washed <hi>us from our Sins in his own blood, shall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 6.</note>
                  <hi>make us all Kings and Priests unto God and his Father;</hi> shall <hi>cloath</hi> us all in <hi>white Robes;</hi> and put his <hi>Palmes into our hands;</hi> and having swallow'd up Death in Victory, shall teach us to sing an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, even a <hi>New</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 5. 9, 13. &amp; 7. 9, 10.</note>
                  <hi>Song</hi> of Triumph, <hi>Salvation unto our God; for thou wast Slain, and hast redeemed us to God, by thy blood. Blessing, honour, glory, and power, to him that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:204239:66"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>